<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Syn theōi en christōi the ansvvere to the preface of the Rhemish Testament. By T. Cartwright.</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843376</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843376</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1092:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Syn theōi en christōi the ansvvere to the preface of the Rhemish Testament. By T. Cartwright.</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64, 81-213, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue, printer to the Kings Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602. Cum priuilegio regio.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An answer to the preface of: The New Testament of Jesus Christ. Rheims: John Foguy, 1582.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  English. --  Douay. --  1582 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  English --  Versions. --  Douay --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> THE ANSVVERE TO THE <hi>PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FACE OF THE</hi> RHEMISH <hi>Testament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> T. Cartwright.</p>
            <p>AT EDINBVRGH <hi>PRINTED BY RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> Walde-graue, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Kings <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie.</hi> 1602.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio Regio.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8106:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8106:2"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Th'anſwere to the preface of &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the ſix firſt ſections page</hi> 1. 2. &amp; 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE true religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like the heauenlie bodies which neuer change: the Popiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion reſembleth the earth, which as the potters claye is readie to receaue any forme, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the wind and weather, times and ſeaſons of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare, winter or ſommer, ſpring or fall wil ſet vpon it. Hereof it is that they which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme did ſo deadly hate the inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the youth, in the groundes &amp; principles of religion; that they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8106:3"/> coulde not heare the worde of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme with patient eares: nowe in feare of a generall falling from them through opinion either of their blockiſh ignoraunce or ſluggiſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence; are conſtrayned both to write and teach their Catechiſmes. Out of the ſame feare it riſeth, that they which hitherto coulde not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the holie ſcriptures to be red of the people, in their mother tongue: nowe leaſte they ſhoulde vtterlie fall from the hope of their gaine, throgh a vehement ſuſpition of jugling and playing vnder the boarde with the people: and conſtrayned to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe a printe of that, which they ſometimes burned, and praetend al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of that, which in times paſt they condemned. Howbeit th'eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the trueth hauing theſe Church robbers vpon the rack: ſee notwith-ſtanding how hardlie they are gotten to confeſſe the trueth, &amp; how they lyſp it, rather then ſpeake it out. For heere they confeſſe that <hi>th' Armenians, Gotthes, Italians, French</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:8106:3"/> and <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> had either ſome part or the whole of the ſcriptures tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into their own tongues. But they will not grant it of the <hi>Slauoies;</hi> which notwithſtanding is moſt euident, not onely by the words of <hi>Ierome,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that he <hi>gaue to his own nation a tranſlation moſt diligently ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded:</hi> but by certaine of their own Doctors, from whom th'euidence of <hi>Ieromes</hi> wordes<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſius d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Saecro verbo Vernac, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo. Alfonſus d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Haereſ. lib.</hi> 1. c. 13</note> doth wring foorth the confeſsion of the trueth in this behalfe. But what needeth all this niceneſſe; when it is euident that in the elder and purer times, the ſcriptures were tranſlated <hi>into innumerable,</hi> yea to <hi>all tongues vſual amongſt men.</hi> In the latter times of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Ioh. homil. 1 Theodoret. de corrig. Graecorum affect. lib. 5.</note> it is not ſhewed, that there were ſuch tranſlations eſpecially in England: where the Ieſuites doe foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, that there was a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in our tongue alowed, becauſe the counſell prouideth that none ſhould be permitted, but that which was <hi>allowed by the Dioceſane.</hi> And if ther were any; yet it being kept cloſe priſoner, that it coulde neither come
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8106:4"/> to the people, nor the people to it: it is all one in this queſtion, whether there were none, or no vſe of them. And if they both were, and were v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: yet for ſo much as, by their owne confeſsion, they were permitted to wring out of the peoples handes the tranſlation whereby the Popiſh Church was beſieged: it is euident, that you permit it not either in reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the holy ſcriptures, or loue to the people; but rather as deſperat enemies, which had rather kill with it, then that the head of your gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full errors ſhould bee ſtriken of by it. And it fareth altogether with you in this poynt, as with men which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a naturall hatred of cheeſe, or ſome ſuch foode, in ſuch ſorte as the verie ſight or touch of it doth offend them: yet being effamiſhed, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for the ſafetie of their liues euen to eate it. For abhorring from the ſcriptures in time of your peace: when it commeth that you and your ſtate is plunged by ſuch as you call <hi>baeretickes;</hi> you are glade to bite or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8106:4"/> nibble vpon the ſcriptures, if happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie you can get any thing to ſerue the praeſent neede. But tell vs (go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſirs) is the reading of the ſcriptures by the people, like vnto Strawberies, that ar good onelye in ſome ſeaſon of the yeare? is it phyſick whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men are ſick and not meate when they be whole? is it triacle to driue out poyſon, and not praeſeruatiue to keepe from it? hath it ſtrength to put the enemie to flight, and hath it none to hinder his approch? finally is it good to weede, &amp; not to plant? The contrary where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is rather true. For if it be able to heale a ſicke man, it is much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keepe him whole which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie in health: &amp; if it be meete to giue light to the ſimple, when the heauens are ouercaſt with the miſt and cloud of haereſie; it is much more forcible to ſhew the way, when they are not ſo clouded. It is therefore a ſottiſh diſtinction which the Ieſuites vſe, in making the peoples reading of the Scripture dangerous in tyme <hi>of peace,</hi> and profitable when th'ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8106:5"/> (by haereſie) hath made a broyle. How beit admitting that the peoples harueſt of reading the Scripture, is onely in foule weather: how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth it to paſſe, that you haue not wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh fortie yeares long, wherein the goſpell after a dead winter hath beene greene and floriſhed againe in our country, and wherein the <hi>Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call tranſlations</hi> (as you call them) haue filled the land: procured that this ſickle of your tranſlation, might be in the hands of the people; therby to get them ſo much grain, as might haue fed them in this dearth of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and other ſuch ſwill and ſwaddes as you were wont to fill them with? Wherefore the people maye well ſee<note place="margin">Tranquillus.</note> that as vnto <hi>Vitellius,</hi> the dead citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen was alwayes of good ſauour; ſo vnto you, the dead &amp; carcaſed ſoules are of pleaſant ſmell. But let vs come vnto the groundes of this difference of the peoples reading of ſcriptures, which they haue ſet in the forefront of the praeface. The firſt is, that it is not <hi>abſolutely neceſſary</hi> for al maner of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8106:5"/> men to read them. It is abſolutely neceſſary that all men ſhoulde vſe all good meanes and helpes, whereby to know Chriſt more perfectly: but reading of the ſcripturs (which al do teſtifie of him) is a good meane and help therevnto: wherefore it is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary. And to this ſtayre of clyming vp to the knowledge of Chriſt by reading, doth our S. Chriſt lift vp his hearers; when hee willeth them to ſearch the ſcriptures. For he<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 39.</note> doeth not will them onely to heare the worde preached, but to vſe all maner of inſtruments, whereby they might digge out the hid treaſure of the knowledge of himſelfe. And the circumſtance of that place, doth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, that hee had in that particular exhortation, a more ſpeciall regarde to the reading of them, then to th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t exerciſe of hauing them preached. For when of th'one ſide, they beleeued not the Sermons of our Sauiour Chriſt, and of th'other ſide, it was dangerous to refer them ouer to the Sermons of the Scribes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8106:6"/> and Phariſes malitiouſlye blinde in that myſterie: there remained onely that with inuocation of the name of God, they ſhould read the ſcripturs; to th'end that by conference of them with the Sermons of our Sauiour Chriſt, they might finde and feele the trueth of them. And as this place proueth that the peoples reading of the ſcripture, is a good help to thoſe that beleeue not after they haue hard the preaching: ſo th'example of the<note place="margin">Act. 17. 11.</note> men of <hi>Baerea,</hi> declareth that it is alſo neceſſary for thoſe that beleeue; that they ſhoulde be able by conference of the ſcripture, to confirme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the faith whereinto they are entered: whereof let the reader fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looke, what is both objected &amp; anſwered in that place. And if it were a ſafe and a ſure thing for the Iewes, not yet beleeuing in our Sauiour Chriſt, to ſearch and reade the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: how can it bee dangerous for Chriſtians, that haue already belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him to read the ſcriptures, which beare teſtimonie of him? And if it be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8106:6"/> commendable, that thoſe that were novices in Chriſtianitie &amp; plantes of a day olde, ſhould ſearch &amp; read the ſcripture: how much more ought the reading of the ſcriptures be commit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vnto their truſt, which (through the covenant of grace) were fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mothers wombe borne Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 15</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly it is abſolutely neceſſary for all men, to vſe all thoſe aides whereby they ſhoulde the more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly know what is the will of God;<note place="margin">Deut. 6.</note> thereby to frame themſelues to th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the ſame. Heereof the law commandeth, that euery one ſhould not onely haue the law ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like a trumpet in his eares: but alſo that it ſhoulde be as a ring vpon his finger, as a bracelet vppon his hande, as a frontlet before his eies: that is to ſay, alwayes in ſight. For which cauſe he commanded further,<note place="margin">Deut. 6. 7. 8. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> that the law ſhould be written vpon the frontiers of the land, vpon the gates of the Citie and Towne, and vpon the poſtes of euery mans pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houſe. Nowe if it were then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8106:7"/> thought good to the wiſdome of God, that the people ſhould in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by, reade the lawe grauen, or painted vpon pillers, gates &amp; dores, wher they could not conſider of it ſo grauely &amp; ſtayedly: how much more was it his good pleaſure, they ſhould read the ſame ſitting in their houſes: where hauing the book before them they might more ripelie and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratelie conceaue the ſenſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the fruit thereof. Further th' A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3. 16.</note> commanding that the worde of Chriſt, ſhould dwell plentifullie or richly amongſt thoſe that are of the Church; doth thereby giue comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, that they ſhoulde vſe all lawfull meanes of familiar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with it. Vnleſſe therefore it be denyed (which cannot bee of them that grant it ſometymes expedient) that the reading of the Scriptures, is a lawful exerciſe in the word of god, for the obtayning of greater wealth in the ſame: it is manifeſt, that it is commanded of th' Apoſtle. If com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, then alſo <hi>abſolutely neceſſary.</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:8106:7"/> Moreouer it is commanded to trye<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the Spirits, whether they be of God or no: But that can not bee without ſome further knowledge of the word then we receaue of the ſpirites them ſelues, that is to ſaye, the miniſters ſpeaking either in the ſpirite of error or trueth: wherefore it followeth, that the whole knowledge that a faithfull man ought to haue, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of the mouth of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but ought to haue a ſupplie of priuate reading, and meditation of the law at home. Againe the King, who of all other for the multitude<note place="margin">Deut 17. 19. Ioſu. 1.</note> and weight of his buſines, in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of the common wealth, might ſeeme to be freed from this exerciſe of priuate reading, and to content himſelfe with the ſermons in the temple: is commanded to reade the booke of the lawe diligently: where other men that are neither ſo full of buſineſſe, nor haue ſo many whoſe welfare dependeth of them, can not bee exempted from this exerciſe of pietie. And if it be neceſſary for the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8106:8"/> King to reade in the worde, that hee may rule well; it is neceſſary that the ſubjects ſhould doe the ſame, that they may obey well. And if it bee needfull for him to read, that hee command not through the pride of his harte thinges that are vnlawfull: there is the ſame neceſsity for them, leaſt in too greate baſenes of minde, they ſhall obeye man rather then God. Laſt of all, reading of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures<note place="margin">Ioſu. 8. 34 Nehe. 8. 2. Reg. 23 2. Act. 13. 15 &amp; 15. 21. Col. 4. 16</note> publikely in the Church, being not onely a laudable and approued cuſtome of the Church vnder the lawe, but commanded alſo in the goſpell: doth declare that that which was continually profitable vnto the whole Church together, can not but aedifie euery one a part in his houſe. As for their reaſon to proue it not ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſarie, for that <hi>through mans malice or infirmitie,</hi> the ſcriptures <hi>are pernitious &amp; much hurtful to many:</hi> It is very chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh. For by the ſame boult they may ſhut out preaching as well as reading conſidering that through eyther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie or malice, many &amp; the moſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8106:8"/> part oftentimes of thoſe that heare, get a greater condemnation vnto themſelues. So alſo the Sacraments ſhall be baniſhed, which by many are receiued to iudgement. Finally, ſo it<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11</note> ſhould be dangerous for the people to meddle with Chriſt himſelfe: as<note place="margin">Luke. 1.</note> one that is ſet for the ryſing and fall of manie.</p>
               <p>And to this manifeſt &amp; ſounding voice in the Scriptures, doth th' echo of th' elder Churches anſwere: which teache that the people ſhould <hi>learne</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orig in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. hom. 4. Chryſoſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gen. homil. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>the Scriptures without booke:</hi> that they ſhould not onelie <hi>hearken vnto the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> of the Scriptures at the Church, but alſo <hi>take the Bible when they come home, and that reading of the Scriptures performeth that to the ſoule, that meate doth to the ſtrength of the bodie: that all men ought, by daylie reading the Scripture</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p 10. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt. Auguſt.</hi> in <hi>Pſal. 33. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>get wiſdome:</hi> that they ſhould <hi>read the Scriptures, for that they were written to th' end we ſhould be comforted.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not the <hi>Churches diuine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> but the Popiſhe Synagogues deuiliſhe craft, to forbidde that at
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8106:9"/> any time, which both the Scriptures, and purer Churches haue not onely permitted th' vſe of to the people, but ſtreightly charged them therewith. And it is not vnlike the ſubtile prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the <hi>Philiſtimes,</hi> the moſt deadly enemies vnto the Lords people: who to keepe them alwayes in ſlauerie, permitted no vſe of weapon vnto them, a fewe excepted, whome they (forſooth) would ſhew grace vnto. So<note place="margin">1. Sam. 13</note> the <hi>diuine wiſdome</hi> of your Church, is to hinder the ſeruantes, that they ſhould not know their maiſters will: to holde from the betrothed maide, that ſhe ſhould not know her faith &amp; duetie to her <hi>ſpouſe.</hi> Where alſo it is to be noted, that as th' authoritie of Gods worde is in no account with them: So neither the <hi>Councill</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> (otherwhere matched with th' au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie<note place="margin">Vpon Act 15.</note> of th' evangeliſtes) nor the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame authoritie</hi> of the Pope is ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred amongſt them, but that for lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre they are boulde with both of them. For in ſteed that they praeciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie command, that none maye reade
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8106:9"/> 
                  <hi>any tranſlation</hi> whatſoeuer, without the <hi>Curates</hi> teſtimonie of his abilitie thereunto: they haue without repeale of Councill, or Popes decree, put their tranſlation in mens hands with no note of <hi>diſcretion</hi> which we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; but <hi>who will giue moſt.</hi> You may not thinke much therefore if wee for Truths ſake make light of your Trent councill, when you for gaine infringe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the three next ſections, pag. 3. and</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>If (as hath bene ſhewed) all ought to reade the Scriptures, then all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, all ſexes, al degrees and callings, all high and lowe, rich &amp; poore, wiſe and fooliſhe haue a neceſſarie duetie heerein: of which particularities, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe the Scriptures nor auncient writers keep ſilence. For the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture declareth that wemen and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; that from their infancie, that<note place="margin">Ioſua <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pſal. 49 Prov.</note> noble and ignoble, riche and poore, wiſe and fooliſh exerciſed themſelues
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8106:10"/> in the holy Scriptures. And <hi>Theodoret</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theodoret. de corrig. Grae. affect lib. 5</note> lyketh well that the points of religion which the Church taught<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were not onelie knowne of <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>maiſters,</hi> but of <hi>Taylers, Smythes, Weauers</hi> and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther artificers:</hi> not of men onelie but of <hi>wemen, and the ſame not onely learned, but labouring wemen, ſewſters, ſeruants and handmaides;</hi> not of <hi>Citizens</hi> alone, but of <hi>Countrie-folke, Ditchers, deluers, neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards and gardiners, diſputing euen of the holie Trinitie, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And being commanded to be tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of both within the houſe &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,<note place="margin">Deut. 6</note> both lying ſitting and walking: a man woulde thinke that therein is commanded th' exerciſe of it in al pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, both <hi>table</hi> and <hi>bench,</hi> both <hi>boate</hi> &amp; <hi>barge.</hi> And it is too great ignorance to make that difference of place in this matter, which was not made vnder the Lawe: when in all manner of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces it is not onelie lawfull, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to talke of the Law. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the cleane, al things are cleane, the boat and boat-man, the rudder<note place="margin">Tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 1</note> and the rower: it is too palpable a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8106:10"/> darkneſſe, to thinke that the Worde<note place="margin">1. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſhould bee profaned by thoſe things, which by faith &amp; prayer it ſanctifieth. Wherefore it is moſt falſe, that the <hi>Bibles</hi> were then onelie in <hi>Monaſteries, Colledges, Churches, Biſhops, Prieſts, and ſome deuout principal lay-mens hands.</hi> For <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> exhorteth al the people <hi>&amp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Coloſſ. hom 9 Hieron. in Pſal. 133 In Matth. homil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne 3 d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſecular men to get them Bibles, at the leaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the new Teſtament. Ierom</hi> alſo ſaieth <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> married men, Monkes, ſillie wemen were wont to conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, who ſhould learn moe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures without booke.</hi> But <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> is bold, and affirmeth it <hi>more fit and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the lay people to read Gods worde, then for Monkes, Prieſts, or any other.</hi> And if priuate reading of the Bible were vrged ſo ſore, when (through the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile of wryting,) it muſt needes coſt much: how much more then is it now to be preſſed, when (through the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of printing) it is ſo eaſilie and lightlie obtained. It is falſe alſo, that either they ſung in an <hi>vnknowne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> or <hi>without knowledge of the ſenſe</hi> in ſome profitable meaſure: which had bene liker vnto the prating, prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8106:11"/> and parating of birdes tickling th' eares of fond men; then to any Chriſtian melodie, pleaſant in the eares of the wiſe God.</p>
               <p>After, like men fighting in the dark, they ſtryke themſelues inſtead of the enemie. For they are forced to bring forth <hi>Ierome, exhorting men and wemen to the reading and meditation of the Scripture,</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>reby to walke comelie in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall callings. Themſelues therefore which dryue men from <hi>reading</hi> of the Scriptures, are cauſes why neither <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irgines</hi> can <hi>meditate of chaſtitie, nor wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of faithfulneſſe, Prince how to rule,</hi> nor <hi>ſubiect how to obey:</hi> ſeeing theſe dueties are euidentlie to th' vnderſtanding of the ſimpleſt, laide forth in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: And if then <hi>th' inferiors taught not their ſuperiors:</hi> it was becauſe that as they excelled their vnderlings in age &amp; dignitie; ſo they went before them in knowledge and vnderſtanding of the word. But becauſe Poperie is ſuch a time, wherein (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) the<note place="margin">Eccl. 10. 4.</note> ſeruants ryde and the maiſters goe on foot: that is to ſay, wherein common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8106:11"/> the Biſhop can byte, but not bark: the Paſtor can milke but not feede: the Prieſt can mum, but cannot ſpeak it is needfull that in ſuch a caſe, the waters ſhould go againſt the ſtreame &amp; the <hi>ſcholler</hi> ſhould teache <hi>his maiſter,</hi> the <hi>ſheepe controule his Paſtor, &amp;c.</hi> Yea in the learnedſt and lightſomeſt times that euer were, and in perſonages of notable marke, it hath ſometymes come to paſſe, that not onelie wemen<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke 2. 38 Luk. 24. 10 act. 18. 26. 2. Reg 5 13</hi> Chryſoſt. in Coloſſ. hom. 9 Auguſt. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tempor. ſerm. 56.</note> haue inſtructed men: but euen the <hi>ſheepe</hi> the <hi>ſhepheards,</hi> the <hi>ſchollers</hi> their <hi>maiſter,</hi> the ſeruant their Lord. And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> will haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one to learne, as they may teach one another. Againſt which as alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the peoples reading of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, neither <hi>Ierome</hi> nor <hi>Auguſt.</hi> haue a word. For <hi>Ierome</hi> in the ſame epiſtle exhorteth to the reading of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, onelie he reproueth them which truſting vnto the ſtrength of their wits, and to their owne ſtudie, ſeeke not the neceſſarie helpe of a teacher, the principall meanes which God hath ordained to bring men to ſound
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8106:12"/> knowledg of the trueth. And how far <hi>Ierome</hi> was from the Ieſuites iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it appeareth otherwhere: when he ſaith, that the <hi>Scripture is tearmed the Scripture of the people, becauſe it is red vnto</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. in pſal. 86</note> 
                  <hi>all people that all may vnderſtand.</hi> Lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he ſharply reproueth ſuch as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned thoſe that <hi>red the Scripture and muſed of them day and night, as chatters &amp; vnprofitable:</hi> which is the very popiſhe ſpirit that reigneth in theſe daies. The ſame anſwere ſerueth for <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who reprooueth not men for reading of the Scripture, but onelie for that in reading them, and finding difficulties which they cannot auoide: they forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with condemne the worde, in ſteade that they ſhould repaire to ſuch as are able to vndoe their knots. Which thing is not onelie cleare vppon the place, but confirmed by other ſayings Where declaring it not to be enough to heare the word in the Church only, he exhorteth al <hi>in their priuate houſes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de tempor. ſerm. 55</note> 
                  <hi>to read, or to get ſome to reade for them.</hi> And againe, that nothing abideth, but that which a man hath lay de vp in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8106:12"/> the treaſure of his conſcience, for health of his ſoule by reading, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or doing good workes, and that we <hi>muſt alwayes pray and read.</hi> And if they wrote this, when the <hi>malady of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie in diuine matters was not ſo great as now it is:</hi> howe much more would<note place="margin">2. Reg. 22. 11. 18. 19 Rom. 7. 7 9. 10</note> they haue wrote it in theſe dayes; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the vſe of the Scripture, is to beat downe the pride and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie of the minde: whereas the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites conclude cleane contrarie, that becauſe men are more proud nowe then heretofore, the Scriptures ſhuld be withdrawne more now then then; eſteeming that pride gayneth by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Scripture: therein like to thoſe whome <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſharply repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,<note place="margin">August. in Pſal. 130</note> which <hi>hearing that they muſt be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, will learne nothing: thinking that if they learne any thing, they ſhalbe proud.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the 4. next ſections, pag. 4. 5. and</hi> 6.</head>
               <p>The <hi>moderation</hi> of <hi>Nazianzene</hi> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, but helpeth you nothing at all. For it maketh a diſtinction, firſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8106:13"/> generally betweene Doctor &amp; Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and then of the Doctors office, varying his teaching according to the difference of one Scholler from another: which we confeſſe; and not betweene Scholler and Scholler, as you praetend. And therefore follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſenſe of <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> which is that the people ſhould not meddle with the Scriptures, but the Miniſter alone: your ſelues are guiltie of the <hi>conſpiracie of Korah,</hi> which permit to ſome of the people the reading of the Scriptures, which (out of <hi>Nazianzene</hi>) you pretend to bee the ſeuerall of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Miniſters. We grant it <hi>is often profitable for the common people not to be curious:</hi> and ſo is it alſo for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, in matters that breed quaeſtions rather then aedifying to God which is through faith in Chriſt. Howbeit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending his ſiſter for her cunning in<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>funeb. orat. de Gergoniae</note> the Scriptures both olde and new: it is manifeſt, that by <hi>curioſitie,</hi> he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not to draw them to careleſneſſe of reading &amp; meditating of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> words, as they make
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8106:13"/> not for you, conſidering that the <hi>ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of faith,</hi> reacheth it ſelfe to the beleeuing, (and conſequently vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) of the whole Scripture, and euery part thereof: ſo to fit them for your purpoſe, haue you ſhamefullie gelded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For you haue left out the pronoune <hi>this,</hi> which marreth al your market. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hauing before, out of the ſcriptures confuted certain which held that there ſhould be no reſurrection of the fleſh, concludeth with this exhortation: that they ſhould be nouriſhed with this ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of faith, which hee had proued out of th' Apoſtles &amp; Chriſts words: with which ſimplicitie, both himſelfe and all other was, and ought to bee conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted. After he ſheweth the cauſe of their error, for that beeing little ones in knowledge, they had negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the firſt principles and grounds of their religion, as it were the milke whereby they ſhoulde haue growne to the ſtrength of partaking of ſounder &amp; harder meat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Al which doth nothing bar them from the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8106:14"/> of the Scriptures; in euery book chapter and almoſte verſe, whereof, there is aſwell milke for babes, as ſtrong meates for thoſe which are grown. And as in the moſt champion and plaine grounds of the bookes of Scripture, there are ſome myſteries (as hillocks) higher then the reſt of their fellowes: ſo in the greateſt and ſteepeſt hill thereof, there is ſooting whereby with labour and trauaile, with much reading and often prayer, wee may come to that height of it, wherein wee may ſee and diſcouer ſo far of the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, as our places &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, ſexes and ages do require. And as there is no booke in the Scripture ſo myſticall and deepe, whereout a good teacher wil not deliuer doctrine fit aſwell for the vnlearned, as for the learned: ſo is there no good ſcholer in the ſchoole of Chriſt, which out of the hardeſt bookes, cannot draw ſome thing, aſwel for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation of that which he hath learned, as for his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the knowledge of that,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8106:14"/> which he is yet to learne. And as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man hath learned Arithmetick, the way is open and eaſie to Geometrie, both which make eaſy ſtaires to clime vp to Aſtronomie: euen ſo the people hauing laide the grounds of Religion wel, and red diligently the eaſier and plainer bookes of the Scripture; ſhall haue alſo a plaine and a paved way, euen in the deepeſt myſteries, and profoundeſt bookes of the Scripture. Heereof <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>al the words</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>of wiſdome are open and eaſie to euery one of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding.</hi> Where becauſe by a man of vnderſtanding, he meaneth euerie one that is godlie; as by the foole, the wicked: it is manifeſt, that he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that all the words of God are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, &amp; open to al Gods people. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of<note place="margin">Geneſ. 18</note> alſo commeth that it is ſaide, that<note place="margin">Pſal. 25</note> God reueleth his ſecrets &amp; hid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, to all that feare him. Seeing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people may aſwell come to the reading of the Scriptures with the feare of God, as the Miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: it followeth that there can be no hardnes or difficultie of any place
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8106:15"/> of Scripture, which ſhall more with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſight of that which is needful for them in their place and calling, then which is neceſſarie for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in theirs. Chriſt ſaith that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer<note place="margin">Iohn. 7, 17</note> will doe the will of God, the ſame ſhall know his doctrine. Seing therefore the people and vnlearned, may haue as ſetled a purpoſe to doe the will of God, aſwell as the Paſtor or learned: it is euident, that their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and trauaile in reading of the Scripture, ſhall be more fruſtrate for their eſtate, then the Miniſters for theirs. Likewiſe there being a certain promiſe, <hi>that thoſe which abyde in the word which they haue beleeued, ſhall knowe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 31 32</note> 
                  <hi>the truth:</hi> it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be, but that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doing that aſwell as the Miniſter, ſhall for their proportion, be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the promiſe aſwell as he. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto belongeth the plaine and moſt vſuall words, the phraſe and manner of ſpeach moſt frequented, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons and ſimilitudes moſt famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are, taken out of the ſhops, and out of the fieldes, from huſbandry and houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiferie,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8106:15"/> from the flock, and from the heard, from the plowe, and the mowe. For notwithſtanding that it had bene eaſy for the Lord by his learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and Apoſtles, and our Sauiour Chriſt eſpecially, to haue flien vp into the heauens, and to haue gone downe to hell, for compariſons to ſet forth his doctrine with: yet we ſee how he cree peth as it were vpon the ground, in taking that which is before mens feet to clear his doctrine with. Wherfore? but that thereby he would notifie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſonnes of men, that hee wrote the Scriptures for the capacitie &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of th'vnlearned. Laſt of al when the whole body of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from the head to the foote ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is tearmed a light &amp; lantern, they<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 Prouerb. 6 2 Pet. 1 2. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> muſt needes be the children of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which breath and bluſter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; obſcuritie continually againſt them. And therefore if it be hidden to any, it is hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thoſe whoſe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings the God of this worlde hath blinded, that the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould not ſhine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8106:16"/> them. This iudgement of th'eaſines and facilitie of the Scripture, haue the auncient fathers. <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith that they<note place="margin">In Exo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hom. 9</note> 
                  <hi>are ſhut againſt the negligent, and open to thoſe which knock &amp; ſeeke.</hi> Another, that<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 2. Theſſal. 2 hom, 5</note> 
                  <hi>all is cleare and plaine in holie Scriptures: whatſoeuer is neceſſary for vs is manifeſt.</hi> Another, that <hi>the Lord hath ſpoken by his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. in Pſal. 86</note> 
                  <hi>Gospell, not that a few, but that all ſhoulde vnderſtand it: that</hi> Plato <hi>wrote his wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, but not to the people,</hi> but to <hi>a fewe, ſcarce three vnderſtanding him.</hi> Laſt of al, <hi>Cyrill</hi> ſaith, <hi>that the Scriptures are profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Contra Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. lib. 7 medium circiter lib</note> 
                  <hi>recommended vnto vs in an eaſie ſpeach that they ſhould not goe beyond the capacity of anie.</hi> Wherefore it is no Catholick, but the Pelagian iudgement, that <hi>the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra Iul. lib. 5. cap. 1</note> 
                  <hi>Scripture is hard and fit for a fewe learned men.</hi> Your owne Pope ſaith, that they are <hi>lyke a flood wherin the lame may wade</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gor. mag. Epiſt ad Leand. in expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Iobi</note> 
                  <hi>and th'elephant may ſwimme.</hi> And if all the Scripture carrie this light with it, it is cleare that euerie booke doth the ſame. Wherefore alſo the book of the <hi>Canticles of Salomon,</hi> intreating of our ſpirituall coniunction with our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, and that in moſt chaſt, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8106:16"/> yet familiar ſpeeches: it is meete for all ages. We aggree that there may be a profitable diſcretion, of reading one book before another, and of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one twiſe before another once. But forſomuch as the whole ſcripture is <hi>a letter ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the almightie to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> there is no iuſt cauſe why the<note place="margin">Greg. epiſt 84</note> booke of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould be plaſtered vp, that young men &amp; chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould not read that part of the letter, as well as the reſt. And howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer <hi>Ierom</hi> in that place ſeem to allow the Iewes deuiſe which they ſaw, what time the vaile was before their eyes: yet the ſame <hi>Ierome</hi> in another place, where he ſpeaketh of th'education of a young maide of ſeauen yeares olde, ſayeth, let <hi>her learne without booke, the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Gaudent.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſalter: and vntill ſhe come to be mariage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, let her make the treaſure of her heart, the bookes of Salomon, the Goſpels, Apoſtles, and Prophetes.</hi> Vnleſſe therefore you will denie, that the <hi>Cantîcles</hi> are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the bookes of <hi>Salomon;</hi> you ſhall be conſtrained to confeſſe, that <hi>Ierome</hi> would not haue the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der ages
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8106:17"/> ſhut out from the reading of them.<note place="margin">Ioſeph. 2. lib. contra Apion</note> Heere the teſtimonie of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, who affirmeth that if any asked any of the Iewes concerning the law: they were aſwell able to tell him, as their own names. And as for your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that the <hi>people ſhould be no more loath to be ordered by their Paſtors, in the reading of the Scriptures, then in th' vſe of the holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts:</hi> it is abſurd. For the Lorde commanded the father of the houſeholde, to teach his children at<note place="margin">Deut. 6</note> home, and by ſome opening to ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and ſet an edge of the doctrine of the lawe, that it might cut the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per into their hearts: yet did not he ſuffer, that the houſeholder ſhoulde miniſter the Sacrament in his houſe. And your ſelues, which graunt vnto certaine laye perſons, leaue to haue th' vſe of the Bible: doe you thinke it lawfull alſo, that you may credite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Howbeit (indeede) you deale with the people much a-like, both in holding them from the reading of the Scriptures, and in excluding them
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8106:17"/> from the Sacrament of the Supper: not onelie in that they receiue but once a yeare, but that euen then they receiue no Sacrament of Chriſt, but an Idole of your owne braine. When therefore you haue anſwered the truſt you profeſſe in the Sacraments; men may commit ſomewhat the more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, in the ſtewardſhip &amp; dealing out of the ſcriptures. There is no ſuch place of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in that booke: If there were, yet th' anſwere is eaſie: that the Bible is called the <hi>Prieſts book,</hi> as they are called the pillers of the<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3</note> trueth: for that they were more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie to occupie themſelues in the reading of them. But that he meant not therby to ſhut out the people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reading thereof: it appeareth in that he ſaieth, <hi>That he careth not much for his</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſe ſerm. 35 Look Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe vpon the pſal. 118. ſerm. 7. in verſ.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>bellie, which is earneſt in the food of reading: That that is the refection that maketh a fat ſoule. Alſo that the reading of the Scripture, is lyfe.</hi> We doe not think, that you doe ſo much <hi>enuie the people the reading of the Scriptures,</hi> as that thereby you ſeeke your vantage: that your vile filthie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8106:18"/> marchandiſe of Maſſes, and Diriges, Pardons and Indulgences, hauing no light to ſhew them by, might be ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted abroad: which would lye rotting at home vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your hand, if men might be ſuffred to bring any light with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into your pack-houſes. But ſeing you obiect <hi>enuie</hi> againſt your ſelues, let vs heare how you anſwere it. You com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare your accuſers heerein to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, ſurmyſing an euill and an enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eie in God, that forbad our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents the fruit of one tree. You do wel, if you be able to ſhew that God hath forbidden the people to reade the Scriptures. Which becauſe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, th' accuſation returneth vppon your ſelues: it being as Satanicall to forbid that which God hath bidden, as to bid that which he hath forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And becauſe it pleaſeth you, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the reſtraint of the Scriptures, with th' inhibition of eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden tree: hearken of how contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a iudgement <hi>Irenaeus</hi> is vnto you in this point: who alluding to this place of Geneſis, exhorteth all men <hi>to eate of</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8106:18"/> 
                  <hi>euerie diuine Scripture.</hi> You take a ſure<note place="margin">Irenaeus lib 5. ad medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um circi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter libri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> way, to keep the Church <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowledge falſly ſo named,</hi> whileſt you wil let them know, neither good nor bad: not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to thoſe parents, which to be ſure that their children ſhall not ſurfet, keepe them altogether from meate. You <hi>woulde haue them wiſe to ſobrietie.</hi> Therefore (belike) you banniſh them from th' acquaintance of the ſcripture the miſtreſſe of all wiſedome and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie. Where reade you that the Scriptures, are compared to <hi>knyues in the hands of little children?</hi> They are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede compared with a ſworde, in the<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6</note> hand of a ſouldier: whereby it is eaſie for them to knowe, that your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is to betray them, into their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall enemies hands, which haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their weapons from them. And if ſome mad men or quarrellers in the campe abuſe them to their owne and others deſtruction: yet the law of not bearing ſword in fielde, will neuer be iuſt. In ſtead therefore that you ſhuld haue generallie commanded that all ſouldiers ſhould weare ſwordes, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8106:19"/> ſuch as (in reſpect of franzie or quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling with their fellowes) are ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie reſtrained: you make your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, that no ſouldier ſhal we are weapon, but with ſpecial licence ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Is this your skill and diſcretion in warfare? But thus at leaſt you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde, that <hi>dogges</hi> &amp; <hi>hogges</hi> ſhoulde not come vnto them: ſo doe you alſo, that neither ſheepe nor lambe ſhoulde touch them. Thus th' vſurpers are kept from them, but the true owners alſo enioy them not. Heerein you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray a contrarie ſpirit, to that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our Sauiour Chriſt was condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. For he oftentimes preached in the hearing of known dogs and hogs, that is the Scribes and Phariſies, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatlie ſet againſt him: leaſt for their ſakes the children ſhould be defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of their bread. And you of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie ſide, defraude the children of their appointed portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leaſt the dogs ſhould happely ſnatch at it. Beſides this, do you think, that the diſcretion of dogs and hogs from ſheep &amp; lamb is ſo eaſie vnto you, as it was vnto our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8106:19"/> Sauiour Chriſt, and his Apoſtles? Can you tell who deuide the hoofe and chaw the cud, who are cleane, &amp; who are vncleane, who read in the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of heart, and who with pretence? Heere therefore you mutter that, which <hi>Harding</hi> your companion ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth plainelie: that the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are dogs and hogs: and indeede your argument is none at all in this place, vnleſſe by <hi>hogs</hi> and <hi>dogs,</hi> you meane all thoſe, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom you ſteale away the reading of the Scriptures. As for your deſcription of <hi>dogs &amp; hogs</hi> out of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> to be <hi>hereticks</hi> and <hi>carnall men:</hi> it maketh not ſo much to take the Scriptures away from the common people, as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the learneder and richer ſorte. For hereſie maketh her neſt oftner in the breaſt of the learned, and of thoſe that reade the Scriptures in the <hi>learned tongues,</hi> then in the common peoples heades. And the riche are more often loaden with carnall luſtes, then the poorer ſort: ſo that if <hi>Chryſoſtome or Tertullian</hi> proue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſtraint of reading of Scriptures,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8106:20"/> they prooue it directly againſt your practiſe, which lay the ſcriptures wide open to all the learned, and as it was in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes (if we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) to thoſe that might diſpend by yeare a certaine land: that is, to thoſe from whome either you durſte not holde it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or of whome you hoped to haue gaine through ſpeciall licence accorded vnto them. You ſay trulie, that no <hi>man can vnderſtand the Scriptures but by the Spirite of Chriſt.</hi> Whereof if you would haue concluded any thing for your purpoſe: you ought to haue ſhewed, that the Spirit of Chriſt is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the learned, or at the leaſt oftner accompanieth them, then it doth th' vnlearned. The contrarie whereof being true, that God reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his ſecrets (for the moſt) vnto the ſimple and vnlearned ones, and that<note place="margin">Matth. 11 1. Cor. 1.</note> not manie wiſe men, nor many noble men are taught by this Spirit: it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, that if any ſhould be ſhut from the reading, and other exerciſes of the Scriptures, the ſame are eſpecially the learned, and not the ruder, the nobler
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8106:20"/> and not the baſer, the richer and not the poorer ſorte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the three next ſections, pag. 6. and</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>Marke (good reader) the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of theſe wretched caitiues, that eſteeme ſo vilelie of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as if there were no better nor more honorable vſe of them amongſt the people, then to make choiſe of the reading of them, rather then to be much occupyed about <hi>ſtage-playes, cardes, and dice.</hi> Theſe men (no doubt) could be wel content, that the people ſhoulde rather ſit downe and pill ſtrawes, then they ſhould take anie booke of holy Scripture into their hand. <hi>Pharaos</hi> prophaneſſe from hence forth ſhall not be ſpoken of, in reſpect of th' vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed lips of theſe beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ieſuites. For he which held the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from exerciſes of godlineſſe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of doing ſome profitable work, tending to the fortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the land: but theſe are content, that ſports and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8106:21"/> plaies, and that of the baſeſt ſort, and of worſt reporte, as <hi>cardes, dice,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playes,</hi> ſhall keep the people from rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Scriptures; ſo that they be not <hi>much giuen vnto them.</hi> And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding if (as you praetend) they engender hereſies, amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: it ſhould appeare that they ſhuld be aſwel occupied in th'one as in th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: both of them being readie and beaten wayes to euerlaſting damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But a lyar (they ſay) hath need of memory. For, if (as you haue alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged) <hi>Chryſoſtome cals carnal men dogs and hogs:</hi> theſe <hi>delicate ones, giuen ſo much t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cardes, dice, and ſtage-playes</hi> beeing car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: it followeth by your diſcourſe, that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> was of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the moſt ſeaſonable tyme for the people to reade the Scriptures in, was when they were dogs &amp; hogs: then which what can be more vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelie ſpoken of the good Biſhop. But marke alſo (good reader) the braſen impudencie of the Ieſuites, whereby it will not be hard for thee to ſee, how all conſcience in them is euen ſeared
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8106:21"/> away, as it were with a hot-iron. For <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> diſputeth of a neceſſary &amp; continuall vſe of reading the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by the people: &amp; therefore doth not ſo much ſpeak againſt the lets of certaine times, as when they were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to <hi>ſtage-playes, &amp;c.</hi> but meeteth with the ordinarie and continual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment, as the <hi>care for houſe, wife, and children.</hi> For which purpoſe he alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth th'Apoſtle, that the <hi>Scripture was written for our correction.</hi> Which if the Ieſuites will reſtraine to the correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of exceſſe in dicing and carding, &amp;c. their cogging and iugling cannot bee hid from anie. <hi>In the third homilie of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> he doth not obiect th'excuſe of paſtime: but declareth that for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer themſelues from the duetie of reading the Scripture, one woulde ſay, that <hi>he hath matters to plead,</hi> another that <hi>he hath publike affaires,</hi> a third that he <hi>hath his handie-craft to awaite vpon,</hi> another that he hath his <hi>wife, his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and familie to maintaine and take care for,</hi> and generallie euerie one could ſay, <hi>I am a man of the worlde, it belongeth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8106:22"/> not to me to reade the Scripture, but to thoſe which hauing taken their farewell of the worlde, dwell in the mountaines and liue a continent life.</hi> To whome when he had anſwered, that they had therefore more neede to reade the Scriptures: he concludeth, that both they and he that liued amongſt men, as it were in the midſt of the ſeas, haue <hi>alwaies need of the perpetuall and continuall ſolace of the Scriptures.</hi> And yet reckoning vp the manifolde vſes of reading of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by the people, hee concludeth thus. <hi>Wherefore it is neceſſary, that wee ſhoulde inceſſantly, fetche our armour at the Scripture.</hi> Againe, he compareth in the ſame places which are heere quoted, the books of Scriptures, to <hi>th'artificers inſtrument,</hi> wherewith he getteth his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, <hi>which he wil not gage:</hi> and <hi>as he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his works with his tooles, ſo we by the Scriptures muſt correct our depraued minds.</hi> And a little after, <hi>The reading of the Scripture is a great munition againſt ſinne,</hi> but <hi>th'ignorance thereof is a downe-fall, &amp; a deepe hell: this begetteth hereſies.</hi> Againe, <hi>It cannot now be (I ſay) it cannot be, that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8106:22"/> any can obtain ſaluation, vnleſſe he be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually occupyed in reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> There would be no end of wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, if wee ſhoulde laye open all that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath in this behalfe, to proue that he herein praeſcribed phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke for the generall diſeaſe of all Chriſtian people, and not for a ſpecial maladie (as it might be the ſweating ſickneſſe) that haunted that people, whereof he had the gouernment. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for all times both in <hi>proſperitie</hi> and <hi>aduerſitie,</hi> euen <hi>vnceſſantlie;</hi> And not<note place="margin">Homil. 3 de Laz.</note> onelie in thoſe wherein (through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance) they waxing wanton, gaue themſelues to dicing and carding, &amp;c Wherfore your diſtinction of <hi>a teacher in the Schoole, and Pulpit-man,</hi> hath no place heere: as indeede it is fooliſhe, and hath no place otherwhere. For the doctrine in ſchoole, is and ought to be the ſame, that is in pulpite, and that in pulpite as exact, abſolute, and neceſſarie, as that in the ſchoole. The difference is, that in the ſchoole hath not annexed the goade and prick of exhortation, as th'other hath. For you
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8106:23"/> may not imagine <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> pulpet, ſo looſe and ſo prophane as yours is, to ſpeake at all randome, without any girdle of truth about your loines. Our <hi>wemen</hi> (God be praiſed) although they are wel able, to ſet ſuch <hi>Doctors</hi> as you are to ſchoole: know their places, and keepe ſilence, content to teach their children at home: which if you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not brooke in them: or euer it can light of them, your condemnation muſt firſt paſſe vppon the head of S. Paule, who commandeth to be tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers<note place="margin">Titus. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3.</note> of good things vnto their daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, and of <hi>Bathſheba</hi> who taught<note place="margin">Prov. 31</note> the wiſeſt child that euer was among the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> Chriſt excepted. The example alſo of <hi>Eunice</hi> who taught <hi>Timothe</hi> from his verie infancie<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1. 5 &amp; 3. 15</note> in the Scriptures, is notable to teach that neither wemen muſte forbeare teaching, nor verye babes to learne. And if <hi>alwayes learning,</hi> they are <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ignorant:</hi> in what degree of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, ſhall yours be found, that neuer learne any thing at all. They reade the whole Bible, ſeeing all is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8106:23"/> of God, and all profitable, and<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3</note> therefore the <hi>morall partes.</hi> But yet praefer thoſe that be doctrinall, or as you ſpeake <hi>dogmaticall;</hi> as both the foundation of all good manners, and the rule whereby they maye iudge of the <hi>example of life,</hi> whether it bee good or bad, worthie of praiſe or diſpraiſe. And it pittieth them, to ſee the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that is yet in your eye: which deemeth that to be ſo crooked, which to all ſounde iudgement is ſtraight: that is to ſay, that the cauſes ſhoulde goe before th' effects, and the rule before that which is ruled by it. And as Saint Paull in the duetie of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Act. 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> coulde not acquite the faith and truſt put in him, but by teaching the people the <hi>whole counſell of God:</hi> ſo they thinke not themſelues diſcharged in the duetie of learning, vnleſſe to the vttermoſt of that they maye, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoure to learne what is the good pleaſure and perfite will of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. Neither doubt they, but<note place="margin">Rom. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> that they vſe more reuerence &amp; true humilitie in comming to the high my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8106:24"/> you ſpeake of, then you doe in turning your backes vnto them. And they are well aſſured, that they are fitter to wonder at, and to advaunce th' incomprehenſible breadth, length, height, and <hi>depth</hi> of them, which haue waded ſo farre in them as the Bowies and markes of holye Scriptures doe teach them: then you, which neuer wet your neb in them. And if they read the harder bookes of Scripture, oftner &amp; more diligently, then they doe th' eaſier: a wiſe Schoolemaiſter which taketh pleaſure in his Scholer, would commend them. Neither hath it bene heard of, that the Scholer was euer reproched, for his greater dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in his harder leſſon, but of ſuch three halfpennie vſhers, as you bee: which are loath your ſcholers ſhoulde learne too faſt; but heere one word, and there another: heere a line, and there a line; leaſt in their dexteritie &amp; forwardneſſe of learning, your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abilitie and vntowardneſſe of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhould appeare. The <hi>claſped</hi> and ſealed <hi>booke,</hi> to vs which come not in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8106:24"/> the ſtrength of our owne wits or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,<note place="margin">Apoc. 5</note> but in the victory of our Sauiour chriſt, who hath vnſealed them for vs, lye ſo far forth open, as therein we are well aſſured to read ſo much, as will ſerue for our certaine direction vnto the kingdome of heauen. But in you, which bring of your naturall powers, and vaunt your ſelues of your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites; It is true that the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Eſai. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that neither can your learned reade, becauſe all is vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a ſealed let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; &amp; your vnlearned being offered the reading, they refuſe to read it, &amp; think themſelues diſcharged becauſe they haue no learning. And wherfore (I pray you) ſhould th' Epiſtle to the Romanes not be reade of artificers &amp; wemen: to both which ſorts (amongſt others) it was firſt written, and why ſhould that be baulked more, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by the ſimpler ſort: which hath a ſpeciall teſtimonie, that both it, and all other the preachings and writings of th' Apoſtle, are tempered aſwell to<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 14</note> the capacitie of the fooliſh &amp; vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as of the wiſe and vnderſtanding
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8106:25"/> men. If there be nothing in that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, for th' ign oranter ſort to learne: then hath Saint <hi>Paule</hi> made a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate debt, which now being dead, he is neuer able to pay. As for Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> wordes, they make no more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the peoples reading of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, then againſt any other part of the Scripture: the whole whereof, he affirmeth to be peruerted of vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and vnſtable men. In which kind if you iudge all th' vnlearneder ſort of your people to be: you fome out your owne ſhame, and manifeſtlie verefie the prouerbe, ſuch <hi>Doctor,</hi> ſuch <hi>Scholer.</hi> For our people we cannot hold them for vnlearned, which haue learned Chriſt; nor vnſtable which by faith are founded and rooted ſo ſtedfaſtlie, that al the winde and weather, waues and floods that can beat againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are not able to remoue them from the trueth, which they haue learned in the Scripture. We acknowledge with <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> their <hi>wonderfull depth:</hi> which would afray no man from rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them, if you had faithfullie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8106:25"/> 
                  <hi>Auguſtines</hi> wordes. Who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth<note place="margin">Confeſſ. li. 12. c. 14.</note> that the <hi>ouermoſt of them, ſmyleth vpon the little ones,</hi> and a little after ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>let vs come therefore together, to the words of thy booke,</hi> meaning Gods. In th' other place quoted by you, hee ſheweth that if a man of the <hi>ſharpeſt wit and greateſt diligence, from his childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſhould giue himſelf to the ſtudy of them, continuing in them vntill crooked age,</hi> as if he ſhould liue the yeares of <hi>Methuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah: yet he might alwayes profite further in them.</hi> Which is manifeſtlie againſt you, for being bottomleſſe, he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">Auguſt. epiſt. 3.</note> that notwithſtanding no man can ſound them, yet that his endeuour to ſearch, is not in vaine, but is ioyned with dailie profite, eſpeciallie in <hi>things neceſſary to ſaluation:</hi> which he affirmeth <hi>not to be ſo hardlie come vnto.</hi> Yea him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf confeſſeth, that euen in his verie firſt entrance to the chriſtian faith, he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red<note place="margin">Auguſt. Confeſſ. lib. 8. cap. 12. et 7. cap. 9. Chryſoſt. in proaem. in epiſt. ad Rom.</note> th' Epiſtle to the Romanes (which you woulde wreſt out of the peoples hands) with great frute. And <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> vpon this Epiſtle, teacheth that the people did not vnderſtand Saint
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8106:26"/> 
                  <hi>Paules</hi> wrytings, not becauſe they wer vnlearned, but becauſe they woulde not haue his writings continually. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom Epiſt.</hi> 13. 4. ſpeaketh of the <hi>hard ſhell of the Scripture,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did of the depth: to whet the diligence and induſtrie of men, to greater and more continuall trauell to be taken in the ſtudie of them: euen alſo as doeth the Scripture it ſelfe, which doth not will<note place="margin">Matth. 24. 15.</note> the diſciples vppon the hardneſſe of a place to giue ouer the reading there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but to ad further diligence &amp; care to vnderſtand it. Where the Ieſuites do it cleane contrarily, to terrifie men from them. And therefore <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith <hi>they ſhine and are verie bright euen in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>very ſhell of them, although the marrowe be ſweeter.</hi> Likewiſe he exhorteth all to crack the ſhell, to th' end to eate the kernell. And in the very next Epiſtle wryting to a Matrone, he ſaith, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the diuine Scriptures be alwayes in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ad Celantiam</note> 
                  <hi>thy hands, and let them vnceſſantly be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or rowled in thy mynde.</hi> Beſide that if al the Scripture were ſo ſhelly as you (out of <hi>Ierome</hi>) praetend: where is the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8106:26"/> milke and honie for children, that are<note place="margin">Heb. 5. Pſal. 19</note> called (as hath bene ſhevved) to the reading of them. They haue no teeth to crack the ſhell, yet they depart not emptie, nor returne not hungry from them. Wherefore <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>that God hath ſo tempered the Scriptures, that by</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri. Chriſt. lib. 2. cap. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>manifeſt places he might prouyde againſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and by thoſe which are obſcurer, he might cleanſe the loathſomnes of our ſtomak</hi> in exerciſing our ſelues about them: noting thereby, that men would grow to diſdainfulneſſe of the Scripture, if with th' eaſier Scriptures, they ſhould not ioyne the ſtudie of the harder. Finallie, if before the lawfull <hi>expoſition of the Scriptures,</hi> whole thirteene yeares are required, <hi>onlie</hi> to runne the courſe of <hi>reading the Scripture:</hi> we ſuppoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relie, that ſuch an expoſitor will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be found in Poperie; although he bee ſought with a candle: where the chief garland and crowne of diuinity, is not giuen to him that hath beene moſt conuerſant in th' olde and newe Teſtament, but to him, that can quite himſelf beſt in <hi>Duns</hi> and <hi>Dorbel,</hi> in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8106:27"/> 
                  <hi>Lombard</hi> and <hi>Gratian,</hi> and ſuch other vnwholſome Nourſes as theſe be, at whoſe breaſts, the popiſh diuines doe ſucke their firſt milke in Theologie. And to what end ſhould they beſtow <hi>thirteene yeares,</hi> before their entrance to the Miniſtrie, and the moſt of their time after they are entred in the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Scripture: if they may bring no other interpretation of any place, then that which they haue receiued of their <hi>fore-fathers.</hi> As for th' interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of euery part of the Scripture, by <hi>th' Apoſtolicke tradition;</hi> further then by <hi>tradition</hi> (as appeareth afterwarde) is vnderſtood the written worde of th' Apoſtles: there is no manner of mention in any writing, that carrieth credite with it. But of interpretation, the diſcourſe will followe after more at large.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the three next ſections, pag. 7. and</hi> 8.</head>
               <p>We are well content that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhould be condemned of them,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8106:27"/> that condemne the reading of the Scriptures: and as if they had to doe with a hand or foot ball, delyte in the taunting tearmes of <hi>toſſing</hi> and <hi>tumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of them. And we waite patientlie<note place="margin">Iudas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note> vntill the Lorde come to giue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all theſe blaſphemous ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which wicked ſinners ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, in his worde. The triall of the cauſe by th' outward <hi>fruites,</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth manie exceptions. Firſt, of foure ſorts of grounds ſowne by the ſeed of the Goſpell, there is but one fruitfull; the reſte beeing not bettered by the preaching therof, are worſe then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they remained in their Popiſh igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or other fallings from the truth Wherfore to praeiudice the fruit that the good ground yeldeth, by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe &amp; vnprofitableneſſe of th' o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three ſortes which haue receiued the ſeede aſwel as it: is not aequal, nor vpright iudgement. Secondly, this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue and apparant wickedneſſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the hypocriticall profeſsion of the Goſpell, proceedeth of the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the gouernors of the Church
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8106:28"/> and common-wealth, which looſing the coarde of both Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth diſcipline, ſuffer wicked men to ſpit out the poiſon of their hearts, which the wholeſome ſeuerity of commanded correction, woulde keepe ſealed vp in them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauiour Chriſt, is not afraied<note place="margin">Matth. 24. 12.</note> to confeſſe franckly that for th' abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of iniquitie appearing in them that made profeſsion of the Goſpell: the loue or zeall of manie, euen of thoſe which ſometimes were forward in the ſame, ſhould waxe cold. Nowe, to lay that faulte vpon the Religion, which cleaueth vnto the gouernours: is likewiſe an vn-aequall and vn-euen iudgement. When in the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and Church of Iſrael, euerie man did what he luſted: who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">Iudg. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> not, that there were heathen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, wherein many vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things, by law and lawfull puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were reſtrained. Yet we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Ieſuites are not ſo forſaken, that they will thereof conclude, that the heathniſhe people were better
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8106:28"/> then the people of Iſrael: and that the religion of thoſe Gentiles, was better then the religion amongſt the Iewes. Thirdlie, it ought to be remembred that although ſinne reigned in Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: yet it appeared not; there beeing no light of the law of God to ſhewe it by: for that the candle-light of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, was cleane put out. Where in the preaching of the Goſpell, by the beames of trueth ſhyning ſo bright, that which in Poperie was holden for no ſinne, is now knowne to be ſinne: and that which ſeemed vnder it, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſinne, the Goſpell ſheweth it to be very great. To iudge therefore our mote, and gnat (which the light of our doctrine ſheweth) bigger then their beame and Camell, which the night of their ignorance woulde not ſuffer to bee ſeene: is not to holde an euen hand, and to goe with a ſtreight foote to the iudgement which is required. Further, it hath bene an olde practiſe of the Diuell, againſt the profeſſors of the Goſpell, to charge them with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered manners: and therefore it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8106:29"/> ought to offend no man, if it be now renewed, by th' aduerſaries of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> truth. And although our witnes in heauen, and witnes in heart might well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent vs; whileſt by your ſlanderous ſpeeches, you doe (as it were blowing in the duſte) raiſe it into your owne eies, to make you blinder: yet wee dare bee bolde with all the faultes of the profeſſors of the Goſpel, (mo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifoldlie then ought or woulde haue bene, if we had walked according to the light that we haue ſeene) to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with ſuch black Mores as you be which beſide teeth and tongue, that is to ſay, vaunts and brags, haue no white about you. For what either <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in men, chaſtitie in wemen, or obedience in children, &amp;c.</hi> can there be amongſt you: which hauing learned no ſuch thing in the ſchole of the word, where they are onely taught, knowe them not. Your men may haue the <hi>vertues</hi> that Turks and Iewes haue, your we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children the chaſtitie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience that is found amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they may fight manfullie for their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8106:29"/> countrie, they may keep their bodies from outward pollution, they may do the things that their parents co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand them, &amp;c: yet is there heere neither true <hi>vertue;</hi> nor vndefiled <hi>chaſtitie,</hi> nor humble <hi>obedience:</hi> as thoſe which are not done for Gods cauſe, but either in ſeruile feare, vain-glorie, filthie lucre, or ſome ſuch by-reſpect. Whereupon wee reade that <hi>Seres</hi> a heathen and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous<note place="margin">Euſeb. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> praeparat. Euang. ex Bardiſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chalde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> people, had through ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diſcipline neither fornicator nor adulterer amongeſt them. In which point with ſome others, howe Angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like we are in reſpect of you; there is occaſion to ſpeak afterwarde. It is a diſorder, if <hi>wemen do teach their husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, children their parents, &amp;c,</hi> which you ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſaying againe to be amongſt vs, neither doe nor can proue it. But it is a greater confuſion, when ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther husband can teach his wife, nor parent his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor old the young, nor <hi>Prieſt</hi> the people. When the ſeer is blinde, and th' Embaſſadour dumb, &amp; finallie when the guide of the way knoweth not the way himſelf: which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8106:30"/> how true it is in your kingdome; wee leaue it to be eſteemed of all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentlie. Singing of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> hymnes, &amp;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1. Cor. 14. 26. Eph. 5. 19. Col. 3. 16.</hi> Beda Histor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. 5 cap. 12.</note> ſpirituall ſongs, the Scripture recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth vnto vs. <hi>Bede</hi> witneſſeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that diuerſe bookes of Scripture were tranſlated into Engliſh meetre. If any man abuſe this ſacred and holy exerciſe to <hi>wantonneſſe;</hi> the ſame ſhall beare his condemnation. But to meet with ſuch an euill, by taking away the good altogether: is like vnto thoſe vnskilfull phyſicians, that ridde their pacients of no diſeaſe, vnles they take their liues from them.</p>
               <p>In the laſte of theſe 3. ſections, are Scriptures and Doctors, idely &amp; foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhlie alledged, to prove that which no man denieth; that <hi>Haeretickes abuſe the Scriptures,</hi> now thriſe in this praeface repeated: by the concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either the Scriptures ſhould not bee tranſlated, or beeing tranſlated ſhould not bee imparted to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people; is naked and deſolate of all proofe: vnleſſe it be proofe, that becauſe <hi>hereticks ſhroud themſelues</hi> in the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8106:30"/> woll <hi>of the Scriptures,</hi> therefore Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks may not warm themſelues with their <hi>fleece:</hi> or that becauſe they drawe poiſon from them, therefore we may not ſuck honie at them: or finally for that they climbe into the Lordes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, to arme themſelues againſt vs; therefore we ſhould not enter by the dore to prepare &amp; appoint our ſelues againſt them. And if haeretickes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning the trueth out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, haue ſuch force to baniſh them from the common people: why ſhould not the confutation of haereticks by the Scriptures, bring them home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the peoples handes. If euer therefore there were doting diſputers theſe are their brethren.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the two next ſections, pag. 8. and</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>It is an olde practiſe of Satan, to beſtir himſelf, and to open the mouth of all his helhoundes againſt the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and learned trauels of thoſe, which haue laboured in this worke of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8106:31"/> the holy Bible, or any part thereof. Hereof <hi>Ierome</hi> complayneth,<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Dom. &amp; R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. in Eſd. &amp; Ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hem. &amp; in paralip. Eraſm. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Moſſella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um.</note> in many places of his prefaces and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles: that he was tong-rent &amp; raild vpon miſerablie. The ſame complaint is renewed of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> who was bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Ley</hi> in <hi>England, Natalis Bede</hi> in <hi>Fraunce, Stunica</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and infinite other vnlearned Monks and Fryers. And therefore it ought not to ſeeme ſtrange, if the worthie labours of Maſter <hi>Beza</hi> &amp; other learned men of ours, and other Countreys haue alſo their currs, to bark at them. As for vs, albeit we are not of that ſorte of men which loue our owne, &amp; (as the Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins doe their young ones) haue in admiration our workes and writings: And further alſo confeſſe, that our tranſlations are not ſo exact in all points of perfection, but that time &amp; ſtudy may better them: yet how falſly they are charged, by the ſlanderous pennes of theſe wrangling Ieſuites, appeareth at large by the learned and ſubſtantiall defence made for our Engliſh tranſlation, vnto th' unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8106:31"/> and trifling quarrels againſt the ſame. And if it appeare to th' indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reader, that our tranſlation which (no dout) for pure loue they beare to their cuntry &amp; countrymen, they iudge the worſt of all others: is free from thoſe corruptions wherewith the Ieſuites haue ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dered it: the good reader may eaſily know, what to iudge of our tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlations in other Languages, Latine, French, Italian, &amp;c. And herein let all men marke their equitie, and by their fidelitie in their iudgment of <hi>Maiſter Caluins and Bezas tranſlations,</hi> affirmed by them to be <hi>as new and delicate, as Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalions,</hi> or <hi>worſe</hi> then it: eſteeme what truſt they deſerue in other their accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, for either they haue neuer red them, or els partly their ignorance, &amp; partlye their furious malice againſt them, hath ſo bewitched the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they can put no difference betwene a ſwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling and ſwaged ſpeach, betweene an honeſt homelye ſtile, &amp; that which is pricked and pranked vp by choiſe &amp; exquiſite words, ſought rather to tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle th' ears of daintie fooles, then for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8106:32"/> the fit deliuerie of the ſenſe the holye Ghoſt inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth. Finally betwene that which goeth vpon a plaine ſandall, fit to goe far for the publiſhing of the goſpell: then that which is mounted vpon moyles and pantofles, meet to keepe it at home, amongſte a-fewe, whom that courtlynes and curioſitie of ſpeach dooth delite. And if they will purge themſelues from a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and impudent ſlander herein? let them note the places, wherin <hi>Caluin</hi> &amp; <hi>Beza</hi> departing from <hi>Caſtalion,</hi> haue either rioted as he doeth, or in licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſnes of ſpeach haue gone beyond him. Now where they charge vs to <hi>diſauthorize,</hi> or to <hi>make doubtfull diuers whole bookes of Canonicall Scriptures, allowed by th' uniuerſall Church of God, a thouſand yeres &amp; vpwardes:</hi> their limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Cyprian de Symb. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt. Euſeb. hist. eccleſ. lib. 6 cap. 25. Hieron. in prolog. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat. cap. 7. &amp; in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. in lib.</note> leuing vnto vs, the moſt ancient fathers and Councels which liued the beſt and firſt fiue hundred years after Chriſt, reiecting the ſame bookes which we doe; argueth a giltie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, conſtreyned to confeſſe the truth which they condemn. A ſtrange
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8106:32"/> impudencie therfore, vvhich neither<note place="margin">Salomon: &amp; prafat. in Iarem. &amp; praefat. in Dan. &amp; ad Domni. &amp; Rogat. in Eſram, &amp; Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miam. &amp; ad Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. lib. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menſ. &amp; ponder. Concil. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odic. can. 59.</note> able to anſwere our manifeſt reaſons, nor to bring any of theirs, nor yet to match in any ſort our authorities: not withſtanding blare out their tongues, crying and barking ſtill, that we <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>authorize the Canonicall Scripture.</hi> Their quarrell againſte <hi>Maſter Beza</hi> is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the proper place: That a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>tenth article of the Creede in mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> is vtterly vnworthy of any anſwer. for the meeter alwayes requiring a paraphraſis, or ſom compas of words: the poet could not more fitly haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded <hi>the forgiuenes of ſinnes</hi> then by noting our ſaluation <hi>by faith alone:</hi> according as th' Apoſtle, of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes out of the Pſalme, concludeth the iuſtification by faith without workes. Th' other corruption of Chriſts ſoule deſcending into hell, after his death argueth no contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongeſt our ſelues, but a ſmal remnant of th' infection of Poperie in that author: which is ſo malitious and ſtubborne a leproſie, as for the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued tryall of their clenſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8106:33"/> haue commonly neede to be ſhut vp from pulpit and pen, ſome reſonable time: and as they ſay in the French prouerb: <hi>The monks Cowle is not eaſely put of in many yeares,</hi> what conſent of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there is amongſt vs in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, the later editions which haue left that Creede cleane out, may ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what declare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the foure next ſections, pag.</hi> 9. 10. 11.</head>
               <p>What <hi>compaſsion</hi> haue you had <hi>of your country men,</hi> which haue kept back the wheat of Gods word from them ſo many yeares and ages, vvherevvith they ſhould haue bene fed to aeternall life. And your <hi>compaſsions</hi> novv, vvhat are they but (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaieth of the<note place="margin">Prov. 12. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>compaſsions of the wicked) moſte cruell.</hi> Wherefore it is certaine, that as the curſes of Gods people haue hitherto pearſed your ſoules, and runne them thorovv for engroſsing into your hands the graine of life: ſo novv they vvill be as ſore and ſharp againſt you,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8106:33"/> for ſelling them ſuch muſtie, mildred, blaſted, and by all meanes corrupted graine. Neither is your impietie leſſe now in poyſoning them, then it was before in ſtaruing them. Wherefore you partly perſwade vs, that you haue done this worke in <hi>feare and trembling:</hi> ſeeing in ſo open corruptions, and ſo manifolde and manifeſt wreſtings, it was harde for you not to ſee eft-ſones hell opened before your eyes. As for your childiſh tranſlation of number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>word for word,</hi> and as it were ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for ſyllable, rather then to giue <hi>ſenſe for ſenſe,</hi> and to tranſlate rather by weight of ſenſe, then by tale of words; although alſo, it ſhal appeare that you haue kept your ſelfe to neither; yet haue you no defence in <hi>Ierome</hi> for it. For although by the wordes you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, maye well be gathered out of him a ſtraighter Iawe in turning the Scriptures, then in turning other writters: yet hauing ſhewed in the ſame Epiſtle, that his vſe in tranſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Pammach de optima gener. inter pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndi.</note> was not <hi>to nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber but to weigh wordes,</hi> that he <hi>followed the wordes ſo farre as they
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8106:34"/> were not ſtrange from the cuſtome of ſpeach, that he tranſlated not wordes, but ſentences;</hi> he addeth, that it is <hi>no maruell, if this were done in tranſlating prophane and eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall writers, ſeing that the ſeuenty inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, th'Euangeliſtes and Apoſtles had done the ſame, not yeelding worde for worde.</hi> And after in the ſame Epiſtle he ſaith, that the <hi>care of th'Evangeliſts, was not to hunt after wordes and ſyllables,</hi> but to ſet downe the minde or ſenſe of the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines. And therefore ſheweth by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers examples, where they in wordes neither aggree with the 70. interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor yet with the Hebrew. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other, th'example that he ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out of Saint <hi>Marke</hi> is notable: where our Sauiour Chriſts words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely <hi>Tabitha Cumi. i. Riſe mayde:</hi> th'Euangeliſte tranſlating it, to make the ſenſe more full, interlaceth <hi>I ſay to thee.</hi> And if the Ieſuites tarie to heare, where <hi>Ierome</hi> himſelf vſeth this libertie in tranſlating the Scriptures: we ſend<note place="margin">Ad Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. &amp; Marcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> them to another Epiſtle of his, where they ſhall find him defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding himſelfe in his liberty of tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlating <hi>Naſchqu Bar</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:8106:34"/> which being worde for worde, <hi>kiſſe the ſonne,</hi> he tranſlated <hi>adore the ſonne:</hi> leaſt<note place="margin">Nolens tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſferre puti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè, ſenſum magis, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quutus ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> (as hee ſaith) if hee had turned other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he ſhould haue <hi>turned it euill fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redlie.</hi> Which we write, rather to ſhew how farre <hi>Ieromes</hi> iudgement in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating, differed from theſe apiſh Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, then that wee eſteeme that th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tranſlation which hee ſhunned, was ſo hard orrough, as hee iudged it. And therefore it was elegantly ſaide of the Emperour, <hi>I hate alike as depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aequally from the meane, both Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Suetonius in Octauio Auguſto.</note> 
                  <hi>and affectors of nouelties.</hi> The firſte place recited out of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> maketh nothing to the purpoſe. For as the ſtile of the Scripture, as it were the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and habite thereof, is neither new fangled, nor exquiſitly laboured by perſwaſible wordes of mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: ſo is it not foule &amp; ſluttiſh; but it is arrayed from top to toe as an honeſt and chaſte matrone, avoyding aſwell barbarouſnes and ruſticalnes of th'one ſide, as curioſitie and affectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of th'other. In th'other place there is no ſuch thing founde as they talke
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8106:35"/> of, albeit that alſo ſhould make as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the purpoſe as th' other. And if the olde writters ſpeaking and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto their people, did ſpeake and write barbarouſlie, that they might bee the better vnderſtoode of them: what is that, to make it a rule in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating. If <hi>Ierome in correcting th' olde tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation,</hi> ſo tempered his penne that <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending it, where it changed the ſenſe of the text, he left the reſt to remaine as they were:</hi> It followeth not becauſe hee ſuffered them to ſtand, that therefore he alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them throughout: conſidering that a man vvill not vſe that boldneſſe in correcting another mans vvorke, vvhich he vvould doe in his ovvn, nor put out euery phraſe, and euery ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeach, vvhich he himſelf could better. Beſides that it is a harder mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then you ar euer able to performe, to ſhevve that this olde tranſlation vvherein theſe <hi>venerable barbariſmes &amp; ſoleciſmes</hi> are found, is the ſame that <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> corrected. In none of th' other places alleadged out of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is there any thing to maintaine this ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhnes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8106:35"/> of tranſlation: but rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, when he affirmeth that ſome bind <hi>themſelues too much vnto the wordes,</hi> vvhich tranſlations hee holdeth <hi>for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient.</hi> Alſo that vvhen the <hi>phraſes are not tranſlated, according to the cuſtome of the auncient Latiniſts:</hi> although <hi>nothing be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> away from the vnderſtanding; yet <hi>they offend thoſe which are delighted with the things, when a certaine purenes is kept in the ſignes of the thinges,</hi> meaning the words. And vvhat his iudgement is in<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. lib de vera re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. cap.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> this cauſe, he doth other where plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and clearely ſet dovvne: vvhen hee ſaith that the Scripture is to be <hi>declared according to the proprietie of euery tongue.</hi> Indeede he ſaith that <hi>ſometime the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſpeach is more profitable:</hi> but his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is farre different from yours. For it appeareth vvhen hee praeferreth<note place="margin">Auguſt. de doctr. Chr. lib. 2. c. 11.</note> thoſe Barbariſmes it is for the better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity &amp; capacity of the people to whome he ſpake or wrote praferring rudenes of ſpeach; onely to that pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which either bringeth new words to offend th' eares of the reader: or elſe maketh the ſenſe doubtfull or obſcure.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8106:36"/> In vvhich reſpect he affirmeth, that to<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 138.</note> let his ſpeach fall th' eaſilyer to th' vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of his people, hee had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, <hi>oſſum,</hi> which is no true ſpeach then <hi>os,</hi> which is the proper and true la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage. Beſide that it is more euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by their barbariſmes in other ſpeaches then in the texts of Scripture: that they ſo ſpeak ſometime, becauſe they met with no better, nor more choiſe wordes. Seing therefore a good pure Latine ſpeach, is now better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, then th' ould rotten and ruſtie wordes: there is no cauſe, why they ſhould not now be aboliſhed, if euer they had any vſe heretofore. And if it pleaſe the Ieſuites, to confer the ſtile of theſe dayes, ſithence the Goſpell (after a long winter of ignorance) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to flowre againe, with the ſtile of thoſe which wrote 200. yeares hence: we ſuppoſe that they will accord vs, that there is as greate difference, as was ſometime betweene the <hi>Dorickes</hi> and th' <hi>Attickes</hi> in Greece, or is now betweene the courte and countrey with vs, yet we think that the Ieſuites
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:8106:36"/> will not therefore, rather chuſe to ſtamber &amp; ſtut with their fore-goers, then to ſpeake clearly &amp; purely with the preſent age: ſure we are, that they haue done their beſt to the contrary. Wherefore it is euident, that you can bring nothing to defend your ſottiſh ſpeach of <hi>hell of fire,</hi> for <hi>hell fire:</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>the ſpirituals of wickednes in the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtials,</hi> for <hi>docible of God, &amp;c.</hi> nor yet for your doubtful and dangerous ſpeach, of the <hi>ſinne of the ſpirit,</hi> for the ſinne <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit,</hi> with a number moe of the ſame late. And yet haue you not kept the law your ſelues haue made, for you haue tranſlated <hi>eighteene years,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 13. 4</note> where both the Greeke and olde Interpreter, which you propound to follow ſo ſuperſtitiouſly, haue <hi>ten and eight years.</hi> If here ſeing your folly, you amended it, why haue you not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected it in places of greater impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and hauing corrected th' olde traſlatour in another place of ſome moment, Rom. 13. 9. where for <hi>reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> you haue turned <hi>compriſed,</hi> why haue you not performed the ſame in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:8106:37"/> other of greater weight. Not to ſpeake of <hi>Lindanus</hi> your brother in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie, who ſpeaking of the truth of the matter retained by th' ould inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, more then the truth: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, confeſſeth the often ſlips of improprietie in ſpeache, and other babiſhnes of him in tranſlating. Now as by your vnlearned tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you haue greatly embaſed the pure mettle of the holy word; ſo by your corrupt <hi>annotations</hi> wreſting and writhing, haling &amp; pulling the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, either to a diuers or contrarie ſenſe of that which the wordes giue, you haue made it no better then fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie droſſe: So that it may be verified of your work which <hi>Ierom</hi> ſayth: <hi>you make of the Goſpell of Chriſt, the goſpell of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. in Epiſt. ad. Gal. cap. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>man, or that which is worſe the goſpel of the Diuell.</hi> If you had giuen your people your tranſlation alone: we dout not, but they ſhould notwithſtanding all your declinings fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the natiue pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the word, haue found releefe in it againſt extream famine, which your vnfaithfulneſſe hath thruſt them into.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:8106:37"/> Which thing you wel perceiuing durſt not vpon the peril of quenching your kitchin-fire: put forth your ſingle few of tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <hi>Cooloquintida</hi> of your <hi>annotatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s;</hi> therby to bring certain death to all thoſe that ſhoulde taſte of them. Wherein let th' indifferent reader compare our confidence, we haue in the goodnes of our cauſe, in either nakedly deliuering the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs without any annotations at al, or els with few &amp; ſhort directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Rather to open the file and courſe of the Scriptures, then to praeiudice the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, either with recommending ours, or condemning th' aduerſaries iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Let him (I ſay) compare it with the fearfull dout, that the Ieſuits haue of theirs: which durſt not commend their ſingle tranſlation, vnto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the reader, vnleſſe (beſide the load and charge of their margent notes) they had added almoſte at the end of euery chapter a iag of <hi>annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> wherein they recommend their owne, and condemne our doctrine: therby (at vnawares) teſtifiing againſt
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:8106:38"/> themſelues, that the wordes of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſpeak nothing for them, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les they be twitched aſide, with the wrinch &amp; wreſt of their <hi>annotatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> We hauing found <hi>Chriſt in the Scripturs,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be to ſeek in the true <hi>Church:</hi> you that hold not the head, it is no maruel, if you haue not layd hold of a filthy &amp; deade caryon, in ſteade of the liuely body of Chriſt, which is his Church. We which follow the light of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture in all queſtions that can be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of religion, and not in thoſe onely which you idely &amp; rouingly alledge out of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> haue promiſe of reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Petr. 1</note> in all our doubts. But you which blaſphemouſly make the Scripturs to giue no more light, to the <hi>deciſion</hi> of diuers poyntes in religion, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a hair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth: do miſerably run your ſelues &amp; others, to the condemnation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto you are ordained. In which way, although you vvould drag <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vvith all your might and maine; yet vvill not he keepe you company, not onely for that he hath nothing for you in the place vvhich you alledge, but
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:8106:38"/> that he hath the cleane contrary vnto you: vvho affirmeth that in <hi>the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures we are to ſeeke the Church, by them to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vnit. eccleſ. cap. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>diſcuſſe our controuerſies;</hi> &amp; after he ſaith, <hi>that all ſhould be remoued whatſoeuer is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged of either ſide againſt other, ſauing that which commeth out of the canonicall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibi. cap. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Scriptures.</hi> And againe, <hi>we deſire not to be beleeued, becauſe wee are in the Church of Chriſt, or that</hi> Optatus <hi>or</hi> Ambroſe <hi>or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Biſhops of our profeſſion haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended it vnto vs.</hi> Howbeit as through the vvhole booke it ſhall appeare, hovv ſmall conſent of the auncient Church, you haue in the principal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes hanging betvveene you and vs: ſo it ſhal appeare a little after, that there is a more certaine rule of th' un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Scriptures then you aſsigne: and that although the former iudgement of the Church of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſithence th' Apoſtles time, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keepe vs from falling danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie in the principal and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall poyntes of our religion; yet that they cannot free vs from error in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very queſtion, that may bee mooued
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:8106:39"/> of it: not to ſpeake of the faint proofes that ſometime they vſed euen in great myſteries of our religion, vvherein notvvithſtanding (touching the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelfe) their iudgement is ſounde and Catholicke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the next ſection page</hi> 11.</head>
               <p>After that by hiding &amp; burning the Scriptures, by threatning and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of men for reading of them, they cannot attaine to the cauſing of ſuch a night of ignorance, wherin they might doe all thinges without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulment: there remayned one onely engine, which Satan (with all his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) hauing framed and hammered vpon his lying forge, hath furniſhed them of. This engine is the defacing, &amp; diſ-authorizing of the Scriptures, as it were the taking from them, their girdle or garter of honour, by a falſe ſurmiſe of corruption of them, in the languages wherein they were firſte written. Which abominable practiſe being attempted in th'old teſtament
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:8106:39"/> by <hi>Lindanus,</hi> (whom ſome term <hi>Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſinus</hi>) is nowe aſſayed in the new by the Ieſuites, who of others (for their deadly hatred of the trueth) are not called vnfitly Iebuſites. Firſt therfore, or euer we come to their particular arguments, whereby they would (as it were) couer the head and maieſtie of th'authentical copies in the Greek to bring them to ſubiection vnto th'olde tranſlation: we think it not amiſſe, to ſet downe the generall doctrine, that no one oracle or ſentence of God can fall away. Whereby it will be euident that the holy Scriptures, both in the old &amp; new teſtament written in their original tongues, cannot either by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, detraction or exchange be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. Wherevnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of th'autor of them, miniſtreth a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall proofe. For ſeing they are of<note place="margin">Pſal. 111. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> God, all whoſe workes remaine for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: it followeth that al the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, being not only his handiework, but as it were the chiefe and maſter worke of all other, muſt haue a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall endurance. And if there be not
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:8106:40"/> the leaſt and vileſt creature in the world, which eyther hath not hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or ſhall not hereafter (by the mightie hand of God vpholding all thinges) be continued: how much leſſe is it to be eſtemed, that any ſentence of God, wherin a greater glory com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to him, and greater fruite to his people then of many of thoſe creaturs, which (for theſe two ends) he doth ſo carefully continue, ſhould periſh and fall away. Secondly they all are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten generally for our inſtruction, &amp; more particularlie for admonition and warning, for comfort and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, &amp;c: vnles we will ſay that God may be deceiued, in his purpoſe and end wherefore he ordeyned them: it muſt needes be, that it muſt continue whatſoeuer hath bene written in that reſpect. For if it or any part thereof fal awaye, the ſame cannot according to th'ordinance of god either informe vs againſt ignorance, or warne vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt danger, or comfort vs againſt afflictions, or finallye doe any other dutie vnto vs, which we haue need of,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:8106:40"/> &amp; they were prepared for. Thirdly, if th'authority of th'authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tical copies in Hebrew, Chalde, &amp; Greek fal: there is no high court of appeale, where co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie (riſing vpon the diuerſitie of tranſlations or otherwiſe) may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: ſo that the exhortation of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing re courſe vnto the <hi>law &amp; to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſai. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and of our Sauiour Chriſt ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke 10</hi> Hieron. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt ad Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel. &amp; epiſt ad Suniam &amp; Fretel. &amp; ad Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſum, &amp; praef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in 4. Euang &amp; praef. in pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent. Ambroſ. de Spirit. ſanct, lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. 6 Auguſt. de doctr. chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana 2. lib. cap, 11 &amp; lib. 11. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Faust, Manich. &amp; opiſt. 59</note> how it is written, and how readeſt thou: are now either of none effect, or not ſufficient: whileſt theſe diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and diſgraders of the Scripture haue taught men to ſay, that the cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies are corrupted, and the ſenſe changed. Nay, not onely our eſtate is worſe then theirs vnder the law, and in our ſauiour Chriſts time: but worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theirs which liued ſome hundred yeres after Chriſt, when th'ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers exhorted in ſuch caſes, that men ſhould make ſute vnto th'origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Scriptures, to haue an end of their controuerſies. Yea their owne <hi>Gratian</hi> out of <hi>Augustine</hi> (falſly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for <hi>Ierome</hi>) ſendeth vs in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding of differences, not to th'olde
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:8106:41"/> tranſlator, but to th'originals of the Hebrew in th'olde and of the Greek in the new teſtament. They vſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relouſly to ſurmiſe againſt vs, that we abbridge the priuiledges of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of our dayes; becauſe vve ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord them not to be ſo ample in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point, as they vvere vvhen the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles liued. But vvo vnto the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of our dayes, if the Scriptures be (as the Papiſtes would beare vs in hand) corrupted, if the Charters and recordes, whereby we hold the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the kingdom of heauen, are raſed or otherwiſe falſifyed, if we haue not wherewith to conuey our ſelues to be children vnto the heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Prieſts vnto God in Ieſus Chriſt; further then from the hand of ſuch a Scribe and Notarie as both might erre and hath erred diuerſly.<note place="margin">Hieron. in 6. c. Eſ. Auguſt. de ciuit dei. lib. 15. c. 13</note> Theſe euidences were ſafely &amp; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept, when one onely nation of the Iewes, and the ſame ſometymes (a few excepted) vnfaithfull, bare the keyes of the Lords librarie: now when there be many nations, that haue keyes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:8106:41"/> th'ark or counter wherein they are kept; it is altogether vncredible, that there ſhould be ſuch packing, or ſuch defect, as th'aduerſarie doth wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſe. Againe, if the Lord haue kept vnto vs the booke of <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> &amp; (in it) the ceremonies (which ar aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, &amp; wherof there is now no pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſe) for that they haue a neceſſary and profitable vſe in the Church of God: how much more is it to be eſteemed, that his prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath watched ouer other bookes of the Scripture, which more properly belong vnto our times. Laſte of all, (paſſing by other reaſons which might further be alledged) let vs heare the Scripture it ſelfe, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it own authority &amp; durablenes to al ages. Thus therfore <hi>Moſes</hi> writeth of it; the <hi>ſecret</hi> &amp; hidden <hi>things remaine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. 29. 29</note> 
                  <hi>to the Lord our God:</hi> but <hi>the things that are reueiled are to vs and our children for euer:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119. 152</note> Dauid alſo profeſſeth, that he <hi>knew long before,</hi> that the Lord <hi>had founded his teſtimonies for euermore.</hi> But our Sauiour<note place="margin">Mat 24. 35 Mar. 13. 32 Math. 5. 18</note> Chriſts teſtimony is of all other moſt euident; <hi>that heauen and earth ſhall paſſe,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:8106:42"/> but that his word can not paſſe;</hi> and yet more vehemently, that <hi>not one iote</hi> or ſmall letter <hi>prick</hi> or ſtop <hi>of his law can paſſe vntill all be fulfilled.</hi> Now as for the common obiection of diuerſe bookes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned in th'old Teſtament, where of we find none ſo intituled in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non thereof: it is eaſily anſwered. That either they were ciuill and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welth ſtories, whether the reader is referred, if it like him to read the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries more at large, which the Prophets (to a ſufficiency of that they wrote the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for) touched ſhortly: or els they are conteyned in the bookes of the kings; which are manifeſtly proued, to haue bene written by diuers Prophets in their ſeuerall ages wherein they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied. In the former kind whereof, if we reape not that fruite, which they did which liued in the dayes, wherein the reader was ſet ouer vnto them: yet we reape a more excellent fruit, which is a certain knowledg of a more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al prouidence &amp; care of the Lord, for the preſeruing of the Scriptures ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering euidently, in that all thoſe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:8106:42"/> away, the books of the canonical Scripture doe ſtil remaine. Hereof we haue a notable example in the books of <hi>Solomon;</hi> whereof thoſe falling away, that he wrote of naturall phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, and other by knowledge, the profitableſt bookes that euer were (the Canon only excepted) thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone which perteined to godlynes, haue bene ſafely kept for the poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Which is ſo much more to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, as there being infinitely moe in the world, that effect the knowledg of naturall thinges, then doe godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: haue not yet with all the care of keeping them, bene able to deliuer them from this whole and perpetuall forgetfulnes, wherevnto they are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, as if they had neuer bene written. Where of th'other ſide his holy writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings hated, of the moſt parte, &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly regarded of a number: haue not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding as whole and full a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance as they had the firſt day the Lord gaue them vnto the church. And ſeing there are now more then 1500. yeares, wherein there is not onely
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:8106:43"/> no booke, but no ſentence of any booke of Canonicall Scripture fallen away: what cauſe is there why wee ſhould think that in the tyme which was vnder the law, whole bookes fell away ſo thick and threefolde. For as for bookes of the nevv Teſtament i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined of ſome to haue ben loſt, their reaſons wherevpon their imagination leaneth, are ſo faint that they are not worthie the naming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Of all which matter, it is euident, that not onely the matter of the Scripture, but alſo the wordes, not onely the ſenſe and meaning of them, but the manner and frame of ſpeach in them, doe remaine.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3</note> For ſeing the Scripture remayneth, vvhich wholy both for matter and words is inſpired of god: it muſt follow that the ſame words wherein th' old &amp; new teſtament were vvritten and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited by the hand of God, do remaine. For how great difference, there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveen the thinges both vvordes and matter, that haue paſſed through the<note place="margin">Act. 9 Act. 17 1. Cor. 15 Tit. 1. 12</note> mouth or pen of God, and thoſe vvhich come from a mortal man: may
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:8106:43"/> appeare by the ſayings of the Poets, taken vp of the holye Ghoſt. For not vvithſtanding the Poets vſe the ſame vvordes and ſenſe, vvhich the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vſeth: yet vvere they neither the vvordes nor the ſenſe of God, but of the Poets, vntill they had paſſed by the golden pype of the Lords mouth. Whereby it came to paſſe, that thoſe ſayings which were before prophane, are now moſt holy: euen as the ſtones and timber which in the quarrey and forreſt were common, were after holy when they were laide in the building of the Temple. If therefore words, the ſame in letters &amp; ſillables with thoſe the holy Ghoſt vſeth, are not wordes inſpired of God, becauſe they were neither written nor ſpoken of him; his Embaſſadors and publike notaries: how much leſſe are the wordes of the olde tranſlator, diuers from them of the holy Ghoſt, inſpired of him, ſeing they neuer paſſed either by pen or mouth of his. And albeit th' olde tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator (which he is far from) ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes giue ſenſe for ſenſe, &amp; waight
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:8106:44"/> for waight: yet ſhuld not his tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which ſo ſhould be y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> truth of god) be therfore the worde of God: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the title aggreeth only to that truth of God, which hath alſo the frame of his words. And therefore the Apoſtle maketh a manifeſt difference betweene the <hi>wholſome wordes of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 3</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt, and the doctrine that is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to godlines.</hi> And our Sauiour Chriſt in ſaying that <hi>thy worde is the trueth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 17. 17</note> doth manifeſtly eſtabliſh a difference betweene gods worde and his trueth; otherwiſe he ſhould ſay, thy trueth is the trueth, or thy word is the word: which were no declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but onely an vnneceſſarie repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition. Wherefore it is truly verefied of theſe men, which the Prophet ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: that <hi>they haue forſaken the fountains,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and digged ciſterns.</hi> But let vs examine the pith of their reaſones, which haue moued them rather to draw from the riuen and leaking cask of th' old tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator, by the which manye thinges haue entred, to th' emparing the ſweet wine of the Scripture: then from the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:8106:44"/> ſtaunch &amp; whole veſſels of the Greek copies, which preſerue it from all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the firſt reaſon.</head>
               <p>Theſe men are worthie to goe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in their olde cloathes, that make th' age of the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation, the firſt and principall commendation therof. Wherby it ſhuld appear, if they could haue come by the tranſlation that <hi>Ierom</hi> amended, they would haue tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their drink out of that, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of this: as that whoſe head was hoarer. And if this be a good reaſon, why ſhould not the tranſlation of <hi>Symmachus, Aquila and Theodotion</hi> bee preferred, which are auncienter then he. Yea why ſhould not the 70. before them all, be much more preferred; as thoſe that were vſed oftentymes of th' Apoſtles, and commended highly of th' auncient fathers. But as gray heares are then onely honorable, when they are founde in the waye of righteouſneſſe: ſo th' age of th' old tranſlator, is there only to be reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reuerenced, where both for
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:8106:45"/> properneſſe of wordes, and truth of ſenſe, he hath wiſely and faithfully tranſlated. And ſo far we holde him worthie to be preferred, before other interpreters. But if antiquitie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended th' olde tranſlation vnto you for that it was aboue 1300. yeares olde: the Greek coppies being more ancient then it: &amp; hauing bene vſed aboue 1500 yeares, ſhould (ye wiſſe) haue had the right hand of th' olde tranſlator.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the ſecond reaſon.</head>
               <p>It is falſe. For it is not the <hi>receiued o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Looke Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome vpon theſe places and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with th' old tranſlator. <hi>Geneſ. 1. 2 Eſai. 1 12 30. &amp; 5. 2 Gal. 1. 16 &amp; 2. 5. &amp; 5 8. Eph. 1 14 &amp; 4. 19. &amp;c</hi>
                  </note> neither is there any probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of it, conſidering that <hi>Ierome</hi> in the old and nevv Teſtament, both tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth otherwiſe then th' olde inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, and often controwleth him. Hereof the teſtimony of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> (a man that had as quick a noſe in <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes</hi> doings, as whoſoeuer:) is nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who flatly affirmeth that this <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation is neither Cyprians, nor Hilaries, nor Ambroſe, nor Auguſtins, nor Ieromes; ſeing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:8106:45"/> his reading is diuers from it, and that it is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Looke alſo afterward, for other examples. Eraſ. epiſt. N. amico ex ani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o dilecto Eraſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Scholijs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> epiſt. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. ad P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mmach. libro 1. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus loui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nian.</note> 
                  <hi>much leſſe, that which he corrected; ſeing there be found in this which he condemneth, not onlye as touching the wordes, but alſo as touching the meaning.</hi> And in another place he ſaith, that <hi>Ierome manifeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the former tranſlation, vvhich wee yet (for the moſt part) doe vſe. Ierome</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though without cauſe) ſcurgeth the old interpreter, for tranſlating <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Sobrietie:</hi> which (ſayth he) ſhould haue bene tranſlated chaſtitie. And this hee doeth in tvvo or three places. Now a man would not think, that <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> was ſo vn-aduiſed, as to haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his aduerſarie this adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage: that he might reply againſt him, that it was his own tranſlation, or that which he corrected, and therfore that he was driuen to a hard ſhift, which could not defend his cauſe but by denyal of him ſelf. But that this tranſlation is not <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fat ad co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> let the reader looke the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that <hi>Munſter</hi> hath made here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Howbeit if this were granted them which they were neuer able to proue: what haue they gained thereby? for it
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:8106:46"/> followeth not, that if either it were truly tranſlated, or faithfully correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Ierome:</hi> that therefore it is now true, and voyd of corruption. The fountaine of the Scriptures is ſo wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the prouidence of God, ſo cloſe ſealed and couered; that by no, either negligence or malice of men, there can any ſuch thing fall into it, to tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the cleare &amp; ſweete water there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: but as for the writinges of men, they haue no ſuch priuiledge, neither are they laid vp in any arke of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wood of <hi>Cittim,</hi> but that they may be, and are corrupted, as the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience doth declare. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is good to heare <hi>Ieromes</hi> own teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony. <hi>I doe not think, that the Lordes wordes are to be corrected; but I goe about</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ad Marcella<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tom. 2. epiſt vlt.</note> 
                  <hi>to correct the falſenes of the Latin bookes: which is plainly proued by the diuerſitie of them, and to bring them to th' originall of the Greek (from the which they do not denye but that they were tranſlated) who if they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the water of the moſt pure fountaine, they may drink of the myrie puddles.</hi> And in the ſame place where they haue alledged,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:8106:46"/> 
                  <hi>if we muſt beleeue the Latin copies, let them</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ad Damaſum in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raf. in quatuor Evangel. tom. 3</note> 
                  <hi>tell vs, which. For there be (in a manner) as many diuers coppies as bookes. But if they think, that the truth is to be ſought out of the greater parte; why doe we not returne to the originall in Greek, and correct thoſe thinges which either haue bene vnskilfully tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or of ignorant preſumptuous perſons foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly amended, or of neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wryters added or changed.</hi> Now if the Latin tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before <hi>Ieromes</hi> time, were in 300. yeares ſo manifoldly corrupted; how much more, may we think that <hi>Ieromes</hi> tranſlation, hath in 1300. yeares bene impared and imbaſed; eſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as in diuers of theſe hundreth yeares, there hath raigned ſuch blindnes and barbarouſnes as neuer the like: and when as it was coppied out (for the<note place="margin">Monach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indocti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Monke. Hieron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in prafat. in 4. Euang. Ludouicus Viues lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de cauſ. cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> moſte parte) by vnclarkly Monkes, whoſe vnlearnednes is come into pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb. Of this corruption of books, the reader may further ſee both in <hi>Ierom,</hi> &amp; others of later times. Wherefore it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that either this tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation is not <hi>Ieromes,</hi> or els it is corrupted and changed, and that more materially,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:8106:47"/> then themſelues are able to alledg of the Greek coppies. Wherfore if you flie from the Greeke, for that there is ſome alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from th' original: there is no cauſe why you ſhould runne to this tranſlation, ſo diuers and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to <hi>Ieromes:</hi> vnles it be for that which <hi>Ierome</hi> ſayeth, that you had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drink of the myrie puddels of the Latine tranſlations, then of the pure fountaine of the Greeke coppies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the thirde reaſon.</head>
               <p>Th' antecedent being vn-true, the <hi>conſequence of Auguſtines commendation of it,</hi> can haue no truth. And if it were the ſame tranſlation, that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> commendeth: yet <hi>Auguſtines</hi> praiſe is ſuch of it, as doeth not free it from faults, nor lifteth it vp (as you doe) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place of Canonicall Scripture. For ſpeaking of his tranſlation of the Goſpels only, he affirmeth that <hi>it was</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. epiſt. 10 Auguſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 8. &amp; 10</note> 
                  <hi>almoſt faultles.</hi> And in another place, ſpeaking of <hi>Ieromes</hi> tranſlation of the olde Teſtament: he ſayth, that if there
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:8106:47"/> were <hi>any dark places Ierome was like to be deceyued in them, as other before him.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that it is knowne, that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth not alwayes follow this tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: yea that hauing ſene <hi>Ieromes,</hi> he<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib 18. cap. 43 de ciuitaete Dei.</note> ſtill preferred th' elder tranſlation to <hi>Ieromes</hi> that was newer: and affirmeth that the ſame was not his alone, but the Churches iudgement of thoſe tymes wherein <hi>Ieromes</hi> tranſlation came abroade.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the fourth reaſon.</head>
               <p>Although your ſpeach <hi>being vſed of the moſt part,</hi> being faint and ſhort to proue that it alone ſhould now be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: yet euen this is verie falſe: firſt you are conſtrayned to confeſſe, that the Greeke fathers vſed it not: which argueth plainly that they had it not in that eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which you haue it. For then they would haue cauſed it to be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated for th' uſe of their own chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; if they had eſteemed it trewer then the Greeke coppies. Secondly the moſt ancient Latin fathers do not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:8106:48"/> follow it, as <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian, Hilary,</hi> who haue ſcarce a footſtep of it: albeit it was (likely) in the church in their times, before <hi>Ierome</hi> corrected certain places in it, <hi>Ierom</hi> often diſſenteth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, often alſo confuteth it. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine <hi>Ambroſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they vſe it more then the reſt: yet doe they often forſake it, and vſed it not (as you doe) ſeruily. This is yet<note place="margin">Hierome. Ambroſe Auguſtine Looke the places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noted. Gregor. magn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> epiſt ad leandru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in expoſit. Iob: cap. 5 Expoſit. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi 20. c. 24</note> more euident, in that th' ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and euen thoſe that vſed them moſt, ſend men (when there is contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie of Latine bookes) to th' origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of Hebrew &amp; Greeke. Yea in the very dioceſe of Rome, long after the time of theſe fathers: the Pope himſelf doth witnes, that not only he, <hi>but the Apoſtolike ſeat vſed both the new and olde tranſlation in Latin.</hi> Now if th' Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke ſeate in <hi>Gregories time</hi> (who made too great account of this tranſlation) vſed both, and (in the booke of the Pſal.) refuſing <hi>Ierome</hi> followed the old tranſlation: there is no liklihood that th' authority which this had before his tyme, buried th' authority of th' other
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:8106:48"/> tranſlation. And as the elder expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors haue not vſed nor expounded it, without controulment: So the later writers wherof ſome haue ben pillers in your ſinagogue, haue bene bould manifoldly to croſſe this tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation of yours. For beſides <hi>Bede, Burgenſis,</hi> and <hi>Armacan:</hi> of late dayes <hi>Lyra, Ianſenius</hi> and others, haue left the ferular in the olde tranſlators hand. As for the Church ſeruice, it was ſo (in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church) in the Latin tongue, as the people by reaſon of the Romaine Empire vnderſtood it. As touching your Popiſh <hi>ſervice,</hi> full of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye and ſuperſtition, as we care not what tranſlation it followeth; ſo we iudge moſte corrupt the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the fift reaſon.</head>
               <p>It might aſwell haue <hi>commanded,</hi> to eate accornes, after corne was found out. And as for this Trent conuenticle being aſſembled by the Pope th' arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enemy vnto our Sauiour Chriſt, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:8106:49"/> holden of a ſorte of blinde Biſhops, ſworne to ſpeak no truth but that he (th'enemy of truth) ſhould allowe of: we eſteeme it no more, then the godly fathers did the councill of <hi>Ariminum &amp; Epheſinum</hi> the ſecond: eſpecially ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that many councils before it, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wiſer, learneder, and more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with hereticks difficulties of tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations, neuer ſo <hi>concluded.</hi> Secondly being here aſhamed of the <hi>Trent</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, they mollify it, as though they<note place="margin">In Martins praeface be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>couery, nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber 35.</note> held it for a good tranſlation: where both the councill concludeth, and the Ieſuites holde it for th'authenticall Scripture, which they doe neither of the Greek, nor of the Hebrew. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let them tell vs how they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the <hi>Trent</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion with Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. his authoritye. Who <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apolog. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmi ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Stu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicam Platina in Damaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Eraſmus tranſlation,</hi> as <hi>Damaſus</hi> had <hi>Ieroms.</hi> Laſt of al, admitting it were the beſt tranſlation: yet that is no cauſe why th'originall ſhould not be rather tranſlated.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:8106:49"/>
               <head>To the ſixt reaſon:</head>
               <p>Further then it hath bene corrupt by popiſhe Monkes, which were (for ſome yeares) th'ordinary Iaylers to keepe it within the priſon of their cloiſters: we accuſe it not of <hi>partiality</hi> to popery, wherevnto it could hardly be partiall, when popery was not, But ſure we are, that the Greek is leſſe <hi>partiall.</hi> Secondly they might tranſlate with purpoſe not to hurt the truth, and yet fail of the purpoſe: as appeareth manifeſtly in th'example of <hi>promeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God,</hi> not only barbarouſly, but falſly tranſlated. As touching the <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, grauitie,</hi> and <hi>maieſtie</hi> of it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with other tranſlations of later yeares: the matter is before the Iudg, where our no, is as good as your yea. but if it were, as you ſay: yet your tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating it, in paſſing by th'originall of the Greek, can by no meanes bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed: but only by this, that not able to clime vp into the Scriptures in the Greeke and Hebrevv tongues; you vvere compelled to ſeaze vppon the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:8106:50"/> Latine, vvhich is the honeſteſt excuſe that you can make.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the ſeuenth reaſon page.</hi> 12.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praeciſenes</hi> in tranſlation is vvorthy to be commended, but ſuperſtition is vvorthy no praiſe. And if the Latine phraſe ſerue the Greeke, &amp; anſvvere vnto it better ſometime then th'Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh doth: that argueth no more the goodnes of the tranſlation, then it proueth th'Engliſh to be better then the Latine tranſlation, becauſe the Engliſh phraſe frameth often better vvith the Greeke, then doth the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine. Of this <hi>praeciſenes</hi> they bring two examples, vvherein commending the old tranſlation they condemne ours. The firſt is for that vve <hi>tranſlate Tit.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 14. <hi>to maintaine to good workes.</hi> Your Greek ſtomackes be very quaſie, that cannot brook this tranſlation. Tell vs (I pray you) how vvill you tranſlate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes contra Timoc. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us in commenta.</note> in <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but <hi>to maintain your right.</hi> Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you tranſlate it vve care not,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:8106:50"/> ſeing <hi>Budaeus</hi> a man of ſingular ſkill in<note place="margin">
                     <hi>rijs, tueri &amp; defenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that tongue, doth ſo tranſlate it, as we haue done. In th'other places Heb. 10. 20. we are charged for turning <hi>he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</hi> Wherein, whether th'old tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator haue ſvvarued further from the Greek, it vvill not be ſo eaſie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern. For the Greek vvord doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſignifie, to make newe; vvhich the Latine vvorde, that th'olde tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator vſeth, doeth not expreſſe. for <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itio</hi> doth not ſignify, to make new, (for that doth <hi>innouo</hi>) but to enter into. And this defect of th'olde tranſlator in this vvorde, the Ieſuites them ſelues do bevvraye, vvhich forſaking a proper Engliſh vvord, more expreſſing the old tranſlators <hi>initiabit,</hi> haue follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed M. <hi>Bezas</hi> tranſlation, who tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth <hi>dedicabit,</hi> which they turne <hi>dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,</hi> without acknowledgment of him by vvhome they haue (in that place) bettered their tranſlator. The other cauill of <hi>Traditions, Iuſtifications &amp; Idoll,</hi> is plentifully anſvvered, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal be, as they fall out in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this booke. But from this <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:8106:51"/> and exact following of the Greeke,</hi> how far th'olde tranſlator is, by differing from it, by being contrary to it, by putting to that which is not in the Greek, and taking avvay that which is in it: ſhall ſoone after appeare. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though if it vvere ſo <hi>preciſe,</hi> yet that is nothing to yours; which goeth ſo far from it, both in vvordes and ſenſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the eight reaſon.</head>
               <p>If Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> commend it, who knew ſo many faultes by it: hee hath thereby teſtifyed the ſoftneſſe and mildnes of his ſpirite, and his louing and charitable affection, couering (ſo far as th'edifiing of the Church might beare) th' olde tranſlators vvants and defects: and thereby laieth naked the proud, diſdainfull and quareling ſpirit of the trifling and caueling Ieſuites, childiſhly ſnatching &amp; carping where there is no cauſe, &amp; diſcouering their owne ſhame, in ſteade of diſgracing others. Howbeit it is vntrue, vvhich they here alledge out of M. <hi>Beza.</hi> For
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:8106:51"/> he doth not <hi>prefer th' olde tranſlator vnto Eraſmus,</hi> but defendeth him in certain places, where <hi>Eraſmus</hi> (without cauſe) doth challenge him. And in th' other place vpon Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> his praiſe of him, is not ſo full, as they pretend. For he ſayeth, that although <hi>he may ſeeme, very religiouſly to haue turned theſe holy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>bookes: yet it appeareth, that he knew not the ſignification of theſe wordes, much leſſe the force and power of them.</hi> But if Maſter <hi>Bezas</hi> iudgement <hi>be one</hi> of the pillers, that muſt vpholde this olde tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, this it is in plaine wordes. <hi>It goeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ften from the Greeke, oft it is abſurde, oft</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beza in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui Teſtam. annot. quae inſcribitur Sereniſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginae.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tdoth add, the learned it neuer ſatiſfied, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnorant is brought into many errours.</hi> Which notwithſtanding he ſpeaketh not altogether, in reſpect of th' olde tranſlator; as in regarde of either the negligence, raſhnes or malice of thoſe whoſe handes it hath paſſed through. But if it were the beſt tranſlation, by M. <hi>Bezas</hi> iudgment: yet it followeth not thereof, that it hath no fault, or ought to be tranſlated, before the Greek. It would vndoutedly be more
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:8106:52"/> credit for your cauſe, to giue better weight of reaſon, although the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were leſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the ninth reaſon.</head>
               <p>It were to be laboured for, that there were in euerie ſeuerall country, for th' uſe of the Church in it, one Bible tranſlated into the language thereof, and one Latine Bible gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally for all the Churches, in whoſe Schooles the Latine tongue is the common interpreter: which (for their euidence and manifeſt preheminence aboue all other tranſlations) might haue at the leaſt the moſt voyces of them which are ſkilful in that matter, to recommend them to the publike vſe of euery country, ſeuerally in their proper language, or iointly of all the Schooles in the Latine tongue, as is before mentioned. But that any ſuch tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlations ſhould be ſeated, with th' originall of the Greek or Hebrew, (whereby they ſhould not haue the principall or royall Chariot, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:8106:52"/> the tranſlations (howe honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo euer) ſhoulde as ſubiectes not once dare to clime:) is in no ſorte to be ſuffered. And although theſe tranſlations, were (for the publike vſe) to be onely holden, and without waighty cauſe &amp; great conſent not to be cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, or without great modeſty not to be checked: yet other inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or tranſlations, might (for conference ſake) haue in priuate houſes and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, their fruit not to be repented of. Which if it cannot yet be obtained, men are therefore (for the meaſure of grace they haue receiued) no more to be diſcouraged, from their worthy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of dayly clenſing the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of tranſlations: then Saint <hi>Luke</hi> was beaten back from writing the moſte holy ſtory, wherein he was preuented<note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> of many, which vndertooke that which he only atchieued. Neither is there any more danger of <hi>diſſentions,</hi> and <hi>endles reprehending</hi> by the diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of tranſlations now, then was in the primitiue Church. Wherein <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> affirmeth that <hi>the number of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:8106:53"/> interpreters, could not be numbered:</hi> yet<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. de doctrina Chriſt. c. 11</note> was he ſo far from deeming that they bred diuerſitie of doctrine, thar he deemed them profitable, eſpecially for thoſe which wanted th' originall tongues: for aſmuch as that which was obſcure in one, might be manifeſt in another. Whereunto may be added, that diuerſitie of tranſlations was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo profitable for the learned, whoſe diligence of ſeeking for the Greeke copies was thus whetted on. It were a pittifull thing, if th' unitie of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4</note> (which the Lord hath bound with ſo many bonds) ſhould be broken by a diuerſitie of tranſlation. And if there may be a diuerſitie of expoſitions vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one place of Scripture, without vnlooſing the knot of vnitie of faith and doctrine: it is not to be feared, that the diuerſitie of tranſlations, ſhall be able to cut in ſunder the ſtringes wherewith Chriſtian vnitie and concorde are tied. And if any will abuſe, this diuerſitie of tranſlation to contention: yet are the tranſlations no more in fault therfore, then many
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:8106:53"/> other good thinges, which being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for the nurcery of vnitie, are (through corruption of men) abuſed to the contrary of that which they were ordeined for. As for <hi>Cochlau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> words of <hi>Luther,</hi> whoſe enemy he was: they wil not be taken of any indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t men. We gladly receiue this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our enemies the Ieſuites, that we are ſworne to no mans iudgment, howe learned and loued ſo euer he be vnto vs. Howbeit we make it no rule, either to condemne Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> where we depart from him, or to iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie <hi>th' olde tranſlator,</hi> where we cleaue vnto him: but ſhew our iudgment on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which we held at that time; which vpon more light of knowledg in th' o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall, we are readie to reforme. For with <hi>Auguſtine we profeſſe our ſelues of that number, which write in profiting and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtine Epiſt. 7</note> 
                  <hi>profit in wryting.</hi> For the particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of <hi>Cainan Luke</hi> 3. 36. looke for anſwer in the proper place. As for that <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 14. who be furtheſt <hi>from the ſenſe of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> may be conſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered<note place="margin">Vpon Act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. verſe 4</note> of the reaſones alledged there.
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:8106:54"/> But that neither we tranſlating with th' olde tranſlator, <hi>wemen,</hi> nor Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlaitng <hi>wiues, are far from the Greeke:</hi> it would eaſily haue bene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of all thoſe which being not Greek borne, had gotten any maner of denization in Greece. For it is wel known, that the Greeke word which th' Euangeliſt vſeth, ſignifieth both a<note place="margin">Hieron. lib 1. aduerſus Iouinianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> woman and a wife. And if they had not learned th' uſe of this worde, to be indifferent to both in the Greek wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: yet they might haue learned it in <hi>Ierome</hi> a Latine author, who telleth them expreſly, that the Greeke word ſignifieth both wemen and wiues. Therfore whetherſoeuer of theſe two tranſlations <hi>departeth</hi> from the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> yet is it euident, that neither <hi>departeth from the Greeke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the tenth reaſon, and firſt to the proofe in the firſt ſection.</head>
               <p>Th' originall copies of the newe Teſtament, are (by this paradoxe of the Ieſuites) leaſt beholden to Gods
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:8106:54"/> watchful prouidence, of all other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges. For in all other learning the good liquor is beſt preſerued in the firſt tongue, as it were the firſt caske wherein it was put; and the water is alwaies ſweeter and holſommer in the fountaine, then in the ſtreames that ſtreame from it. Wherevpon it is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by all learned conſent, that it is better to reade <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle, Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon, Euclide,</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> in Greek then in any language whereinto they haue bene turned, be th' interpreter neuer ſo wiſe and faithfull. And therefore (in their workes) the doubts which riſe of their meaning are voyded by their Greeke Copies, as by their higheſt court which taketh knowledg therof. Only in th' art of all artes, &amp; learning of all learninges, which concerneth men ſo deeply, as al other knowledge (in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon) is ſcarce as one haire to the whole head: the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God hath ſo ſlept, that therein th' originall as the gold is become ſiluer, and the olde tranſlator which would hardly goe for good ſiluer, is become the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:8106:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:8106:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:8106:56"/> and pureſt golde. The prophane writers ſome hundreth yeares before the new Teſtament, haue bene main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in that purenes, that their tranſlations, haue alwaies remained in ſubiection and obedience of their firſt copies, from whence they were drawn: only in th'original of the new Teſtament, the watchman of Iſraell hath ſo not ſlumbered only, but ſlept alſo: that that which was ſomtime the Ladie &amp; Dame of all, is now become tributarie to th'olde tranſlator. Theſe are the golden co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Ieſuites, which hovv brutiſh they be, let the reader iudge, of that vvhich hath bene ſpoken in th'entrance to this queſtion. They might (vvith aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much truth) haue led the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe into captiuitie, and thraldome of th'olde tranſlator, as to put doun his ſcepter vvhich is the new Teſtament in the Greeke tongue; by not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be born vp, in the preſence of th'olde tranſlator. But th'olde tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor himſelfe, from vvhence hath he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, the great welth &amp; riches ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:8106:56"/> to be in his tranſlation? from th'originall: for vvhat can they els an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver? And hath they of Gods careful prouidence, bene more vpon th'olde tranſlation, then vpon th'originall: more vpon a mans worde, then vpon his owne. If therfore th'original, haue bene ſithence that time corrupted: hovv much more the tranſlation, that hath bene more the tranſlation, that hath bene dravven from it. It vvould require a booke by it ſelfe, to ſet forth the iudgment of th' fathers, directly fighting againſt the horrible blaſphemy of the Ieſuites: vvhich olde fathers ſend men for reſolution of all doubtes, vnto th'originall of the Greek for the new, &amp; the Hebrew for th'olde Teſtament. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſpeaking hereof concludeth that <hi>the water of the fountaine, is to be beleued to flow more</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidium Hieron. ad Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tum</note> 
                  <hi>pure, then that of the riuer or ſtreame.</hi> And againe <hi>as the truth of the bookes of the old teſtme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, are to be examined by the Hebrew: ſo the bookes of the new Teſtament, require the triall of the Greeke:</hi> vvhich ſentence <hi>Gratian</hi> citeth as it were out of <hi>Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſtinct. 9 ad veter.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh in a certaine
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:8106:57"/> place of the new teſtament, affirmeth<note place="margin">Lib. 2. cap. 6 de ſpirit. ſanct. Auguſtine de ciuitate Dei lib. 15 cap. 13 Auguſt. in Pſal. 38</note> that <hi>th' authoritie of the Greek bookes, is to be preferred. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>that we ought rather to beleue that tongue, from which it is (by interpreters) deriued into another.</hi> And againe, <hi>the former tongue expoundeth the later, &amp; it is made certain and plain in one, that was doubtful in another.</hi> And if it be ſaide, that th' originall vvas then a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, vvhich is ſithence defiled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flovvred: vvhat reaſons can the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites alledge, vvhy the Hebrevv &amp; the Greeke, vvhich kept their integritie 400. years together after Chriſt, amid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt as bitter enemies, as euer they had, as troubleſome and tempeſteous times as euer vvere ſithence: ſhould after, in time of leſſe danger, &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quiet, looſe not their beautie only but their chaſtitie alſo. And vve mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that the Ieſuites are not afraide, to ſuffer this blot to fall vpon their popiſh gouernment, vvhich braggeth it ſelfe to be the piller of trueth, &amp; yet hath had no better care to preſerue the truth. But th' abominable ſtinch of this blaſphemous opinion, vvill bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:8106:57"/> appeare by the Ieſuites reaſones: vvhereby they haue raked, &amp; ſtirred vp this dung of theirs. The firſt reaſon vvhereby they bring vp an euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of th' undefiled virginity, of the Greeke originall: is that through mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of hereticks riſing out of Grece it hath (as it vvere) loſte her maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. But they remember not, that as many cloudes of haereſie roſe from thence, by occaſion of vvorldly vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; humane ſciences, vvherinto they (excelling) leaned rather then to the ſimplicity of the vvord: ſo there roſe from that ſame corner of the vvorld, great lights of Catholick do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, vvhereby thoſe miſtie cloudes vvere ſcattered. Neither was the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the heretickes greater to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face them, then vvas the care of the Catholicks, to keepe them vndefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And ſeing they conuinced their hereſies out of the Scriptures, forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as error is not confuted but by truth: it follovveth that if the falſify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Copies by heretikes were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; yet the ſame could be but in part,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:8106:58"/> not ſo much as in the narrow compas of Grece, much leſſe in the vvide cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite of the vvorld, vvhere the Greek copies vvere ſpred, aſvvell as in Greece. And notvvithſtanding that there haue bene, for many 100. years, vveightie controuerſies betvveen the Greeke Church and the <hi>true,</hi> diuers alſo betvvene you and it: yet neither doe vve accuſe them, nor you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſhevv one place of the new teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament, vvhich they haue attempted to corrupt for their aduantage, either in the proceeding of the holy Ghoſt, or in your ſole primate and vniuerſal Biſhop or othervviſe. This ſecuritie from incorruption of the Greeke Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, is greatly ſtrenghtned by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Lords ſafe conduct, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to th' originall Hebrevv for the ſpace of about a 1000. yeares, before the firſte comming of our Sauiour Chriſt. For hovvſoeuer that is alſo charged to be empaired and embaſed eyther throgh malice or negligence of thoſe that were put in truſt vvith the keeping thereof: yet the contrarie
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:8106:58"/> thereof is manifeſt. For men muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, who put them in truſt, not man which looketh only vpon the preſent eſtate and face of men; but God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which looketh into the ſecreteſt<note place="margin">Rom. 3</note> kidneyes of the heart, to diſcerne, not onely ſuch as they were at the time wherein he committed his oracles vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, but alſo what they ſhould be a thouſand yeares after. Whereupon it will be eaſie to vnderſtand, that if the Lord had eſpied any ſuch vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in them of keeping thoſe eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, whereupon the happy &amp; good eſtate, not of them onely, but of the great poſteritie of the Church depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and whereby they ſhould haue both certaine &amp; vndoubted entrance and ſeaſon of their inheritance; and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, whereby they might confer the promiſes made vnto the Fathers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lawe, with the full and exact accompliſhment of them in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, he would haue made other choiſe of the Wardens of his bookes, then they were. And ſeeing the Law went<note place="margin">Eſai 2 Iohn 4</note> out of Sion into all the world: it went
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:8106:59"/> forth pure &amp; vndefiled, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe had not beene the Lawe of God, but either of man, or man &amp; God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But what truſt the Iewes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged herein, may appeare manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtlie in our Sauiour Chriſts time, of all other the moſt corrupt, yet was there no ſuch corruption of the text broght<note place="margin">Math. 5. 23</note> in, by either Phariſies, Sadduces, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other the ſworne enemies of the trueth. For ſeeing our Sauiour taking them vp hotelie and ſharpely for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt interpretations which was peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larimie in regard of their famous rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries that ſhould change the text of the ſcripture: it is euident that if there had bene any ſuch church-robberie of raiſing the recordes, hee would haue made a ſcourge of Scorpions to haue laide vpon their skinnes, for ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable treacherie. Yea when of the contrarie part he exhorteth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to <hi>ſearche the Scriptures,</hi> ſuch as they were then: he alloweth them for the<note place="margin">Iohn 5.</note> ſame, which the Prophetes had by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine inſpiration left vnto the Church. And this latter reaſon <hi>Origen</hi> vſeth to<note place="margin">Hicron. in cap. 6. Eſa.</note>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:8106:59"/> maintaine the perpetuall virginity of the Hebrew Text. As for their trifling<note place="margin">In the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 44.</note> reaſons brought againſt in their diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of want and ſurpluſage, they are ſcarſe worth the naming. They alledg <hi>Pſalme</hi> 22. which they ſuppoſe to differ from the Euangeliſts words in Greek: whereas the <hi>Maſſorites</hi> doe witnes, that the moſte corrected copies haue, <hi>They pearſed my hands &amp; feete,</hi> word for word with the Greeke. And your owne <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrard</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Genebrard in Pſal. 21.</note> will not haue the Iewes char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with any falſification in this place They further alledge, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. where there is no manner of difference of ſenſe, for the Hebrewe hauing Chriſt receaued gifts for men: doth in thoſe words declare manifeſtly that he gaue them vnto men. For otherwiſe they could not haue bene to the vſe of men vnleſſe Chriſt had giuen. Howbeit in the very next vers there is added that God doth load vs with gifts. So that the Hebrewe doeth not onely tell vs, that Chriſt gaue gifts, but that he gaue them as Mediatour, hauing receiued them. Beſide that it is knowne that
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:8106:60"/> the Apoſtles in alledging teſtimonies, doe not nomber the wordes but giue the waight of the ſentence, to which nombring of words, when not ſo much as tranſlators are alwaies (as it is ſaid) bound to; much leſſe were th'Apoſtles tyed vnto it, which were no tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters but expounders of the Scripturs. And all reaſonable men will iudge it good payment if for foure ſingle pence, he receaue a whole groate: or if th'opportunity ſo ſerue, eight ſingle half-pence. They proceed with the 40 <hi>Pſalme,</hi> where in ſtead of the Hebrew, <hi>Thou haſt pearced my eare,</hi> th'Apoſtle hath, <hi>Thou haſt prepared me a bodie.</hi> But they ought to haue vnderſtoode, that there is firſt a Trope of the part for the whole, which th'Apoſtle doth elegant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expres, when for the eare he ſetteth down the body. Secondly, they ſhould knowe that there is a manifeſt Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore in the worde <hi>pearcing</hi> vſed of the Prophet, which being drawn from the law, prouyding that the ſeruant which would willingly giue himſelf ouer to a perpetuall and whole ſeruice of his
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:8106:60"/> maiſter, ſhould ſo be ſerued: ſignifieth an inabling of the Prophet, for a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling obedience to be giuen vnto the Lord. And therefore this Metaphore is elegantly expounded by th'Apoſtle when he ſaith, <hi>Thou hast prepared and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me a body,</hi> without the which our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt could not haue beene the ſeruant of God, to any ſuch purpoſe as he was ordayned. So that if as <hi>Dauid</hi> by Chriſt, ſo Chriſt for <hi>Dauid,</hi> muſte bring not a legall ſacrifice, but his ears bored through, that is, a bodie obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vnto the death: men may eaſilie ſee, that th'Apoſtle did expound and make plaine that, vvhich vvas ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what obſcure in the Prophete, whoſe ſenſe (and not whoſe words) he alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Further they alledge, 2. <hi>Chron. 28. 19. Achas King of Iſrael, for King of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</hi> As if they ought to be ignorant, that the place where <hi>Achas</hi> was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was firſt the place where the kings of Iſrael, that is, of the twelue tribes were buried, or euer it was the place of the kings of Iuda only. And if they had marked it, they ſhuld eaſily haue
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:8106:61"/> knowne both the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> and<note place="margin">Lamé. 2. 2 Rom. 9. 4. 17. &amp; 10. 21. &amp; 11. 7. 16. &amp; 29. 10. &amp; 3. 1. &amp; 29.</note> th'Apoſtle to containe Iuda vnder Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and contrariwiſe Iſrael vnder Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da. And the vulgare according vnto the Hebrew in the laſt verſe, readeth, <hi>in the ſepulchres of the Kings of Iſrael.</hi> And as ignorance of the ſtory of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, deceiued you here: ſo in the next the ignorance of the tongue abuſeth you. For 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 2. 18. that which you turne out of the Hebrewe, hee begat <hi>Azubah</hi> his wife and <hi>Ierioth:</hi> is falſlie and ignorantlie tranſlated. For ETH the particle, there is not a note of the accuſatiue caſe: but is a praepoſition, and ſignifieth that he begate of <hi>Azu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah</hi> his wife, &amp;c. as is confirmed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, vvhere it is ſo taken. As<note place="margin">Gen. 44. 4 Ezech. 6. 9</note> for that out of 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 24. 19. of putting <hi>brother</hi> for vncle, it argueth you vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnacquainted with the Scriptures in any tongue, ſeing the word brother is generall for all kinſmen both in the olde and new Teſtament. Wherupon<note place="margin">Geneſ. 13 Matth. 12. 16. 47</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> is called <hi>Lots</hi> brother, as your vulgar printed by <hi>Plantine</hi> 1576. himſelfe readeth; and ſo our Sauiour
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:8106:61"/> Chriſt is ſaide to haue brethren. Whereupon it is euident, howe free the Hebrew is from corruption: when th'obiections againſt it are ſo friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as nothing can be more. And as this is eaſy to conceiue of al that know the Church (which vnto that tyme was alvvaies ſealed amongſt them) to be the piller of truth: ſo it ſhall much<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3</note> more be ſetled firmely in their breaſt, if the Iewes carefull minde and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of keeping the Hebrewe text fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence the time of their falling away, be conſidered. Which appeareth not onelie in that the greateſt teſtimonies vvritten by th'Apoſt. &amp; Euangeliſtes (for the proof of Ieſus to be the Chriſt doe remaine as they vvere alledged: but alſo by the teſtimony of th'aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers 400. yeares after Chriſt,<note place="margin">Hieron. in 6. cap. Eſ. Auguſt. de ciuita. Dei lib. 15, c. 13 Hier. epiſt. 74. ad Mar cel. Look in his epiſtle of di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</note> vvhich beare vvitneſſe to their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie heerein. Your owne men are nowe as much aſhamed of you in this charge of th'Ebrewe Text, as <hi>Ierome</hi> vvas of ſome in his time, charging the Hebrew as you doe. Look <hi>Arias Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> vvhich defendeth the Ievves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:8106:62"/> in this behalfe. Looke <hi>Lucas</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Franciſ. lu eae Burg. an not at in ſa era Biblia. Looke alſo his epiſt. ad Cardinal. Sirlet.</note> 
                  <hi>Burgenſis,</hi> hovv he defendeth the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew againſt the vulgar Latin, where he cannot reconcile them. Read <hi>Iohn Iſaak</hi> a Popiſhe Ievve, againſt <hi>Lindan.</hi> Now let them anſvvere vvhether the Lordes care be not as great to keepe the newe Teſtament, as to keepe the olde: vvhether it be not as great to keep thoſe vvords vvhich he ſpake by his ſonne, as it vvas to keepe thoſe<note place="margin">Hebr. 1.</note> vvhich he ſpake by his ſeruants. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, whether he keepeth not his wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, as ſafelie by the Church, which is his friend, as hee keepeth it by the ſynagogue vvhich is his enemie. Laſt of al, let the good reader vnderſtand, that this Popiſh allegation, is a verie haereticall practiſe, and ſhameleſſe ſhift of the deceauers of Gods people.<note place="margin">Hieron. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Hel. bidium Hieron.</note> For thus <hi>Ierome</hi> chargeth <hi>Helbidius, that he quarrelled with the truth of the copies, &amp; did moſt fooliſhly perſwade himſelfe, that the Greeke bookes were falſified.</hi> The like pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe vſed the monſtrous hereſie of the<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Hieron. epiſt. 19</note> 
                  <hi>Manichees,</hi> of vvhome <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vvry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus. <hi>The Manichees not able to wreſt
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:8106:62"/> many places of the holie Scripture, whereby they are moſte euidentlie conuinced; affirme the ſame to be falſe: yet ſo, that they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the ſame not to the Apoſtles which wrot them, but I knowe not to what other, which afterward corrupted them. Which becauſe they cannot proue, neither by the moſt copies, nor by the moſt auncient, nor by th'authority of the former tongue (from which the Latine bookes were tranſlated) they are confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp;c.</hi> We may be bolde therefore to range you vnder the banner of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes, vvhich beare their proper marke and recogniſance.</p>
               <p>But let vs come to the particular places, ſuppoſed to be corrupted. Wherein let the reader obſerue, firſt that to diſcredite nombers of the Greek Copies, reading as we do, they bring but th'authoritie of one only Doctor. For although in the third place they alledge the corruption, from the <hi>Tripartite ſtorie</hi> and <hi>Socrates:</hi> yet it being known, that the tripartite ſtory gathereth that which he writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of <hi>Socrates:</hi> vnder two authors there is but one authoritie. Which
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:8106:63"/> may alſo be ſaid of the ſecond places, where th' authors alledged ar not eye witneſſes, but hang al of the report of th' olde tranſlator. And if in Gods law, the witnes of one man is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to take away a mans life: much leſſe may one mans witnes take away the life and authoritie of Gods word, which (without that witnes) ſhould vndoutedly be ſo taken. And if we ſhould weigh th' olde tranſlator with ſuch weightes; we might with far more right, daſh out a great part of your tranſlator, in th' olde Teſtament: Euen ſo much as he differeth and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ire. lib. 3 cap. 25 Tertul. apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>log. c. 18. 19 H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. pſal. 2 Auguſt de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iuit. Dei lib. 15. c.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> in from the 70. interpreters. For there is a great conſent of th' old fathers, that the interpretation of the 70. interpreters in greek was written by the ſame ſpirit wherewith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets wrote in Hebrew. Secondly it is to be obſerued that in proouing the Greeke copies in three places to be corrupted, by the Greeke heretikes: they alledg for two of thoſe places La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tine writers and Latine tranſlators, ſuch as were vſed in the Latin
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:8106:63"/> Church: ſo that if the teſtimonies proue any thing of the corruption of th' originall; it proueth it more againſt the Latine, then againſt the Greeke Church. For notwithſtanding that <hi>Marcion</hi> were Greek born: yet was not his hereſie begoten in Greece, but in Rome, after that his father (being a Biſhop) had for his lewd behauiour caſt him out of the Church, in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrie. And ſeeing Rome tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon her, to be the piller of truth, and the Lords librarie: whatſoeuer can be proued of the corruption of th' originall, ſhall by their owne doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine returne to the further diſcredite of the Latine, then of the Greeke Church. Now touching the firſt exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Marcions</hi> corruption: you doe belie <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and that in two ſortes. For firſt <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaieth not, that the truth is as it is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vulgar. For <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> himſelfe readeth otherwiſe then the vulgar, after this ſort. <hi>The firſt man</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> carn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> 
                  <hi>of th' earth earthy, that is ſlimie, which is Adam. The ſecond man is from heauen, that is the word of God, which is Chriſt,</hi> leauing
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:8106:64"/> out heauenly, which the vulgare hath<note place="margin">Cyprian de zelo &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos &amp; a. libi.</note> and you ſtriue for. And ſo his ſcholler <hi>Cyprian</hi> readeth. Secondly you falſifye him, for that he doth not ſay (as you ſuppoſe of him) that the <hi>Greek text which is now, is Marcions corruption.</hi> For ſo ſhould he haue accuſed himſelfe, aſwell as <hi>Marcion:</hi> conſidering that himſelf alſo departeth from that which is in the vulgar. Indeed <hi>Marcion</hi> had corrupted the place, by leauing out (<hi>man</hi>) in the ſecond place; therby to help his haereſie of th' untruth of Chriſts manhood. It may alſo be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, that <hi>Tertullian</hi> liked not the word <hi>Lord;</hi> but eſteemed it, a corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Marcion.</hi> This is therefore novv the queſtion, vvhether <hi>Lord</hi> in that place, be the true or heretical reading Firſt therefore let them ſhevv vs, hovv this reading doth maintayn (in any ſort) the hereſie of <hi>Marcion:</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that the Greek hath (vvith full conſent) the ſecond man, which <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> left out, vvherby the humanity of Chriſt is plainly eſtabliſhed. And it appeareth that the vulgar tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlation,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:8106:64"/> hath more coulour of that hereſie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Greek reading. For he might haue eaſier abuſed the vulgare, to proue that Chriſt broght his fleſh from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; then he can do the Greek. And as the Greek reading is further from the hereſie of <hi>Marcion,</hi> then the vulgar: ſo it is (in diuers reſpects) more proper; both for the generall analogie of the true doctrine of the perſon of Chriſt, and for the circumſtance of that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular place. For firſt the Greek rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, containeth a notable teſtimony of the two natures of our Sauiour Chriſt, in th' unitie of one perſon; which the vulgar doth not ſo manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly expreſſe. Secondly th' oppoſition of <hi>Adam</hi> from th' earth, and of Chriſt the Lord from heauen: is much fuller and liuelier: conſidering that he might haue bene both from heauen and heauenly, and yet haue bene but a naked creature as th' Angels. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Greeke copies did not ſhunne the word heauenly, which <hi>Marcion</hi> is ſuppoſed to haue of purpoſe avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: conſidering that they call Chriſt
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:8106:65"/> heauenly. For in the next two verſes the Greek copies (with full conſent) apply the word heauenly vnto Chriſt. Therfore the Greeke copies ſhunned not this worde heauenly in ſpeaking of Chriſt: but reſerued it vnto a fitter place. For hauing in the former verſe called Chriſt the Lord from heauen: in the verſes following, he might (without danger) call him hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly: whereas if he had not ſent that title of the Lord from heauen before, he might haue bene thought to haue bene called heauenly, in reſpect of the place, he came from, as the firſt man is called earthly in regard of the earth from whence he was taken. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſeing that <hi>Marcion</hi> did corruptly alledg verſe 45, as plainly appeareth by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> which corruption is not in the Greeke: there is no liklie-hood that one of the corruptions of <hi>Marcion</hi> ſhould continew in the Greeke, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th' other. Moreouer the Syrian &amp; Arabian paraphraſis, auncienter then was <hi>Marcions</hi> reading as the Greek co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pies doe: it is euident that either <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:8106:65"/> brought not in this reading (<hi>of the Lord</hi>) or els he brought it in long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was borne. Laſt of all ſeing the Greeke Fathers ſo reade, <note n="a" place="margin">Lib. de orthod. fide cap. 3</note> 
                  <hi>Damaſcene</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> locu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome, Theophilact, Oecumenius,</hi> al which deteſted the haereſy of <hi>Marcion:</hi> either this is no corruption, or elſe theſe learned mens noſes were ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed, which coulde neuer ſmell the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of any <hi>Marcioniſine.</hi> And althogh diuerſe ancient and other writers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtoming themſelues to the reading of the vulgare tranſlation, followed it in this point, becauſe there is no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt repugnance in it, to any article of faith: yet that is no let, but that this may bee (as indeede it is) the trueth, which is found in Greek copies, and not that which is in th' old tranſlator.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place <hi>Ierome</hi> alone is brought to diſcredite ſo many Greek copies. Againſt whome (beſide the great conſent of the Greeke copies)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil. lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> we oppoſe the Syrian &amp; Arabian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſis, <hi>Chryſoſtom, Theophilact, Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Baſile,</hi> who thriſe in one book doth ſo alledge it, as the copies ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:8106:66"/> to be falſified. And laſt of al, wee oppoſe <hi>Ierome</hi> himſelfe: who for once alledging it thus for his benefite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">Hieron. ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſus Hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bidium<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; ad Euſtoch de ſeruand. virginita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te.</note> his aduerſarie in that booke, where the Papiſts themſelues cannot denie, but he abuſed diuerſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of th' Apoſtle ſhamefullie, alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it twiſe as it is in the Greek copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, which they condemne. Let al men therefore iudge what a worthie proof this is, broght from <hi>Ierome</hi> to diſcredit theſe copies, which is contraried of ſo manie, and of himſelfe: who after he was departed from his heate of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to ſet downe what was more aggreable to the truth, then what ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued beſt againſt his aduerſarie, ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth as we reade. Beſide all this, ſome<note place="margin">Beza anno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tat. in hunc locum.</note> Greeke copies read as th' old tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor doth. And therfore it is falſe which they ſay, that <hi>it is not in the Greeke.</hi> The <hi>third</hi> pretended <hi>corruption,</hi> ſtandeth on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly vpon <hi>Socrates</hi> teſtimonie; who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that in the Greeke copies to be an haereticall corruption. Howe ſo? What one word is there in the Greek copies, that leaneth to the <hi>Neſtorian
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:8106:66"/> haereſie?</hi> What light footing thereof can you ſhew? If you can ſhew none, there is no likelie-hoode of haereticall corruption: conſidering that <hi>Neſtorius</hi> voice, differing far more from Saint <hi>Iohns,</hi> then <hi>Iacobs</hi> did from <hi>Eſaus,</hi> might euen of a blinde man haue beene di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned. Secondlie, the Greeke rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, falleth in farre better with the phraſe and circumſtance, then that which <hi>Socrates</hi> commendeth. For in the verſe before Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> hath thus, <hi>Euerie Spirite that confeſſeth Ieſus Chriſt to be come in the fleſhe, is of God.</hi> Wherupon hee inferreth the wordes in queſtion, that <hi>euery spirite that confeſſeth not Ieſus Chriſt to be come in the fleſhe, is not of God.</hi> Where it is euident not only that this doth aptly anſwere in oppoſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the verſe before: but that it keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the frame and phraſe of ſpeach, which is to amplifie, and deeplier to imprint one thing in the memorie of the hearer, by denyall of one propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition directly oppoſite vnto another. As in the 6. verſe of the ſame chap. <hi>He that knoweth God, heareth vs, he that is not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:8106:67"/> of God heareth not vs.</hi> Againe in the 7. verſe, <hi>Whoſoeuer loueth is of God &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God; he that loueth not, knoweth not god.</hi> Likewiſe 1. Epiſt. chap. 5. verſe 10, &amp; verſe 12, &amp;c. Thirdly, it is plaine that he which ſaith that Chriſt came in the fleſhe, condemneth him that diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth Chriſt: ſo that it was to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to change it ſo. Laſte of all, if we would examine your alone witnes in this cace, by the ſame lawe that your companion examineth the double<note place="margin">Copus dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. 1. pag. 154.</note> witneſſe of <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Sozomene,</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Paphnutius</hi> commendation of the miniſters marriage: wee might vtterlie diſ-able him, and throwe him from the bar. Who (to diſcredite the trueth of this ſtorie) ſaieth thus. <hi>The thing dependeth of Socrates and Sozomene, whereof th'one was a Nouatian, th'other greatlie extolled Theodorus whome the fifth Synod condemned.</hi> And a litle before, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth it to haue ben <hi>a tale of th'Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, or of ſome vnchaſte perſons.</hi> Nowe if <hi>Socrates</hi> were not (as your man ſaieth) to beare witnes in the matter of <hi>Paph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius:</hi> howe commeth it that you lift
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:8106:67"/> vp his credite ſo high, as not alone to counteruaile, but to praeuaile againſt ſo full a conſent of the Greek copies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the next ſection.</head>
               <p>The Ieſuites in knocking their heades againſt the originall copies, haue loſte euen the common ſenſe &amp; vnderſtanding of a man. For to proue that we (in many places) haue <hi>left the Greeke to followe the vulgare tranſlation:</hi> they haue not brought ſo much as one place, wherein Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> hath not ſhewed that hee followed better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight, then that which he had of th'old tranſlator. In ſome places manye Greeke copies, in euery place ſome one or other Greeke copie, and that of ſingular note: beſide the Syrian pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſt auncienter then th'old tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator. And if Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> being but one man, was able (by the prouiſion he had made of copies) to warrant his interpretation by one Greeke booke at the leaſt: it is euident, that if it had beene poſsible for him to haue gotten
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:8106:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> all the Greeke copies in his ſtudie; he ſhuld haue bene able to haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it more plentifully. Touching the firſt place <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 1. It is falſe, that ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>M. Beza, or we haue followed the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare,</hi> who tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlateth that place doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie. For his word <hi>former</hi> may aſwell aggree with the copies, which reade the firſt Tabernacle, as with the firſte couenant. And Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> ſheweth that both <hi>Photius</hi> the Greek interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Syrian Paraphraſt, as alſo the Greek copie of <hi>Cleremont</hi> reade as the copie which the vulgar followed. And becauſe both the diſcourſe of the former chapter, and the direction of the verſe next going before, argueth that this word <hi>former</hi> is referred to the couenant. Therefore (for more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) we put couenant in ſmal letter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Which was ſo much more needefull to be done, as certaine readings ioine this word with Tabernacle. And yet becauſe wee are entred into queſtion of this place, wee will not feare to ſet downe what wee thinke in this caſe. Which is that (ſauing ryper iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:8106:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> the conſent of the Greeke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> may well and ought to bee retained: not in proper ſignification, but in a Trope of the part for the whole outward and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall worſhip of God: euen as the writer of the Hebrewes doeth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde vſe it, where he ſaieth, that we<note place="margin">Heb. 13. 10</note> haue an aultar, whereof they haue no authority to eate, which ſerue the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle: that is to ſay, which retaine the ceremoniall worſhip. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 11. they ſay, that <hi>the Greeke hath ſeruing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>me, for ſeruing the Lord.</hi> Wherein they doe nothing but dallie with the truth. For manie Greeke and auncient co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, haue <hi>ſeruing the Lord.</hi> So hath the Greeke Scholiaſt, <hi>Chryſoſtome, Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baſil defi. nit. 6 9</note> and <hi>Baſile.</hi> And the cauſe of this diuerſity Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> noteth to haue the ſhorte writing by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which was taken of ſome for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> where they ſhoulde haue taken it for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 11. 2. they affirm that the greek hath, <hi>the Court within the Temple, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e hauing (and truely) the Court without the Temple.</hi> We anſwere, that that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:8106:69"/> is found in Greek both ſcholiaſt and copie. Wherfore herein we had more certaine guides, then is the olde tranſlator.</p>
               <p>2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 2. 14. we <hi>read (but) as th' old interpreter.</hi> But th' olde tranſlator and we both, read ſo without any word of that ſignification in the Greek: onely to lay open to the reader, that which the ſhort ſpeach of the holy Ghoſt, might haue made harder to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in our language. And therefore this is meere dotage to bring this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to proue that we haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Greek to follow th' olde tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator. And as for vs; we haue put our (but) in a ſmall letter, to note it an addition aboue the wordes which are in Greek, yet needfull to cleare the ſenſe vnto the reader, and to make plain th' Eclipſe that is in the Greeke: wheras the vulgar hath not de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, who hath put it in the ſame let<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter with the text. And beſid that ſome of your copies make no ſupplye of the Eclipſe which is in Greek in thoſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of yours, where there is in any
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:8106:69"/> ſupply, it is fondly made by <hi>niſi;</hi> which is not an aduerſitiue anſwering to our <hi>but,</hi> which you allow of, but a note of exception. And therefore wee haue bettered your tranſlator here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <p>They ſay that in <hi>Iames 5. 12. we haue</hi> left the Greek and followed the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine: which is moſt falſe. For there is ſhewed forth, for warrant of that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, a moſt excellent Greek copie, beſide the <hi>Syrian</hi> paraphraſt tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Greek before the Latine did. Hereby the reader may eaſily vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that where our tranſlations ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with th' olde tranſlator: it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot in following him but through warrant of the Greek copies, which are extant at this day. And that the Thraſonicall Ieſuites <hi>of th' infinite examples,</hi> wherein they would make the world beleeue, that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue forſaken the Greeke to followe the vulgar: are not able to ſhew, ſo much as one poore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the next ſection page</hi> 13.</head>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:8106:70"/>
               <p>Leaſt there ſhould want anie thing, wherein theſe enemies of God and of his word, ſhould not play their parts againſt th' originall Greek: they haue thought good to ſet vpon it with a new accuſation of <hi>ſuperfluitie:</hi> whereof notwithſtanding they cannot bring a worde of reaſon, beſide the bare au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> whoſe naked te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie (without proofe) againſt the Greeke they are content to admitt: which notwithſtanding they vtterlye reiect, when (with good and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall reaſon) it commeth againſt th' old tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlator. But let vs ſee into th' autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. Firſt it is confeſſed of the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, that the Greeke copies read the ſuppoſed ſuperfluities, with full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. And doe they thinke that ſuch a conſent of Greek copies ſhall not be able to weigh downe th' authoritie of the vulgar tranſlation, and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raſmus</hi> allowance of it in this place: where neither vntruth of doctrine nor anie vnſutablenes to that which either go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before or commeth after, is able to bee ſhewed. If you your ſelues
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:8106:70"/> ſhould lay in ballance together, <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> which here maketh for your vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare, and <hi>Valla</hi> that maketh againſt him: we ſuppoſe that vnleſſe your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame pouertie in this caſe drawe you to doe otherwiſe, you would giue the better weight to that ſkale, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you lay <hi>Valla:</hi> as one that dealt not ſo roughly with Monckery and other your pedlary as did <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> And as for the preheminence and authoritie, that all the Greek copies haue before th' old tranſlator (thoſe Papiſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted only which haue made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues driuels &amp; drudges vnto him:) we refuſe no mans weights, nor no mans iudgment. Beſide that to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden the Greeke of this falſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of <hi>ſuperfluitie:</hi> we haue the Syrian paraphraſt, which in this poynt is not ſuperfluous in that being long before the vulgar, he beareth witnes in all theſe pretended <hi>ſuperfluities</hi> vnto our Greeke copies; as vnto thoſe that are moſt auncient. Now as for the place <hi>Math. 6. for thine is the kingdome &amp;c.</hi> If <hi>Eraſmus</hi> had vnderſtood that it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:8106:71"/> out of the booke of Chronicles, written by the pen of the holy Ghoſt: he would (no doubt) haue taken heed howe he had called this concluſion of the Lords praier, <hi>triſles.</hi> For it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth manifeſtly, that this ſentence was borrowed from the Prophete <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Chro. 29 11.</note> with ſome abridgement of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes words: which being then fit to ſet forth the zeale and preſent touche of the loue wherewith hee loued the Lorde, was not ſo fit (without an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract) for that prayer wherein our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſought all ſhortneſſe poſsible. Secondlie, that cannot be <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> without the which we ſhuld not haue had a perfect form of Praier. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer ſtandeth, as well in praiſing of God and thankſgiuing, as in petitions and requeſts to be made vnto him: it is euident that if this concluſion had bene wanting, there had wanted a forme of that prayer, which ſtandeth in praiſe and thankſgiuing. Laſt of all, if to giue a reaſon of that which goeth before be ſuperfluous, then this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion may be ſo. But we ſuppoſe that
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:8106:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> it wil be a ſtrange voice in th'eares of all the learned; to affirme that a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall reaſon giuen of any thing, ſhould be iudged reaſonleſſe, and the coupling vp of the cauſe with the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in their ſurmiſed <hi>ſuperfluitie</hi> of this place. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 6. is charged likewiſe. Where it is no maruel although they iudge the latter propoſition ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: ſeeing they are not able to beare th'enimity of the former, as that which hangeth their blaſphemous opinion of merit; ſo that it can draw no breth vvhen it appeareth. Which becauſe the Apoſt. would be ſure to hang tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowlie, he doubled his coard by a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt oppoſition, frequented often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of the holy ſcriptures. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvith the ſame knife they cut off this branche, that they may lop as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous boughs a nomber of ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Scriptur, eſpecially in S. <hi>Iohn</hi> And theſe men that account Logicall reaſoning ſuperfluous in th'Apoſtle: how wil they bear the holy ghoſts rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorick, in repeating one thing in one place, by variety of words alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:8106:72"/> any variety of ſentence: which is ſo cuſtome-able a thing in the Proph. as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rabbins (for auoyding of tediouſnes) note y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole rule<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> therof in fiue let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And if they wil not giue th'Apoſt. leaue to vſe his Logicke, vvithout reproach of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity: they may (vvith better reaſon) denie the Prophets that figure of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorick, vvhich of all other they moſt delighted in. Laſt of al, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie heere (vpon vvhome they only leane) is not ſo full. For he doth not condemne the place of ſuperfluity but ſuſpecteth it. There follovveth <hi>Mar.</hi> 10. 29. where (with other things) <hi>wiues</hi> being ſpoken of in one verſe, is not vvith them repeated in the next. Whereupon is concluded, that in the former verſe it is a ſuperfluitie. And if it vvere not, for reuerence of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> learning, vve might vvell ſay it vvere a fond concluſion. For vvhy may ther not be aſvvell a defect in the latter verſe, as a ſuperfluitie in the former: and rather a defect heere, then ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:8106:72"/> there; conſidering that in <hi>Luke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 29</note> there is a full agreement of all Greek copies, reading as Saint <hi>Mark</hi> doth in the former verſe. But that this reaſon is neither proofe of <hi>ſuperfluitie</hi> nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: it is manifeſtly ſhevved by a like place. For th'Apoſtle hauing nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and marked out diuerſe giftes &amp; offices in the Church: in the two next<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 28. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> verſes making rehearſall of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, leaueth out two: of which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he might as trulie affirm that which he aſcribeth to th'other as of anie of them whatſoeuer. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a rehearſall the leauing out of ſome thinges ſent before, be an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>ſuperfluitie:</hi> let them thruſt out theſe two ordinarie offices out of the Church; and together with the whole honourable traine of the greeke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, which they will be eaſilie intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto: let them alſo condemn their vulgare tranſlation. Nay more then that, let them condemne (with the greeke) their owne vulgar in this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie place of Saint <hi>Marke:</hi> vvhich ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made mention of <hi>fathers</hi> in the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:8106:73"/> former verſe, maketh no more men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, in the verſe following then of <hi>wiues.</hi> And vvhere they would proue, that by theſe two pricks" in <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Stephanus edition of the new Teſtament in Greeke,</hi> is noted a ſuperfluitie in the greeke: vve know not vvhether vvee ſhould aſcribe it vnto their blockiſhe ignorance, or to their hatefull mallice againſt the truth. For doe they think that <hi>Robert Steuen and Criſpine,</hi> men of great iudgement and learning, both ſo ſenſeles, as to haue put that for the text of the Scripture, vvhich by their note, they vvould diſcredite with the reproach of ſuperfluitie: vvhoſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vvas to ſhevve by thoſe notes, ſome diuerſity of reading in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which they ſo marked: as it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by th'examples heere alledged. In all vvhich Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> declareth, that there is difference amongſt the greeke copies. But yet the difference is not ſuch, but both by the greater number of the greeke copies, and by their antiquitie, manifeſtly confirmed by the Syrian Paraphraſt, and laſtlie
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:8106:73"/> by the good cohaerence &amp; ſute of one ſentence with another: it may eaſilie appear that there is defect in the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare, and no ſuperfluitie in our editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As in <hi>Mar.</hi> 6. 29. hovve aptlie is that threatning added againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers of the Goſpell, <hi>that it ſhall be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier &amp;c.</hi> So in <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 22. the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Baptiſme vvith the death and afflictions of our Sauiour Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, is not only elegant to declare, how they ſhoulde be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with them, as the bodye is plunged in the waters: but alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable exceedinglie, to ſhew that as the perſon baptiſed, lifteth vp his head, after that he hath bine ſowced in the waters: ſo both he and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſhould haue a certaine and moſt aſſured good iſſue, out of all their tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and death it ſelf. Of which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, liuelie ſet forth in this ſimilitude, which was not in the ſimilitude of <hi>drinking the cup:</hi> the Church had bene depriued of, if there had not bene ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſer heades or diligenter hands then your vulgar had. Which being
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:8106:74"/> 
                  <hi>repeated in the 23. verſe</hi> ſhould not haue bene iudged a ſuperfluitie, ſeing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide th'uſe of repetition, to imprint it deeplier in memory, there is a noble increaſe whereby it is declared, that they ſhall aſſuredlie ſuffer with him: that ſo calling them home from their ambitious preaſing after ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ouer their fellowes, they might think to prepare themſelues to trov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the next ſection.</head>
               <p>The Ieſuites taking pleaſure to proue the Lord an euill husband in ſuffering thornes and thiſtles to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grow his moſt ſacred and holy field, of th'originall in the new Teſtament: alledg Maiſter <hi>Beza, which preferreth the reading of th'old tranſlator in ſome places vnto the Greeke copies which hee had.</hi> Wherein firſt mark, that one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> is ſnatched at contrarie to his continuall practiſe, through euerie page in a manner: where he conuinceth th'old tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:8106:74"/> of ſlipps and falles in tranſlating. Secondly, obſerue how fondlie they would conclude that Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> iuſtifieth the vulgar tranſlation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſayeth: that in ſome places his reading is ſounder then the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding which he found in his Greeke copies. Thirdly, it ought not to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by, how ſottiſhly, they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude: that therefore th'old tranſlator is in ſome places purer then the Greek copies, for that he is in ſome places purer then thoſe copies which Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> had. For they might well haue knowne, that as Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> had Greeke copies which <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> had not, whereby he was able to relieue the olde interpreter againſt <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> that charged him to haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Greek: ſo diuers others may haue other copies, which neither Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Beza</hi> nor <hi>Eraſmus</hi> haue come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. And therefore if th'old tranſlator ſhoulde haue anie thing better then the Greek copies, which Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> had: yet thereof ſhould it not follow, that it ſhould be purer then all the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:8106:75"/> Greeke copies. But this is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane minde of the Ieſuites, which would rather put fault in the Greeke copies, then either in the negligence, or inabilitie of tranſlators, to get ſuch a number of copies, as might be able to furniſhe that worke of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation throughly. Now of all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in the new Teſtament that they could chuſe to iuſtifie th'olde tranſlator againſt the Greeke copies: it ſeemeth good vnto them to ſend vs to <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 20. wher we nothing doubt but th'olde tranſlator vſed the ſame Greek copie that we haue in full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. But becauſe there are not 450. yeares vnder the gouernment of the Iudges: he changed the place of the praepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſet it ſo, as th'account of the 450. yeares ſhould be referred vnto the time which was from the birth of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> vnto the time of the Iudges. Wherein as we take his iudgment to be good and ſound: ſo his meanes to ſhew it, needed not to haue bene ſo violent, by carying the praepoſition ſo far from his home: if
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:8106:75"/> (according to the manner of all tongues) he had vnderſtood a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious participle. For (ſauing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and riper iudgement) we would thinke that it may well be thus read. <hi>After theſe thinges</hi> done <hi>in 450. yeares or there-about,</hi> he gaue &amp;c. The like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of ſpeach, we read in another place of the Acts, where it is ſaid, that <hi>Ioſeph ſent for his father Iacob and all his kindred,</hi> ſtanding of 75. perſons. And again <hi>to you the promiſe was made.</hi> And<note place="margin">Act. 7. 14. Act. 2. 39.</note> ſo th'account of the yeares is verie certaine. For adding to the 400. yeares expired at their departure from Egypt, 40. yeares, wherein they were vnder <hi>Moſes</hi> in the deſert, and 7. yeares, wherein they hauing made a great conqueſt of the land, receiued their inheritance by Lot: there riſeth the number of 447. whereto make a round number, as the Scripture doth in diuers other places: the Apoſtle added three yeares. For which cauſe, he ſaith not praeciſely 450. yeares, but about 450. thereby marking out either the defect of the ſame number
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:8106:76"/> of 50. if (ſeuen only yeares of <hi>Ioſue</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken to his account) the reſt of his yeares be gathered to the raigne and gouernment of the Iudges, or the ſurplus of the ſame nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of 50, if the whole gouernment of <hi>Ioſue</hi> (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed in 17. yeares) be numbered. Such al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is the forehead of theſe Ieſuits, that they dare cite <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in this caſe, as if there grew any thing in his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that can giue th'olde tranſlator ſuch an incorruptible nature, as they pretend: whoſe iudgement againſt theſe ſcourgers of the holy Scriptures, hath bene before ſhewed. Who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth alſo in the very chapter by them alledged, <hi>that all Latine bookes whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. de doctr. chr. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ca. 15</note> 
                  <hi>ought to be reformed by the Greeke c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies,</hi> if therefore th'old tranſlation, was ſo highly commended of him, as they ſay; yet it is euident, that he woulde not haue him priuiledged againſt the Greeke in ſuch ſort as he ſhould not (as a ſubiect) appeare before the Greeke copies, as before his lawfull and competent Iudge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:8106:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To the ſixe next ſections page</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>In all theſe ſections the Ieſuites poynts of their ſwordes are ſet againſt themſelues. For if to iuſtifie the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tranſlation they iudge it expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſhewe the aggreement of it, with ſome Greek readings either co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies or fathers that followed their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies: then followeth it that the Greek is of more authority then the Latine; as that whoſe credite dependeth of the good report, which the Greeke will giue of it. Whereof alſo it is brought to paſſe, that in tranſlating the vulgar rather then the Greek; you are like to thoſe ſilly poore men, that hauing not wherwith to buy new out of the marchants ſhop, goe to the huck-ſtars that haue things at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hand. Maiſter <hi>Bezas</hi> reuerence of the Greek copies, which you haue vtterly caſt from you, doth herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: that euen where his iudgment leadeth him otherwiſe, he notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding leaueth the Greek reading, according to the vniforme conſent of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:8106:77"/> the Greeke copies: as <hi>Iam.</hi> 4. 2. where alſo we miſlike not the vulgar for his tranſlation, conſidering that th' Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle (to make th' enuious emulation which followeth more deteſtable)<note place="margin">Matth 5.</note> doth as our Sauiour Chriſt did, in the cace of cruell and vnaduiſed wrath, call it murder: wherein alſo th' Apoſt. doth verie excellentlie expound the commandement of murdering. But in the other place of 1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3. 21. you falſely report Maiſter <hi>Beza,</hi> who cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth th' old interpreter, by a Greek copie of great authoritie; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>correcteth not the Greek.</hi> How ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous they make themſelues and their <hi>Gagneye</hi> in iuſtifying th' olde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter, which maketh it a wonder, that a great deale of fire, ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume a great deale of wood: all men (that haue but their common ſenſe) may eaſily vnderſtand. Howbeit what good choiſe your vulgar hath made of Greek copies, where it hath any that are now extant: it alreadie appeareth manifeſtly by your deepe ſilence; againſt their reaſons which
<pb n="567" facs="tcp:8106:77"/> haue conuinced the frailtie of his iudgment that wayes: and more ſhall in the cenſure of your tranſlation which pretendeth to follow him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the next ſection page</hi> 15.</head>
               <p>Looke for the anſwere in the laſte ſectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of pag. 13. beſide that they deal vnfaithfully heere with M. <hi>Beza.</hi> For although he affirme that th' old inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter might (in ſome places) haue a better copie, then himſelf could come vnto: yet heere he praeferreth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Greeke readings. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede it is moſt fit, for the circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the place. For telling afterward, how often they waſh, namely as often as they had come from any place of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon and ciuill meetings: it agreeth better both with the ſhortneſſe of ſpeach which S. <hi>Mark</hi> (aboue al other) followeth, and with the doting ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition of the Phariſes: to expound this by a diligent and exact waſhing, thereby declaring that they did not only waſh often, but waſhed with great endeuour of rubbing one hand
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:8106:78"/> againſt another: leaſt (happily) anie vncleanneſſe ſhould ſtick vnto them: which ſenſe alſo is confirmed of the Syriack paraphraſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vnto the next ſection.</head>
               <p>If your Latine interpreter be ſo neare driuen, as to borrow his <hi>iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of the <hi>Latine fathers,</hi> which ſeeke themſelues throughout to be iuſtified by the Greeke copies; it is euident, that th' accuſations againſt him, muſt needes cleaue ſtill vnto him; vntill ſuch time as his proctours can get ſome Greeke copies, to cleare him by.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the next ſection.</head>
               <p>And if the multitude of Latine co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, hurt th' authoritie of your vulgar amongeſt the Latine fathers, becauſe (after it was ſet forth) there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other tranſlations abrode in their hands. Why did they hurt it, vnles it were becauſe the fathers eſteemed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tranſlations (in diuers poynts) better then it? for they were neither ſo
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:8106:78"/> proud, nor ſo negligent, as to haue left th' old interpreter in thoſe places, wherein they eſteemed him to haue approached nearer vnto the truth: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſeing your vulgar is ſaid to haue had <hi>Damaſus</hi> the Popes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, to whoſe voyce you woulde beare the world in hand that the fathers gaue no leſſe reuerence, then to an oracle from heauen. If therefore the Latine fathers, forſooke th' old interpreter, when he was freſh and new, and therefore furtheſt from corruption. How much more would they if they were now aliue, in many places let him goe peaking alone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath bene ſo corrupted, as hath bene before declared, and is further euident, by the multitude of Latine copies differing one from another, by<note place="margin">Looke the King of Spaines great Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> far greater diuerſities, then the Greek copies doe: ſo that if it were an impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible thing to make choiſe of the trueth of Greek copies, becauſe of their diuerſitie: it is much more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, to pick out the trueth of the old tranſlation, encombred with ſo
<pb n="570" facs="tcp:8106:79"/> many and great varieties.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Vnto the next ſection page</hi> 16.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus then</hi> we may <hi>ſee,</hi> that all the ſope, niter and ſcouridge, that the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites are able eyther to beg, to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to ſteale, or otherwiſe to come by: are not able to cleanſe the vulgar tranſlation, from the filth of blood, eyther wherein it was firſt conceiued, or which it hath gathered, from ſome hundred yeares by paſſing through ſo manie filthie handes of vnlearned Monkes; from the which the Greeke copies, haue had great freedome and reſt: becauſe vntill a few yeares ago, wherein the Popiſh ſhauelings haue bene ſomewhat wakened, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Goſpell: their vnſkilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the Greek tongue, was ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, that they cauſed it to come into prouerb: <hi>It is Greek, it cannot be red.</hi> yea we doubt not, but it is apparant vnto all indifferency: that it is not only cleanſed from the filth thereof, but that the more they haue laboured to rub and ſkoure it, the fouler it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:8106:79"/> to all that haue not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cloſed their eyes againſt the trueth, which, that it may more euidentlie and without contradiction be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; goe to you Ieſuites, and after a vomit of your dogged ſtomack diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged againſt the Greek copies, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in a continuall vntrueth. Heare the moſt trew and modeſt charge, that ſhall be obiected againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencies of your vulgar tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in one kinde alone. Where, far be it from vs, that we ſhould take a vantage of that which may (proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) be deemed, to haue crept in, by the ſlip either of <hi>pen or print.</hi> For it were not only a poynt of vnfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re folly, in ſuch an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit nomber of foul corruptions, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the mower may (in a manner) fill his arme, labouring in this feild: once ſo much as to ſtoupe after theſe ſlipps, before th'other were cut downe. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (euen in them alſo) the loue that popery is in with error, may eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlye appeare: which counting them ſlippes of pen, haue not yet in
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:8106:80"/> ſo many yeares, &amp; after ſo many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, cauſed them to be amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Wherby they bewray how they dote after lies, which will not farme out that, which (in their vulgar tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) they are conſtrained to confeſſe, to be ſowtage or kitchin-ſtuf: ſo much more intollerable, as ſome of theſe corruptions are blaſphemous: as in ſtead that the greek hath, that Chriſt committed himſelfe vnto him (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God) that iudgeth iuſtly: it hath, that he committed himſelfe to him, that iudgeth vniuſtlie. For we had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lay this fault being ſo groſſe, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the writer then vpon the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. And albeit the Ieſuites retaine it dreaming of a ſenſe to make this inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pretation ſtand: yet it is manifoldlie confuted and cannot be admitted without foule and groſſe error. Yet <hi>Rom.</hi> 12, they haue left th'old tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: which ſaieth <hi>not defending your ſelues,</hi> and followed the Greek with vs, which is not <hi>reuenging</hi> your ſelues. In theſe corruptions of the vulgar, which ſhall be layd forth: let the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:8106:80"/> vnderſtand that they are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced by the general co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of al the Greeke copies which are knowne at this day, by the Syrian Paraphraſt, by their own interlineal, and by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the place in diuers places moſt euident, in other ſome pregnant and apparant ynough, to ſuch as haue any ſingleneſſe of eie to looke vpon them. Amongſt the corruptions that ſtand in addition, let that be for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, which is <hi>Luk. 2. 18. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe thinges ſpoken by the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards.</hi> Where beſide the ſuperfluitie, there is no good ſenſe. Secondly, <hi>Iohn 2. 15. he made as it were a whipp:</hi> where is added <hi>as it were:</hi> which beſide the falſifying the ſtorie, can hardly haue any tollerable vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding. Againe <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 19. if you knowe mee <hi>perhaps</hi> you might know my father. Where perhaps is da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerouſly added, fauoring the hereſy of <hi>Arrius:</hi> conſidering that our Sauiour Chriſt other-where alſo doth praeciſelie affirm, that he that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">Iohn 14.</note> him, ſeeth the father. <hi>Hebrew.</hi> 3. 14. if ye keepe the beginning of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:8106:81"/> firme vnto th'end: where he hath added <hi>his,</hi> not only to th'obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of th'argument of th'Apoſtle, but to inſinuate thereby an aduantage to th'<hi>Arrians,</hi> that chriſt had a beginning of his ſubſtance. And theſe may ſuffice for a taſt of addition. The detractions follow. <hi>Math.</hi> 6. the concluſion of the Lords prayer is wholy left out. <hi>Mark 9. 38. becauſe he followed not vs,</hi> left cleane out. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13. 14. where is left out <hi>which was ſpoken by the prophet Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> Alſo in the ſame chapter, <hi>neyther doe you meditate</hi> left out. 1. <hi>Cor. 4. 4. to my ſelf</hi> left out. Diuers alſo of detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, detract from the trueth which is in controuerſie. <hi>Math.</hi> 17. where it is ſaid <hi>Elias</hi> ſhall come, there is left out, <hi>firſt,</hi> for the maintenance of theirs &amp; the Iewes idle fable of <hi>Elias,</hi> comming a fewe yeares before the worldes end. <hi>Rom. 11. But if it be of workes now it is not of grace: otherwiſe, &amp;c. Heb. 1. 3. by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> left out: which is verie effectual to exclude all mans merites with other meanes whatſoeuer in the matter of our ſaluation, and therefore went to
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:8106:81"/> the heart of their ſinfull ſacrifice: and is prooued that it ought not to be left out, by th'other member of the verſe. Th'alterations are infinite almoſte, &amp; thoſe often of waight. <hi>Math. 1. 20. born in her,</hi> for <hi>begotten in her.</hi> And in the ſame verſe and other-where, in <hi>ſleepe,</hi> for <hi>in dreame. Mark,</hi> 3. 29. Gyltie of <hi>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſinne,</hi> for aeternall iudgement. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 30. when <hi>they had ſaide an hymn,</hi> for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had ſung an hymn. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. 45. ſhalbe <hi>teach-able of God,</hi> for ſhalbe <hi>taught of God. Rom. 1. 13. hatefull vnto God,</hi> for <hi>haters of God. Rom. 14. 5. Let him abound in his owne ſenſe,</hi> for <hi>let him be perſwaded fullie in his owne minde. 1. Cor. 15. 51. we ſhall all indeede riſe againe, but we ſhall not all be changed;</hi> for <hi>we ſhall not all ſleepe, but we ſhall all be changed.</hi> Of<note place="margin">Hieron. Minerio. &amp; Alexan.</note> which reading of the vulgar <hi>Ierome</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth, that there is any warrant in the greeke copies. <hi>Gal,</hi> 3. 1. th'olde hath that that Chriſt was <hi>proſcribed,</hi> which is a law worde, ſignifying a man whoſe ſubſtance (for debt or ſome crime) is ſet to publicke ſeale: where th'Apoſt. ſetteth forth, that Chriſt was (by Saint
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:8106:82"/> 
                  <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching and adminiſtring the Sacraments) ſo pourtraied and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before their eies, as if he had bene crucified amongſt them. <hi>Gal. 4. 7. heir by God,</hi> for <hi>heir by Chriſt:</hi> as both the phraſe of the Scripture, &amp; the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the place conuinceth. And often in aduantage of their Popiſhe doctrine, as <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. for this <hi>the holye Ghoſt ſhal bring to your remembrance, what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer I haue ſaid vnto you,</hi> to further the Churches vn-written verities, it hath <hi>he ſhall ſuggeſt whatſoeuer I ſhal ſay to you.</hi> For the merite of workes. In ſtead of <hi>Epheſians the</hi> 2. God hath created vs vnto good workes, it hath in good workes. And <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. in ſtead of, with ſuch ſacrifices God is <hi>delighted.</hi> It hath is <hi>promerited. Luk.</hi> 10. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt more:</hi> it hath, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou ſhalt <hi>ſupererogate. Luk.</hi> 1. for looked on <hi>the lowe eſtate</hi> of his handmaide: it hath <hi>the humilitie</hi> of his handmaide. And in the ſame place, for had <hi>freely graced,</hi> it hath <hi>full of grace. Collos.</hi> 2. 23. In <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> for in <hi>will wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> therby to make way to th'inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:8106:82"/> of their own braine. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. (For multiplication of ſacraments) in ſtead of a great <hi>myſtery</hi> it hath <hi>ſacrament.</hi> And <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 20. For <hi>this cup is the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> it hath <hi>this is the cup:</hi> thereby to auoyd th'euidence of the figuratiue ſpeach. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 11. Which <hi>cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded,</hi> for which is hard to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded; therby to defend the popiſh opinion of the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Heb. 7. 25. To ſaue for euer,</hi> for <hi>to ſaue wholy or throughout. Heb. 9. 14. By the holy ſpirit,</hi> for <hi>by th'eternall ſpirit,</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of their wicked opinion that our Sauiour Chriſt is high Prieſt only in regard of his humanity, and not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his diuinitie, with numbers of others the iuſt treatiſe whereof would require a whole booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vnto the two next ſections</head>
               <p>Notwithſtanding theſe ſwyniſh Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, tread the pearles of the Greek copies vnder their filthie feete, and that either without anie manner of reaſon at all, or els with ſo ſmall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as will hardly iuſtifie them to be
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:8106:83"/> reſonable creatures: yet can they not beare that Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> ſhould (with great probabilitie and likelyhood of trueth) ſomuch as ſuſpect the Greeke copies. For they are not able to ſhew one only place that he hath correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, contrarie to a whole conſent of the Greeke copies. They may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn without reaſon, he may not ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, with great probabilitie thereof. They may ſet in the text what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them, contrary to th'authority of all the Greek copies: he may not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his opinion in his ſcholies and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations vpon the text. They cannot beare to be charged, with their prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent errour. But he muſt beare the blame of ſlippes &amp; errors, which haue paſt and now are reformed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either their hatred is ſo great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Greeke copies, that they cannot abide Maiſter <hi>Bezas</hi> modeſt and ſhamefaſt reprehenſions of them, vnles he would flatly condemn them, as they doe: or els their equitie is ſo little, that they can ſee a mote in his eie: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they perceaue not the beame
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:8106:83"/> that is in their own. And if the places were ſo manie, wherein <hi>M. Beza pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the Greek to be corrupted, that they would make the reader to wonder:</hi> you haue done verie fooliſhly, which (in the great ſtore you pretend) haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated the moſt places twiſe, and that of <hi>Cainan,</hi> thriſe at the leaſt in this book: bewraying thereby, how (in great want of abilitie of accuſing him iuſtly) the will and deſire to accuſe, was out of all meaſure. Yet ſpeake we not this, as taking vpon vs Maiſter <hi>Bezas</hi> defence, without all exception. For we haue ſhewed <hi>Acts.</hi> 13. how the Greeke copies doe well aggree with the trueth: ſo we hope that the ſame might be performed in other appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances<note place="margin">Look verſ. 14. how Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rome recon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cileth theſe places which the Ieſuites think irr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliable in his quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns vpon Geneſis.</note> of contradiction, euen in the two moſt difficulteſt places of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which are in the 7. of th'Acts. And touching that of the 75. ſoules beſide <hi>Iacob,</hi> it accordeth well with the nomber which <hi>Moyſes</hi> particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reckoneth vp <hi>Genes.</hi> 46. where (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide <hi>Iacob</hi>) are mentioned 75. perſons. Neither doth S. <hi>Steuen</hi> affirme that 75.
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:8106:84"/> perſons came into Egypt: but decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth<note place="margin">Looke Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malius and Iunius in their anno. tat. vppon Geneſ. 46</note> in that number the whole family of <hi>Iacob</hi> was, before he came to Egypt: that when men knew, that it came in ſo manie yeares to no greater a ſumme then to 75. perſons, reckoning alſo the 4. wiues of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and two ſonns of <hi>Iehuda</hi> that were dead: they might the more clearlie ſee the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous and miraculous bleſſing which followed before their departure from Egypt. Th'other place which ſeemeth likwiſe irreco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliable, concerning <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 16.</note> buying of a peece of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at <hi>Sichem</hi> of the ſonns of <hi>Emor:</hi> is as cleare as the ſun at noone dayes: If this place of th'acts be compared with the places of Geneſis 12. 3. 4. and 33. 19. 20. for in the former of theſe places it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that <hi>Abram</hi> had built an altar vnto the Lord in the verie ſelfe ſame place, which <hi>Iacob</hi> (in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter of theſe chapters) is ſaid to haue bought, for 100. peeces of money. Now if <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> would not bury his wife in that land, wherein he was a ſtranger, but in ground bought with his own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney:
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:8106:84"/> much leſſe would he build an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar to ſerue the Lord with, but vpon a purchaſe thereof made. It appeareth therefore, that S. <hi>Steuen</hi> might (with as good right) call it the place which <hi>Abram</hi> bought, as that which <hi>Iacob</hi> bought; both of them hauing bought the place. Neyther can it ſeeme ſtrange vnto anie, that <hi>Iacob</hi> purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame againe, that his grand-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had bought before: if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the fathers were often iniured and depriued of welles and<note place="margin">Geneſ. 26</note> other things that they had gotten, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially amongſt a people, who (in all kinde of impietie and in-iuſtice) were now come almoſt to the top. And that it was Saint <hi>Steuens</hi> meaning, to note out <hi>Abrahams</hi> purchaſe, rather then <hi>Iacobs;</hi> it may partly appear in that he maketh no mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a certain price paid for the ground; which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is twiſe praeciſely made men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of in the purchaſe of <hi>Iacob.</hi> And<note place="margin">Gen. 33. 19 Ioſ. 24. 32.</note> if the places were of that difficultie, that we were not able to cleare them: yet (for our parts) we had rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:8106:85"/> our own ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to charge a full co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of Greek copies, with an vntrueth. And although it ſhould be trew, which Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> ſuſpecteth ſome-where of the Greeke copies: It followeth not, that the trueth or anie part of the trueth, is fallen from the Greek copies: conſidering that the corruptions ſuſpected of him, are not ſuch; but by eyther circumſtance of the place, or conference of other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, the repaire may be made.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, where they aſſigne ſuch contrarietie, betwene the teſtimonies cited according to the 70. interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres in the new Teſtament, and the Hebrew text in th'old; that either we muſt be driuen <hi>in cleauing to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew of th'olde, to forſake the Greeke of the new; or in cleauing to the Greeke in the new forſake the Hebrew in th'old:</hi> they declare themſelues to be verie trifelers, and to abuſe their reader impudently. For they know, that we are able to iuſtify euery place cited out of the 70. by the Apoſtles and Euangeliſts, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:8106:85"/> with the Hebrew, and (in ſome diuerſitie of words) to haue the ſame ſenſe; at the leaſt to haue no ſenſe repugnant, to that in the Hebrewe: which is manifeſt by this, that where the 70. differed in ſenſe, there they leauing the 70. whome they ſo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſlie followed (for ſupport of the Gentiles acquainted therewith) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Hebrew text. And as this is manifeſt by experience, ſo is it obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued<note place="margin">Hieron. pro log. 15. lib. in Eſai.</note> expreſly of <hi>Ierome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the next ſection page</hi> 17.</head>
               <p>Doubt not (good reader) but the Ieſuites are like to bruſte for anger, to vnderſtand that we are ſo well praepared, to proue both that the princely garments are not worn vpon the Greek originals, for the ſpace of aboue 1500. yeares, wherein they haue paſſed from hand to hand in the horrible deſerte of this wicked world: and that both the bread and apparel of th'olde tranſlator, ſetting out ſome hundreth yeares after it, if euer it were clad and vitailed, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:8106:86"/> paſſable meaſure of a tranſlation: yet that nowe it is ſo patched and ſo peeced, ſo hoary and ſo mouldy, that any man (that asketh counſell of the Lord) may eaſily ſee, that neyther it commeth ſo far as the Ieſuites doe praetend, neither hath foode and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, able to feed or cloth the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren &amp; heires of ſo great a King. And where hauing no more ſhamefaſtnes in their forehead, then they haue haire on their bald pates: they haue taken this boldnes to ſay, that <hi>the Greek is not ſo corrupt as we ſay, although th'olde tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator be leſſe corrupted then the Greek:</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom what may we anſwer better, then that which our Sauiour Chriſt anſwered vnto the Deuill confeſſing him to be y<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſon of God: <hi>hold your peace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 1.</note> For beſide that the truth ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not beare anie praiſe of ſuch foule mouthed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies as theſe be: their praiſe (inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to the Deuils in-trueth) is alwaies to the ſame end that his, that is wholy tending to the deſtruction of the trueth. <hi>The Greeke is not ſo corrupt as we ſay.</hi> O impudency: as if there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:8106:86"/> that hath cald downe the royall value of th'originall Greeke, as you haue done. <hi>Though (in compariſon) we knowe it leſſe ſincere and corrupt, then the vulgar Latine.</hi> O noble commenders of the Greek copies. Could you haue ſet them lower then in placing them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the vulgar? You might aſwel haue ſet the heauens vnder the earth: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the Greek originall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne in heauen, your vulgar ſprung out of the duſt. How doth alſo this aggree, with your owne ſaying: which affirme that you haue forſaken the poynting of the Latine to follow<note place="margin">The laſt page of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> the <hi>poynting</hi> of the <hi>Greeke.</hi> And if the Greeke hath kept the trew poynting, why ſhould it not keepe the trueth of words. And if your Latine haue loſt the trew pointing (without the which he that readeth the Scripture is like him that rideth without a bridle) why ſhould it not rather be ſaid, to haue loſt the trueth of the words and ſenſe, then the Greeke which keepeth the trueth in poynting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:8106:87"/>
               <head>To the next ſection.</head>
               <p>The principall cauſe that hath made you, take armes againſt the<note place="margin">Iohn. 8. 47</note> Greeke copies: is that you are not of God, and therefore cannot abide the wordes of God. Thereupon it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that th'olde tranſlation as it is further from the worde of God, ſmacketh you better then the Greek copies doe. And althogh you may ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner get water out of a flint, then anie reliefe of your cauſe from the Greek copies: yet if it were poſſible, for trueth to helpe to maintaine a lye, it were yet vnpoſſible for you to like of it: &amp; therfore althogh we are aſſured that you had great aduantage out of the vulgar, which is a great cauſe, that maketh you ſtand ſo cloſe vnto it, and no aduantage at all out of the Greeke (as partly hath and further ſhall appeare) yet we know that you haue a further fetch in preferring the handmaide vnto her miſtres: which is thereby to vndermine all authoritie of the holy Scripture, that (it being
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:8106:87"/> ouer-throwen) the Popes decrees might ride on horſeback; which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take breath, as long as th'autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the holy Scripture remaineth. And if it be as you ſay, that the Greek ſerueth your turne better then the vulgar: you beare vs witnes (at vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares) that the ſmall eſtimation which we haue your vulgar in, proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not of anie feare, that we ſtand in, leſt he ſhould hurt our cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the next ſection page</hi> 18.</head>
               <p>It were (doubtles) vnworthie the name of a tranſlation, that ſhould be inferiour to the vulgar. Howbeit we charge not th'old tranſlator of <hi>Popery,</hi> and impute not all the corruptions in the vulgar to the tranſlator: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to th'enemie, which ſowe tares in his field: albeit as (hath bine ſaid) he might ſome-where preiudice the trueth, not thinking of it. As for the teſtimonies both here and in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſection, they are diſcuſſed in their proper places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:8106:88"/>
               <head>To the next ſection.</head>
               <p>We grant they are <hi>word for word at in the Greek.</hi> And therefore vnleſſe we ſhewe that Poperie leaning vpon them, falleth to the ground, and that it is not only ſtaied by them, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed of them. We will willingly confeſſe, our ſelues moſt vnworthie eyther of the defence of ſo good a cauſe, or of the places which we ocupy in the Church of God. In the meane ſeaſon your beggery is too impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent which take that for graunted, wherin you haue bene alwaies (in the face) reſiſted. And if we would trifle out the time, as you doe; we could for fiue or ſix ſentences which you bring, as ſeming to ſmyle vpon you, alledge fiue or ſix hundreth, which doe ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly frowne vpon your Poperie, as at the verie ſight of them it falleth downe dead. If you had any generall councils or anie other auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the weſt part, beſide <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Primaſius</hi> to warrant your phraſes by: we dout not, but you would haue made them ſpeake: which handle the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:8106:88"/> matter ſo cunninglie, that the dumbe in your cauſe, and ſometime thoſe which are eloquent againſt it, are notwithſtanding (for want of others) compelled to ſpeake for it. As for the two fathers alledged: let the reader looke the anſwer in the proper place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the next ſection page</hi> 19.</head>
               <p>As the Philoſopher ſaide of his work, that being ſet forth, it ſhould<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for the hardnes and darknes thereof (as it were) be vn-ſet forth: ſo may it be verified in a good part of the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites tranſlation; that being tranſlated, it remaineth, partly for the ſottiſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition of keeping of words rather then ſenſe, and partly for th'unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie newe fangledneſſe of forraine ſpeach, as it were vn-tranſlated. So is your <hi>tranſlation</hi> as litle <hi>Catholik,</hi> as may be: as that which is ſo proud, ſo ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; diſdainful, that none of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſort, can haue any acquaintance with it: wheras a good tranſlator will endeuour to deliuer to his reader, the
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:8106:89"/> meaning of his author which he tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, with al light &amp; plainnes of ſpeach poſsible. What are the <hi>ſacred words &amp; ſpeaches,</hi> for retaining whereof you are fallen into this ſeruitude? If you had tranſlated the Greek you might bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haue pretended this. For we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the pens of th'Apoſtles and Euangeliſts to haue bene <hi>ſacred:</hi> which we cannot acknowledge, not you cannot ſhew in th'old tranſlator. Vnleſſe your Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſo manie yeares after th'olde tranſlator, was able then to make that ſacred, which had not beene ſo before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To the next ſection.</head>
               <p>But let vs heare their examples. The firſt kinde whereof is, of Hebrew wordes retained in the Greeke text, and by the ſame reaſon to be contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in all tranſlations. But this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment turneth not all together ſo round as you thinke. For it may well be, that theſe wordes of <hi>Amen, and Alleluia &amp;c.</hi> were well knowne by
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:8106:89"/> th'Apoſtles preaching to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in that time. Wherfore th'uſe of them then, when they were well and generallie knowne, was more iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then now, when they are not ſo.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1. 20</note> And for the word <hi>Amen,</hi> firſt we haue th'Apoſtle, which giueth the iuſt weight thereof in a Greeke worde,<note place="margin">Matt. 5. 18</note> whereunto our yea anſwereth. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly th'old tranſlator vſeth it as an indifferent thing, eyther to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate it into Latine, or to let it remaine, as he found it in the Greeke text. Heere therfore the drudgerie of the Ieſuites is manifeſt. For notwithſtanding they eſteeme it not meete, that <hi>Amen</hi> ſhould be tranſlated: yet becauſe the vulgar hath tranſlated it, they haue alſo thoght good to follow him therin Thereby tying themſelues faſter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vulgar, then the vulgar did tye himſelf vnto th'originall. Hovvbeit in retayning of the Hebrevv vvords, vvhich the originall doth vſe, they ſhould (for vs) haue paſſed vvithout blame if by contrarie practiſe of that which they profeſſe, they had not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:8106:90"/> as much from themſelues, as from vs: yet deceiue themſelues in that they think they may keepe <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bana aſwell as we keepe Hoſanna, Raca, Beliall.</hi> For Saint <hi>Luke</hi> hath tranſlated <hi>Corbana, Gazophylacium:</hi> vvhich is in our tongue a treaſurie, and tearmeth<note place="margin">Luk. 21. 4</note> it alſo the <hi>place</hi> of the giftes of God. Which interpretation when none of th'Apoſtles or Euangeliſts giue, in the vvords vvhich we haue retained: it is euident, that they haue not that vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of reteyning this vvhich we haue of thoſe: much leſſe to keep <hi>Paraſceue,</hi> which they ought aſwel to haue tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Engliſh the tongue which they write in, as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> (forſaking the Hebrevv and Syriack vvords) v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the vvord that vvas proper vnto the tongue he vvrote in. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you impudently face dovvne the trueth, vvhen you ſay that <hi>Paraſceue is as ſolemne a word for the ſabaoth euen, as Sabaoth is for the Iewes ſeuenth day.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there more cauſe, to leaue it vn-tranſlated, when we are not able, vvith like ſhortnes of our ſpeach, to
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:8106:90"/> attaine the full ſignification: then to leaue it vnturned, when the ſhortnes of our ſpeach, affordeth a ſentence in a ſmaller compaſſe of wordes then doth th'originall. And if this be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon, to hold the tranſlators hand, becauſe there are <hi>three wordes in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 1. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>the tranſlation of Paraſceue, aboue that which is in the Greeke:</hi> why haue you tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>put to open ſhame.</hi> Naye, howe commeth it to paſſe, that without all warrant of the Greeke, or circumſtance of the place, beyond the mark of the vulgar tranſlation, which you propounde vnto your ſelues, and that in text<note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> letters, you tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>they took order for buriall.</hi> We knowe therefore that your Dirigie groates, and Trentall money, will make you lauiſh and rauill in your tranſlation, as much as your ſeruile minde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth you dumb &amp; mute in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where you might better ſpeake. In the reſt alſo, your compariſons are fooliſh. For if we haue retained certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> words in their originall, becauſe our
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:8106:91"/> ſpeach fitteth them not ſo well: it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not therefore that you might doe that, where it is at hand and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to ſerue the Greeke, or Hebrew word. Or if we haue ſometimes not vſed the benefite and wealth of our tongue: doth it follow therefore, that you may ſo doe? And if we ſeeking to tranſlate all the Greek wordes, haue left ſome vntranſlated, becauſe the Engliſh phraſe either did not afford it vnto vs, or els ſtood at that time far from vs: doth it followe, that you ſhould retain thoſe words in a ſtrange tongue, which our tongue doth afford you, the tranſlation of which, we haue found out vnto your hand, and which hath confirmation, by the common vſe and practiſe of our nation for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie yeares together. Breifly, whereas our people by the grace of God, in knowledge of the worde, through the meanes of a lightſome &amp; plaine tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, haue bene deliuered out of Egypt: in ſteed that you ſhould haue added light where it is wanting, and plained that which is rough: you haue
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:8106:91"/> endeuoured, by your clouddy and hacked ſpeaches to bring in againe all confuſion and ignorance of God, and of his trueth. And if your daintie ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack could not brooke <hi>the feaſt of the ſweete bread;</hi> yet was there no cauſe for you, to accuſe it of <hi>falſhood</hi> ſeing <hi>ſweete bread,</hi> &amp; vnleauened bread (with vs) are all one. The tranſlation alſo prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Geneua, hath <hi>vnleauened bread.</hi> But nothing taſteth you but <hi>Azymes,</hi> and that becauſe the people cannot chaw theſe cruſts of yours, or bones rather, which of purpoſe you ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, that they may departe hungrie from your table. Your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; is falſe, without all manner of proofes, fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of your cruell and vnmercifull iudgement, of throwing all into hell which die without baptiſme: as if they were not planted in the houſe of God, before they be baptized: where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true vſe of baptiſme is towards thoſe, which we vnderſtand either by their own confeſſion, or by the couenant, to be already planted in the houſe of God.
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:8106:92"/> As for the meaning of th' Apoſtle, it is euident: that he would haue none drawne to the miniſtery of the worde which is lately come to the profeſſion of the Goſpell: &amp; therefore your fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie of <hi>a neophyte that hath bene an olde ſcholler</hi> in the ſchoole of Chriſt (for ſo you muſt meane) implieth a manifeſt contradiction, and is all one, as if you ſhould ſay, he is a new olde plant, or a new olde ſcholler. For in thoſe that were not gathered from heatheniſh religion to the fellowſhip of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, before the yeares of diſcretion: the ſame daie that they became true ſchollers, they became true plants, and contrariwiſe. Wherefore to be a <hi>young ſcholler,</hi> is the ſame thing in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as to be a yong plant: where <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophyte,</hi> to a bare Engliſhman is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, no more then <hi>depoſitum, exinanited, exhauſt:</hi> the foolerie and beaſtlines whereof, is euident to all men, ſeing our ſpeach is able to yeeld the iuſt valuation of them. And if <hi>our ſhewing the glad tidings,</hi> be not ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to our nation, much leſſe is your
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:8106:92"/> Euangelizing: which ſcarce one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a hundreth doth vnderſtand. And if you had learned that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt vnder the Goſpell, is not ſet forth ſufficientlye by the Greeke word, without a Trope of <hi>ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necdoche,</hi> or as they call it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> you might eaſilie haue knowen, that the ſame Trope being vnderſtood in our <hi>glade tidings,</hi> would haue reached the Greek word, and whatſoeuer is ſignified by it, ſufficientlye. For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> was a Greeke worde before the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell came into the world: and is vſed of Greek authors, to ſignifie all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of good newes, and nothing els. And therefore the word can properly ſignify no more now, then it did then. But th' Euangeliſt choſe that word e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to note, that where men are deſirous to knowe good tidings they ſhould beſtowe both their eares to vnderſtand this doctrine, which is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worthie of that name. And if our tranſlation liked you not, as you haue tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpell:
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:8106:93"/> ſo you might haue tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Goſpell, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpelling, with more vnderſtanding of our people, and with as full attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſignification of the words vnleſſe you will confeſſe, that you haue fayled in turning <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Goſpell. Laſtly, if ſo much of the <hi>ſignification is loſt,</hi> vnleſſe <hi>it be turned E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelize:</hi> how commeth it, that you, <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 5. haue tranſlated it, <hi>the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is preached.</hi> Heere therefore your drudgerie to th'old interpreter, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine manifeſt, for notwithſtanding you hold it ill turned vnleſſe the Greek word be retayned: yet becauſe th'old tranſlator turneth it otherwiſe; you ſtick not, contrarie to your iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to turn it as he doth: ſo haue you no iudgement of your own, and th'old tranſlators iudgement (who by turning it nowe one way, and nowe another, ſignifieth an indifferency of tranſlation) you vtterly ouerthrowe. But that vvhich follovveth, is more abſurde: that the people muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the naturall tranſlation of
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:8106:93"/> the vvords, through your ſottiſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of keeping of Latin vvords, which the vulgar vſed: vvhich theſe lying ſpirits calling firſt the <hi>Latine text of the Scripture,</hi> after by and by call it, the <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie words of the Scripture:</hi> as if the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tranſlated into the Engliſh tongue, vvere not as much the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as that vvhich is tranſlated into the Latine. For your <hi>poenance,</hi> you muſt do poenance: conſidering that <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. 4. you turne the ſame vvord vvhich you tranſlate <hi>doe poenance, be poenitent.</hi> The ſame vvhip commeth to you, for your <hi>aduent:</hi> which in one and<note place="margin">Mat. 24. 27</note> the ſame chapter and ſenſe, turne it <hi>comming &amp; aduent</hi> both. We are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent you keepe your <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and your <hi>Chalice</hi> to your ſelues. Albeit you greatlye forget your ſelues, vvhich maks your <hi>Prieſt</hi> here, to come of the Latine vvord; vvhom othervvhere,<note place="margin">Vpon Act. 14. 22.</note> you vvoulde faine driue from the Greek.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:8106:94"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To the next ſection, page</hi> 20.</head>
               <p>We need not trauaile much to lay forth the ſhame of theſe men, vvho themſelues ſhevv their ovvn naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Let their firſt example heere be conſidered: and ſo let all men iudge, vvhether a moſt plain ſentence of the holy Ghoſt, be ſhamefully obſcured: and not obſcured onely, but made ſenſeleſſe. For the Hebrevve phraſe being rendred, it is plaine, that that vvhich they turn <hi>ſpirituals of wickednes,</hi> ought to be turned ſpirituall vvick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes. And if they had any care, that the people ſhould haue bene made vvarie, againſt this ſpirituall crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: they would haue ſaid, in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly places or things, as the text conſidered in the circumſtance would beſt beare, rather then to ſay, <hi>celeſtials.</hi> But it ſhuld appeare that beſide their peeviſh affecting of obſcuritie, th'ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the Hebrevv phraſe in the former part of this ſentence, and th'ignorance of the ſenſe in the latter part: droue them vpon this vvitleſſe
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:8106:94"/> tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſame ignorance of the Hebrevv tongue, cauſed them to vſe ſome like dotage in the next exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. For if they had knovvne, that it is ordinarie and vſuall for the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to vnderſtand the verbe ſubſtantiue: &amp; had further learned, that the verbe ſimple, hath (as the place and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance requireth) the ſignification of the compound: they ſhould eaſilie haue vnderſtood, that this tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>what is betwene me and thee,</hi> had not paſſed the meaſure of a ſimple and plaine tranſlation. The next example doth likevviſe bevvray, their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in all good lavv of tranſlation. For it is vvell knovven to children, that euerie tongue hath a proper compoſition: in ſuch ſort, that he that vvill make the compoſition of one tongue, aggree vvith the compoſition of another, vtterly corrupteth the tongue, vvhich he vvill conform. And is all one as in a body, vvhich is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured and deformed by diſplacing of the ſeuerall members thereof. In Hebrevv he that ſaith, MARA MALE,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:8106:95"/> and not MALE MARA, is eaſily knovvne, not to ſpeake the tongue of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Bread white in our ſpeach woulde offend patient cares, white bread in the French language would be as offenſiue. And if ſo ſmall a change, &amp; as it were the remoouing of a worde to the next houſe, be ſo foule: how much more, is it not to be abidden, that the word, whoſe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall place is in the beginning, ſhould be ſet in th' end: as if it were remoued from one end of the ſtreete to th' o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And if there could be any profite in this dotage: yet haue not you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it. For where the Greeke hath<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 20</note> in one verſe, <hi>a reed bruſed, &amp; flax ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king:</hi> you haue in the former followed th' order of the Greek, and ſay a <hi>reed bruſed;</hi> but in the latter you haue left th' order of the Greek, and kept the naturall order of our ſpeach, ſaying <hi>ſmoaking flax,</hi> not <hi>flax ſmoaking.</hi> And although it be no anſwer heere, to ſay that they followed their olde tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſeing rather they ought to haue followed the ful conſent of the Greek
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:8106:95"/> copies, if ſuch an imitation had bene needfull: yet they are eaſily ſtripped of that anſwere. For ſometimes they leaue the order of th' old interpreter, and follow the Greeke: as <hi>Math.</hi> 4. 4. they ſay as the Greek <hi>bread alone,</hi> and not as the vulgar <hi>alone bread.</hi> Which alſo they doe not in phraſe only, but in whole ſentences: as <hi>Math.</hi> 4. they forſake the vulgar, which ſayeth, <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in darkenes,</hi> and take the Greeke which ſayeth, <hi>ſate in darkenes.</hi> And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. in ſtead of that the vulgar hath, <hi>not defending our ſelues,</hi> they haue cleaued to the Greeke, which is <hi>not reuenging your ſelues.</hi> Neyther can they ſay, that this was the ſlip of a pen of the writer, for beſide that there is no reſemblance of the wordes, they are ſhut from that, in that that <hi>Ierome</hi> ſo readeth. And other ſometime they forſake the order of the Greeke and<note place="margin">Math. 4. 6.</note> vulgar both. For where both the Greek and vulgar haue, <hi>to his Angels ſhal he giue charge of thee:</hi> they haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">Ibid. ver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> it, <hi>he will giue his Angels charge of thee.</hi> And againe, where both Greeke
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:8106:96"/> and Latine haue <hi>into an hill high verie:</hi> they (as it ſhould ſeeme) aſhamed of this their apiſh and ſottiſh imitation, haue tranſlated it, as we doe, <hi>into a very high mountaine.</hi> So it appeareth, that as they are vtterly ignorant of all good order of tranſlation: ſo they keepe not themſelues to their owne crooked rule, but when and where it pleaſeth them. And as they make themſelues ridiculous in the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a ſuperſtitious obſeruation of th' or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of words: ſo are they not only of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ridiculous, but ſometime impious in the ſenſe, which their ſeruile obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of like number of words, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them vnto. Take for example one of the moſt comfortable places in al the ſcripture, which by their ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh tranſlation (in ſparing a worde)<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 33 34.</note> they haue turned into deadly poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and bitter wormwood. For vnto this queſtion, <hi>who ſhall accuſe againſt the elect of God?</hi> They haue added for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>God which iuſtifieth:</hi> as if god ſhuld accuſe his elect. And to another queſtion, <hi>who is he that ſhall condemn?</hi>
                  <pb n="205" facs="tcp:8106:96"/> They ad for anſwer, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp;c.</hi> Cleane contrarie to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and phraſe of th' Apoſtle: alſo contrarie to their meaning; but yet their words can beare no other ſenſe, where th' Apoſtle keeping the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew phraſe, left out the verbe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiue; which being alwaies in that phraſe vnderſtood of it ſelfe, is not ſo in our tongue; vnleſſe it be expreſſed. Now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſe their peruerſe imitation of wordes, is not religious, but ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, and ſometime impious, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time obſerued, and ſometime not, at their pleaſure: it wilbe alſo eaſie, to ſee in diuers examples, that they riot and play the wantons in their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation. Albeit it hath alreadie bene performed, and that in three or foure of thoſe examples, which they haue alledged, to teſtifie their great fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in tranſlating: yet there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whereby the ſame is conuinced.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>prohibebat.</hi>
                  </note> As <hi>Math.</hi> 3. 14. where the Greek hath he vtterly forbade him, and the vul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gar forbad him they leauing both the Greek and the vulgar, tranſlate <hi>ſtaied
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:8106:97"/> him,</hi> and in the ſame chapter verſe they tranſlate <hi>praeſented,</hi> and yet 8. chap. 16. <hi>offered:</hi> th' olde tranſlator ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>obtulerunt,</hi> in both places. <hi>Mark.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> 9. 49. they tranſlate <hi>victimae. Hebr.</hi> 5. 1. they tranſlate <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> and <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 16. they turn <hi>hoſtes:</hi> the word with full conſent of the Greeke copies, being one, and the ſame in all. Ordinarilie they tranſlate <hi>prepuce</hi> and <hi>prepuced:</hi> yet <hi>Act.</hi> 7. 51. they ſay vncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Mark.</hi> 10. 42. they tranſlate <hi>ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> 
                  <hi>them,</hi> contrarie to the meaning of our Sauiour, contrarie to Saint <hi>Luke</hi> which vſeth the verb ſimple, as of the ſame value as the compound, and contrarie to their own vulgar, who vſeth an indifferent word, which hath not ſo great exceſſe of rule adioyned with it: thereby to help the Lordſhip of their clergy. To ſtand vpon the reſt of their examples, whereby they glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in their owne ſhame, would be ſo ſmall profite of the reader: eſpecially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that the places of anie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, are other-where debated, ſome of them being ridiculous as <hi>a
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:8106:97"/> word done, hell of fire &amp;c.</hi> yet can we not paſſe ouer, one open impudent, will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſauſie corruption, which they haue vſed throughout their whole tranſlation: which alwaies in ſtead of <hi>the Lord</hi> haue ſet (and that text-wiſe) <hi>our</hi> Lord, contrarie to the faith both of all the Greeke examples and the vulgar tranſlation: hauing therefore taken from, and put to: you haue all the curſes ſtanding at your doores, which are threatned, againſt falſifyers of the publick recordes of the church: whether they be conſidered as they are in deed, or as they are in your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. For notwithſtanding you haue laide vp the vulgar tranſlation, in the holy ark of the Lord, hurling out from thence th' originall, as it were the two tables, written by the finger of God; when ſuch dealing may ſerue your turne: yet bear you ſo little reuerence vnto it, as that in a matter of ſmall importance, which can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hinder vs, nor help you, you haue put out, and put in at your pleaſure. And although the former fault, may
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:8106:98"/> happily be imputed to your ouerſight yet the latter of adding, vvherein you fall ſo often and continually, can ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue nothing els, but a challenge of maiſterſhip and Rabbiniſme in the Church of Chriſt, and of a chaire ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced ſo high, as that the chaire of our Sauiour, may ſcarce ſeeme to be a foot-ſtoole vnto it. And if you could ſhew but one ſuch boldnes of ours, through-out the tranſlation of the vvhole body of the Bible: vve vvould couer our faces, and our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver ſhould be in ſilence. We ſee ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily vvhat a ſmall gale of vvind, hath driuen you vpon theſe ſands. Only for that vve according to the moſt accuſtomable phraſe of the Scripture, do ſo ſpeake: you haue choſen to<note place="margin">Heb. 7. 14.</note> ſpeake othervviſe then the Scripture, rather then you vvould ſpeak as vve doe. Ywiſſe you ſee it othervviſe in vs; vvhich bank not your phraſe of ſpeaking, vvhereſoeuer the texte of Scripture doth offer it vs. You haue made the vvall of your ſeparation from vs, high othervviſe: and you
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:8106:98"/> might haue made it higher, with much leſſe apparance of your contempt of the worde. Sauing that the Lorde would thus diſcouer you: to a hatefull abhomination of your malapertnes, in handling his worde. Beſide that, as you haue deuided your tongues, from the tongue of the holy Ghoſt; ſo you haue deuided it, from your owne harts. For neyther in deed, nor by your own doctrine, can you ſay <hi>our</hi> God, or our <hi>Lord:</hi> which ſtand in a continuall mammering, whether he be louingly affected towards you or no. You haue preſumed further here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then durſt your good maiſters and betters. For the whole vniuerſitie of <hi>Louaene,</hi> tranſlating the Bible into French, as you doe the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into Engliſh: kept themſelues<note place="margin">Le Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur.</note> herein praeciſely to the old tranſlator, turning the Lord, and not <hi>our Lord.</hi> Where if the weight of authoritie be asked after: the vniuerſitie of <hi>Louane,</hi> is of better mark then the vniuerſitie of <hi>Rhemes:</hi> the Doctors and Diuines of <hi>Louane,</hi> then the Nouices and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioniſts
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:8106:99"/> of <hi>Rhemes:</hi> the whole vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of <hi>Louane</hi> of greater credite, then one ſmall Colledge of the vniuerſitie of <hi>Rhemes.</hi> And if to all theſe we had (for anſwer) only returned; <hi>in ſuch and ſuch places, we tranſlate thus and thus, not as the Ieſuites doe;</hi> as they ſay that <hi>they tranſlate not as the Proteſtants doe:</hi> we feare not, but al indifferent iudgment wil be conſtrained to giue the praehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence of a true and plaine tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto vs, eſpecially in reſpect of theirs. As euen in the next example, where the Greeke word is different, eyther to the holy Ghoſt, or to the wind; foraſmuch as it is moſt euident by vndoubted arguments, that the wind is to be vnderſtood: we holde it for a grace of our tranſlation, which hath appropriated the ſpeach to the meaning of the Scripture. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may iuſtly condemne their tranſlation; which, where one thing is intended and marked out of the Scripture, vſeth that worde, which is common to both ſignifications. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit we know neither generall ſpeach
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:8106:99"/> of the whole land, nor particular lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of any ſeuerall ſhire: where the word <hi>ſpirit,</hi> doth ſignifie wind. So that if it were a vertue for your tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo to hault of both ſides, that the certaine meaning coulde not bee knowne: yet haue you not here, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned vnto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the next ſection, page</hi> 21.</head>
               <p>That the <hi>Greeke</hi> neuer <hi>fauoreth</hi> you, it ſhall euidently appeare, that there is no <hi>corruption</hi> vſed of Maiſter <hi>Beza</hi> in either of theſe verſes: let the reader looke in their ſeuerall places. To the reſt we anſwer nothing: as we doe not vnto the next ſection, nor the next to it. For firſt, it is knowne to all the world, that in both th' Epiſtles to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> &amp; Saint <hi>Iames:</hi> we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the holyeſt and higheſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that can be. Secondly, it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the place, that we keepe the boundes of modeſtie, in abſtaining to name the writter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> whoſe name the holie
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:8106:100"/> Ghoſt hath concealed. Thirdly, not ſticking to name Saint <hi>Iames</hi> Epiſtle in our beſt tranſlations, <hi>Generall:</hi> it is well knowen, that both that title, is not giuen of the holy Ghoſt, but of the ſcholiaſt, which tooke it of <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and is not giuen, for a mark of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther degree of holynes aboue other Epiſtles, but only to note the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of th' other Epiſtles, writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with greater reſtraint of perſon or place. Where theſe latter Epiſtles of Saint <hi>Iames, Peter, Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Iude,</hi> were direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Iewes, ſcattered in diuers countries &amp; prouinces, whither they had bene carried captiue: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are called generall. Beſide that it were good for you, not to be bould with <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the title of <hi>Catholike:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 4. hiſtor. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. c. 22. 23.</note> vnleſſe you will matche Saint <hi>Iames</hi> moſt holy Epiſtle, with the Epiſtles of <hi>Denys</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which <hi>Euſebius</hi> calleth Catholike, as he doth Sainte <hi>Iameſes. Euſebius</hi> therfore was not a fit<note place="margin">Euſeb. 2. lib. hiſt. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 23.</note> author for this: eſpecially, if you had remembred, his raſh iudgement of
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:8106:100"/> Saint <hi>Iameſes</hi> Epiſtle. To the three next ſections, vve anſvvere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>In the laſt, let (hardly) the reader iudge how they <hi>help his vnderſtanding euerie way,</hi> which make plaine places rough, darken that which is lightſom, by diſorder of ſentences, by vnwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted phraſe, by wordes fetched from far countries, which their owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie doeth affoard them off. And finallie, by doubtfull ſpeache, incly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as well to that, which is not the meaning of the Scripture, as to that which is. And the way which is ſo plaine and lightſome, that they can neuer make rough nor dark by their tranſlation: they doe by their <hi>annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> vtterly peruert. And therefore <hi>we comfort our ſelues with this ſaying</hi> of th' Apoſtle, that <hi>you ſhal proceede no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 5. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>for aſmuch as your madnes ſhall be knowne to all men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
